<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great necessity of preparation for death and judgment a sermon preached in the parochial chappel of Macclesfield, in the county palatine of Chester, at the funeral of Mr. John Corker, als Cor Cor, of Hurdesfield, on the eleventh day of November, 1693, and since revised and enlarg'd at the request of the relations of the deceased / by Samuel Corker, als Cor Cor ...</title>
            <author>Corker, Samuel, 1645 or 6-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 253 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34575</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6307</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9062</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11983728</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11983728</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51925</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34575)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51925)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 61:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great necessity of preparation for death and judgment a sermon preached in the parochial chappel of Macclesfield, in the county palatine of Chester, at the funeral of Mr. John Corker, als Cor Cor, of Hurdesfield, on the eleventh day of November, 1693, and since revised and enlarg'd at the request of the relations of the deceased / by Samuel Corker, als Cor Cor ...</title>
                  <author>Corker, Samuel, 1645 or 6-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 93 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Joseph Ray,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Corker, John, d. 1693.</term>
               <term>Death --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51925:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Great Neceſſity of Preparation for Death and Iudgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON Preached in the Parochial Chappel OF MACCLESFIELD, In the County Palatine of CHESTER, AT THE FUNERAL OF Mr. John Corker als Cor Cor of HURDESFIELD, on the Eleventh Day of <hi>November</hi> 1693 and ſince Reviſed and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larg'd at the Requeſt of the Relations of the Deceaſed.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Samuel Corker</hi> als <hi>Cor Cor,</hi> M. A. Rector of <hi>Alderley</hi> in the County aforeſaid; and ſometime a Student in <hi>Trin. Coll.</hi> in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Behold the Bridegroom cometh go ye out to meet him, <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 26.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Be ye therefore ready alſo, for the Son of Man cometh, &amp;c. <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke 12.40.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Veniet, fratres, veniet; ſed vide quomodo te inveaiet. <bibl>
                  <hi>Aug. Ser.</hi> 140. <hi>de Tempore.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>DUBLIN: Printed by Joſeph Ray, 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51925:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51925:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>TO HIS TRULY HONOURED AND MUCH VALUED COUSIN Edward Corker <hi>als</hi> Cor Cor, Eſq; The Authour wiſheth Grace, Mercy, and Peace.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE death of Friends (who were loving and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable in their Lives, and Encouragers of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue) is very piercing and grievous; but moſt of all penſive and afflictive, when they are taken away (as your dear Brother, and my truly loving Kinſman was,) by a ſudden ſurreption, without a foregoing Viſitation and Sickneſs: which ſevere and ſtartling Providence made a very great breach in his Family and Neighbourhood, and a deep impreſſion upon my Thoughts.</p>
            <p>But the Great and Wiſe God, in whoſe Hands our Lives are, hath a Sovereign Right to diſpoſe of, and put a period to them, when and in what manner his Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Wiſdom ſeeth meet; without being accountable to his Creatures for his Actions. Our Duty is humbly to ſubmit to his Holy Will, and with good Old <hi>Eli</hi> to ſay, <hi>It is the Lord, let him do what ſeemeth him good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When Your Affectionate Brother had paid that Debt which We yet owe to God and Nature; His mournful Relict deſired that I would perform the laſt Miniſterial Office for him at his Interment. I had not power to
<pb facs="tcp:51925:3"/>deny her Requeſt, altho at the ſame time I was ſenſible he deſerved a better Orator to commemorate his Vertues.</p>
            <p>The Diſcourſe I then made, and here preſent to You Revis'd and Enlarg'd, is plain, not cloathed with pomp of Words, and tunable Expreſſions, which in Sermons and Books of Divinity, are like Paint laid upon Pearls, which shine beſt in their native luſtre. Flourishes of Wit and fine Phraſes, may tickle Mens Ears, and pleaſe their Fancies, but rarely convince them of the important neceſſity of preparing for Death and Judgment: or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with them to live holily, that they may die happily.</p>
            <p>The Text it ſelf is very momentous, and the ſubject matter of the Comment is ſalubrious, and may claim at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and regard from all Orders and Degrees of Men, who by the eternal and unchangeable Decree of God <hi>muſt once die and appear in Judgment:</hi> But if it meet with unkind entertainment from ſome perſons of corrupt Principles and profligate Lives, who atheiſtically droll upon and ridicule every thing that is ſerious; yet it may be beneficial to others, who are really ſolicitous to know what they muſt do to obtain Salvation, and to inherit Eternal Glory.</p>
            <p>That the God of Mercy and Conſolation would ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and ſweeten to you this sharp and afflictive Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: that he would work in your Soul a cheerful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation to his Holy Will, and enrich you with all the Bleſſings of Heaven and Earth, is the dayly fervent Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt affectionate Relation and very humble Servant,<hi>Samuel Corker</hi> als <hi>Cor Cor.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51925:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached at the FUNERAL, of Mr. <hi>John Corker</hi> of <hi>Hurdes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field, November</hi> the 11th 1693.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Mathew 24.44.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Therefore be ye alſo ready; for in ſuch an Hour as you think not, the Son of Man cometh.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe Words are part of a Sermon, Preached by our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour, to his Diſciples; the Occaſion was this; They were all met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> admiring the Magnificence, Firmneſs, and Statelineſs of it, and highly commending the Beauty, and Order of the Fabrick; which was Adorned
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 21.5.</note> 
               <hi>with goodly Stones,</hi> and ſumptuous Mate rials, ſet off with all the Advantages and Curioſity of Art, Pains and Induſtry; which <hi>Joſephus</hi> calls, <hi>a Work of all that we have ever ſeen, or heard; the moſt Admirable, both for the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Pile, the ſumptuouſneſs of the Edifice, and the Riches of the inward Furniture; in which reſpect,</hi> Tacitus <hi>calls it, a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51925:4"/>Temple of Immenſe Riches,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Immenſae Opu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentiae Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum.</note> ſuitable to the Majeſty of God, who was therein to be Adored and Worſhipped.</p>
            <p>Our Lord, to take off his Diſciples Eyes, from beholding thoſe Gay and Stately Things, with ſo pleaſing Admiration; foretold the Deſtruction of it, and the utter Ruin of the City; that it ſhould come to paſs, according to the Predictions of the Prophets;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 26.18.</note> Zion <hi>(for your ſakes) ſhall be Plowed as a Field, and</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>ſhall become Heaps, and the Mountain of the Houſe</hi> (on which the Temple,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Micah</hi> 3.12.</note> one of the Wonders of the World did ſtand) <hi>as the high places of the Forreſt;</hi> i. e. ſhall be demoliſhed, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo deſolate, that Trees ſhall grow there as in a Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>See ye not all theſe things? Verily, I ſay unto you, there ſhall not be left one Stone upon another, that ſhall not be thrown down;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>de Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le Jud. cap.</hi> 10.</note> which was fulfilled, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> Reports, by the Roman Army, who burnt all of it, that was of combuſtible Nature, expreſly contrary to the command of <hi>Titus Veſpaſian,</hi> who would have ſaved it, but could not reſtrain the fury of his Souldiers, tho' he charged <hi>Liberalis</hi> the Centurion of his Guard, to beat them that would not Obey him, and to drive them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; and the Foundation which the Fire conſumed not, was Ralſed by <hi>Turnus Rufus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the General of the Roman Army there; who at his departure thence, drew a Plow over it as God had ſaid.</p>
            <p>And after this, when <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, out of ſpight, and oppoſition to the Chriſtians, gave all manner of Encouragement to the Jews, to Rebuild their Temple, Re-edifie their Altar, and Reſtore their Sacrifices, and the Solemnities of their Worſhip; and appointed <hi>Alypius</hi> of <hi>Antioch</hi> to over-ſee, and carry on the Work, with all poſſible Briskneſs, and Activity, hoping by that means to evidence to the World, that our Saviour was a falſe Prophet, and an Impoſtor, in pronouncing the final and irrevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Diſſolution of that Church, and State: Heaven was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on a ſudden, to baffle the whole Undertaking, and by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Illuſtrious, and Miraculous Inſtances of God's Diſpleaſure; <hi>Viz.</hi> Violent Hurricanes, dreadful Earthquakes, and Eruptions of Fire, which brake as it were under the Foundation, and ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed upon the Work-men, and Spectators, burnt their Tools and Inſtruments, and made the place inacceſſible, for any ſuch At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts for the future: A more full Relation hereof is given by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51925:4"/>the Learned Dr. <hi>Cave,</hi> from <hi>Socrates, Philoſtorgus, Rufinus, Am.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Life of St.</hi> Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril <hi>of</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. <hi>Sect.</hi> 9th</note> 
               <hi>Marcellinus,</hi> and others, where the Curious may meet with ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>The Aſtoniſhment of this dreadful Relation, impreſſed upon the minds of the Diſciples, ſtruck them with ſilence; till they came from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to the Mount of <hi>Olives,</hi> which afforded a curious Proſpect of the Holy City, about a
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 1.12.</note> Sabbath Days Journey diſtant from it; a Mountain famed in Sacred Scripture, for the frequent Apparitions of Angels, and for being often ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with the Preſence of Chriſt;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 22.39.</note> for hither <hi>He</hi> was wont to retire; here <hi>He</hi> Prayed, and from the ſummit top hereof <hi>He</hi> Aſcended into Heaven; but at this time he ſate down here, either to reſt himſelf, (for he was of like Infirmities with us) or elſe in imitation of the Jewiſh Doctors, who, when they were about to Teach in the Temple, ſate down; teſtifying by that <hi>Geſture,</hi> their great Authority, and the calm compoſure of their Minds.</p>
            <p>Our Lord by this Poſture, giving his Followers a fair oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, of making their Addreſs unto Him. St. <hi>Peter, James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> came and asked him privately,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 13.3.</note> 
               <hi>When ſhall theſe things be? and what ſhall be the Sign of thy coming, and of the end of the World?</hi> For 'tis probable, they did ſuppoſe, that the Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the World ſhould immediately follow the Ruin of the City and Temple, and Deſtruction of the Jewiſh State; and therefore they deſired ſome Prognoſticks, by which they might diſcern its approaching Funeral. <hi>Maſter, what Sign ſhall there be,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 21.7.</note> 
               <hi>when theſe things ſhall come to paſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Lord gave them no certain Sign, from whence they might poſitively conclude the particular time; but he gave them many common Signs, which ſhould portend the Deſtruction of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> and the end of the World; which when they, and others in their ſeveral Generations ſhould ſee them, they might from thence conclude, that the time was at hand; and from which, we alſo may be aſſured, that they are Fore-runners of the near Approach, of the Great Day of Judgment; for it is agreed by Divines, that the Ruin of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> was a Type of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the World; as therefore before the particular Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, upon the Jews, many Deceivers and Seducers did ariſe; ſuch as <hi>Theudas</hi> who boaſted himſelf to be ſome body, ſome
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51925:5"/>great Prophet:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib. Antiq.</hi> 18. c. 1 <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>Judas</hi> alſo of <hi>Galilee,</hi> mentioned by <hi>Joſephus,</hi> and <hi>Sadoc</hi> his Confederate, who Laboured to ſeduce the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and a certain <hi>Aegyptian Magician,</hi> who took upon him to be a Prophet, and coming into the Country of <hi>Judea,</hi> gathered a company of deceivable People to him, to the Number of
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb. Eccl. Hiſt.</hi> l. 2. c. 21. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.9.</note> 30000 and <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorcerer, whom the Antients called,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>—</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Eldeſt Son of the Devil, who gave out, that he was ſome great one,</hi> and pretended to be, <hi>that Divine Being,</hi> who made both the Angelical, and Viſible World; and perſwaded all, from the leaſt to the greateſt, to believe, that he was that <hi>Numen, or Divine Perſon,</hi> who was under one Name, or other, Adored and Worſhipped in every Nation, as the Supream and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Deity; in honour of whom, the Emperour <hi>Claudius</hi> Ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted a Statue, with this Inſcription upon it; <hi>Simoni Deo Sancto, to</hi> Simon <hi>the Holy God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Even ſo in the laſt Ages of the World, there ſhall come ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Deceivers, Evil Men, Lying Spirits, that would Vent their own Idle Fancies, and ſeduce others from the Truth, to their corrupt way. The Truth of this needs no Proof in our Days, for the time is come, when, many that live in the Boſom of the Church,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>will not</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>endure ſound Doctrine,</hi> which tends to promote Holineſs, to recover the Soul from Sin, and teacheth to Order the Life aright: <hi>But after their own Luſts, heap to themſelves Teachers, having itching Ears,</hi> diſpoſed to No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty and Error; <hi>to be Toſſed to and fro (like Ships without Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſt) and carried about with every wind of Doctrine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>by the ſlight of Men and cunning craftineſs, whereby they lie in wait to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.9.</note> 
               <hi>Nullum ſaeculum Religionis feracius, nec pietate Sterilius.</hi> No Age, ever made a greater Profeſſion, and leſs practice, of Chriſtian Vertue. Never was there a more ſplendid ſhew of Religion, and leſs ſincere Love, and ſerious Piety; for if we may without breach of Charity, judge of the Tree by its Fruit, and of Mens Religion, by their Converſation, and Actions; little remains with ſome, but an outward Form; and with too many, nothing but the empty Name, and Title of being Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; for by their Immoral, and Licentious Lives, they may rather paſs for Turks, and Heathens, than for the Diſciples of Chriſt; ſo that, our Saviours Advice, is very ſeaſonable; <hi>beware, look about you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>take heed that ye be not deceived.</hi> Nay, rather
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51925:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>look home, into your hearts, leſt the Old Man of Sin, the great Impoſtor deceive you; and the Son of Man come at that time, when ye are leaſt prepared for his coming.</p>
            <p>In this Chapter, Our Bleſſed Saviour Remarks ſeveral other ſearful Preſages, of the downfal of the Jewiſh State: Such as great Rumours, and Diſcourſes of Wars, which would create panick fears, civil broils, and commotions; Seditions and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections, both in <hi>Judea,</hi> and other Countries; for Nation ſhall riſe againſt Nation, and Kingdom againſt Kingdom, and there ſhall be great Famines and Peſtilences, and Dreadful Earthquakes, in divers places, Perſecutions of the Saints, <hi>who ſhould be delivered to the Synagogues, and into Priſons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 21.12.</note> 
               <hi>and be brought before Kings, and Rulers, for the Name of Chriſt, and be put to Death.</hi> So <hi>Stephen</hi> was Stoned,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 7.29.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were called before the Jewiſh <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> where the Scribes &amp; Elders,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 4.26.</note> 
               <hi>Annas</hi> and <hi>Caiphas</hi> uſed to ſit in Council. <hi>Paul</hi> was brought before <hi>Agrippa</hi> and <hi>Feſtus. James</hi> was killed with the Sword,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 16.23.</note> and afterwards as the Doctrine of the Goſpel ſpread it ſelf,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 12.2.</note> the Profeſſors of it were Perſecuted by the Heathen Powers, with the keeneſt Malice, and put to moſt lingering and tormenting Deaths; and by reaſon of the great ſharpneſs of theſe Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, many would ſtumble and turn Apoſtates, as <hi>Phigellus, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, Hermogenes, Hymeneus,</hi> and <hi>Philetas</hi> did; for Iniquity would abound, and the Love of many, both Parents and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Friends, and Relations, Strangers, and others would grow cold, and the Goſpel ſhould be Preached to all the World; theſe are percurſory Tokens of this great Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>But thoſe, which ſhould immediately precede its coming, were the <hi>Abomination of Deſolation,</hi> ſet up in the Holy Place, the which would be attended with great Tribulation: By which Expoſitors do underſtand the Roman Armies (made up of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Souldiers) beſieging the City of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as once God in his Righteous Judgment, ſuffered the Holy Place to be polluted, by the abominable Armies of <hi>Antiochus,</hi> which made moſt horrid devaſtation: And the <hi>Sign of the Son of Man</hi> in Heaven; what this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is, we cannot certainly tell, tho' there are many conjectures about it: Some conceive it to be a Figure in Heaven of Chriſt on the Croſs, with his Wounds on his Hands and Feet, and the Angels round about him, which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51925:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhould fall out at that time: Others take it to ſignifie ſome ſpecial Prodigy, which ſhould attend that Deſtruction. The Jewiſh Hiſtorian mentions ſeveral;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Bello Jud.</hi> l. 7. c. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Viz.</hi> a Stupendious Comet in the Form of a fiery Sword; which for a year together, did hang over the City of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſ Ecc. Hiſ.</hi> l. 3. c. 8.</note> Meteors in the Air, like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Iron Chariots, and an <hi>Army</hi> in Battle Aray, Marching along the Clouds, and begirting the City, a <hi>Light</hi> about the Altar, and Temple, at the Ninth Hour of the Night; Shining as clearly as Day; a <hi>Voice</hi> in the Inner-Temple, which was heard by the Prieſts, as they were offering Sacrifice, ſaying, <hi>Let us depart hence:</hi> And what was more dreadful than all this, the Cry of one <hi>Jeſus,</hi> the Son of <hi>Ananus,</hi> going about the City when it Flouriſhed in Peace and Riches; ſaying, <hi>A Voice from the Eaſt, a Voice from the Weſt, a Voice from the four Winds, a Voice againſt</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>and the Temple, a Voice againſt all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; Wo, wo, to the Temple, and People.</hi> But the general Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Learned concerning this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is, That thereby is to be underſtood, <hi>Signum Crucis,</hi> the Sign of the Croſs. Such as Eccleſiaſtical Story does Record, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great ſaw in the Air,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 3. c. 28.</note> when he was Marching his Army againſt <hi>Magnentius</hi> the great Enemy of the Church. A Pillar of Light in the Heavens,
<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Signum Crucis hic intelliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, aut Vexillum fidei Victoria triumphantis.</hi> Anſelm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Teſtatur Eccleſia Signum Crucis eſſe Signum filii hominis &amp; Agni.</hi> Cajet.</p>
               </note> appeared to him in the Form of a Croſs, whereon was this Inſcription, expreſt in Letters formed in the Configuration of Stars, <hi>In this overcome,</hi> the ſemblance of which Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, he afterwards wore in his Shields, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Banners, in all his Wars.</p>
            <p>Some ſuch Aſtoniſhing Signs as theſe, ſhall precede the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the World, for thoſe things were written for our Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and they do lively repreſent the Wars and Confuſions, which are at this day abroad in the World, and which ſeem to have a Commiſſion to go through all <hi>Europe,</hi> and all Lands; for there hath of late been very dreadful Earthquakes, in divers Places, which have overturned many Famous Cities, and laid them in heaps of Confuſion; and many thouſands of People, have gone down quick, into the Pit of Deſtruction. We our ſelves have felt the Shocks, and Tremblings of the Land under us; as if God deſigned thereby, to diſplay his Wonderful Power, and to awaken us out of our ſecurity, by ſhaking the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51925:6"/>Pillars of the Earth, upon which we tread, diſtant King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, trembling at the ſame time, notwithſtanding the Vaſt Ocean interpoſed; which wonderful Signatures of Divine diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, <hi>ſhould learn the Inhabitants of the Earth Righteouſneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 26.9.</note> and make the moſt ſecure and profligate Sinners, to take notice of the Brightneſs of his Glorious Power and Wiſdom, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg his terrible Majeſty, to ſtand in awe of him, and to Sin no more, leſt ſomething worſe befall them.</p>
            <p>But, where is the Ancient Zeal, and ſounding of Bowels and Mercies, to indigent and diſtreſſed Objects? The Chriſtian Religion was immediately deſigned, to mollifie, and ſweeten the Nature of Men, to change their Boiſterous and Phariſaical Spirit, into a calm and obliging Temper. It enjoyns them, <hi>to have fervent Charity, to love as Brethren, to be kindly affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, one to another,</hi> and to prove themſelves, to be the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Chriſt, <hi>by loving one another,</hi> as he hath commanded, and as the Primitive Chriſtians did in the firſt Ages of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; when (as <hi>Tertul.</hi> ſaith) it became ſo ſignal, that the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens obſerved it, with this ſpecial Remark; <hi>See how theſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians love one another:</hi> And <hi>Julian</hi> (the profeſſed Enemy of Chriſtianity) teſtified of the
<note n="*" place="margin">For ſo in deriſion he termed <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Galileans,</hi> That by their Charity, they begot the greateſt Admiration of their Religion, in the minds of Men.</p>
            <p>But this Generous, and Excellent Spirit of the Goſpel, ſeems to be loſt in our days; as the
<note n="*" place="margin">Ovid Met. l. 1. Fab. 4.</note> Poet deſcrib'd the Iron Age Malice, Enmity and Ill Will, Strife and Contention, Envy, Hatred and Uncharitableneſs, inveterate prejudices, and ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities, inteſtine heats, and diviſions, hot Perſecutions, and oppreſſions, and all manner of Injuſtice, Covetouſneſs, and Impiety, ſucceed in the Room thereof.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5, 19.</note> There ſeems to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a general Corruption in the Lives, and manners of Men. <hi>The whole World lieth in Wickedneſs;</hi> and if this be a porten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous Sign, we have reaſon to fear that a Storm is coming, and that the end of the World is near approaching.</p>
            <p>But now admit, that there will be no other Antecedents thereof, no Stupendious Comets in the Heavens, no fiery Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teors in the Air, no extraordinary Flaſhes of Lightning, to give us warning of that dreadful hour; <hi>in which the Heavens ſhall paſs away with a great Noiſe, and the Elements melt with ſervent
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51925:7"/>heat, and the Earth with its,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Works that are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſhall be burnt up;</hi> and all thoſe delectable things, in which worldly Men place their Felicity, ſhall be deſtroy'd: Yet there ſhall be heard as was before, in the Temple and City, <hi>a Voice,</hi> but much more Shrill, and Aſtoniſhing, in compariſon of which, the loudeſt clap of Thunder, which was ever heard from the fraction of a Cloud, will be but as the ſound of the Silver Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets under the Law; when the Congregation of <hi>Iſrael</hi> Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled; or as the blowing of the Rams Horns, when the Walls of <hi>Jericho</hi> fell; for it ſhall be ſo loud and vociferous, as to make the Dead in their Graves to hear, and come forth, to meet the Great Judge,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>who will deſcend from Heaven with a ſhout, and with the Voice of the Arch-Angel,</hi> under whoſe Conduct ſhall come all the Angels of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 13.26.27.</note> 
               <hi>with a great ſound of a Trumpet, to gather the Elect from the four Winds, from one End of Heaven to another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as concerning the period of time, when this coming of the Son of Man will be in Power, and great Glory, God the Father hath reſerved it in his own Power, and Pleaſure, and not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed it, either to Men or Angels, that we might not be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curious, in enquiring after it. But this he hath made known concerning it; that it will be at a time, when we leaſt expect it; for as the Univerſal Deluge came upon all the Inhabitants of the Old World; when they were immerſed in their Carnal Delights and Security, and never thought of a change, and ſo were ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized by it. So will the coming of our Lord be; he is his own Herald, and in the Text, proclaimeth the certainty of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but from the uncertainty of the time when, preſſeth his Diſciples to rouze up themſelves, and to ſtand perpetually up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Watch; looking for, and awaiting the coming of the Lord, either by Death, or Judgment, for it is all one in effect, whether he come to us, or we go to him, whether the World endeth to us, or we to it; for when we die, we then part with all our dear Delights, and ſweet enjoyments of this Life, and go to Judgment; for as Death leaves us, Judgment will find us; as ſoon as ever the Soul is ſeparated from the body, it is winged by the holy Angels to the Tribunal of God, to receive its de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>finitive Sentence, to Joy or Miſery, according to its Works done in the body in this Life: So that, we had need to be ever wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51925:7"/>and prepared for that hour: <hi>Therefore be ye alſo ready; for in ſuch an hour as you think not, the Son of Man cometh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Words were ſpoken by our Lord, particularly to his Diſciples, but are of Univerſal concern to all Chriſtians, and do as much belong to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> in our days, as to <hi>Them</hi> in theirs; and therefore I ſhall look upon them with particular Application to our ſelves: they do contain two General Parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. Our Bleſſed Saviours ſeaſonable and ſerious Advice, ſolemnly to prepare our ſelves for Death and Judgment; <hi>Be ye alſo ready.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. A powerful and cogent Motive enforcing this good Advice; <hi>For in ſuch an hour as you think not, the Son of Man cometh.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">I. The firſt thing to be conſidered, is our Saviours ſerious Advice, ſolemnly to prepare our ſelves for Death, and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi>therefore be ye alſo ready,</hi> for this Reaſon, becauſe ye muſt die and come to Judgment, and the time when, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known; <hi>be ye ready,</hi> the Original imports, <hi>ſet in the way;</hi> as all thoſe are, whom God hath ſet in the Path of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85.13.</note> 
               <hi>Righteouſneſs ſhall go before him</hi> (as his Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binger) <hi>and ſhall ſet us in the way of his Steps, i. e.</hi> in the path wherein he walketh, and which he hath preſcribed and appointed us to follow him in. The Vulgar Latine reads it <hi>Parati, made fit.</hi> Now, for as much as this is a long and difficult work, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires many Acts, and Duties, to be performed by us, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and qualifie us to meet our Lord with Joy, and Comfort, I will therefore ſhew,</p>
            <p n="1">i. Wherein this Preparation does chiefly conſiſt.</p>
            <p n="2">ii. Manifeſt the urgent neceſſity hereof, and the many Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations which we lie under, to be always prepared for Death, and Judgment.</p>
            <p n="1">i. My firſt work is to ſhew, wherein this Preparation does chiefly conſiſt; this I ſhall do two ways, Generally, and Particularly.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:51925:8"/>
            <p n="1">1. Generally. This preparation does conſiſt in the conſtant courſe of a Religious, Holy, and Heavenly Converſation, and in the daily practice of Univerſal Purity. (1.) For this end the great and wiſe Creator did make us noble and reaſonable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 5.9.</note> 
               <hi>to walk in the fear of God,</hi> to approve our ſelves by a blameleſs and harmleſs life;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>the Sons of God without rebuke, in the midſt of a perverſe Nation, among whom we</hi> (being enlightned by the Son of Righteouſneſs) <hi>ſhine as lights in the World;</hi> that others may ſee our good works, the beauty and ſplendor of our Gifts and Graces,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> 
               <hi>and glorifie our Father which is in Heaven.</hi> For herein is he glorified, if we bring forth much fruit of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and true Holineſs. Not that it is in our power to add any thing to the eſſential glory of God: but only contribute to the manifeſtation of his Glory and Majeſty.</p>
            <p n="2">(2) This he doth command and require from us as we are his Creatures. When God had choſen the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and had ſeparated them from all Nations, and from all Impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Idolatries, and ſet them apart for himſelf, <hi>a peculiar People, an holy Nation, a choſen Race, a People purchaſed to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by Temptations, by Signs, and by Wonders, and by War, and by a mighty Hand, and by a ſtretched out Arm, and by great Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.34.</note> 
               <hi>according to all that he did in</hi> Aegypt, He charged them thus, <hi>Levit.</hi> 20.7, 8. <hi>Sanctifie your ſelves and be ye holy, for I am the Lord your God, and ye ſhall keep my Statutes and do them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are the Seed of <hi>Faithful Abraham,</hi> Gods peculiar People, his proper portion and poſſeſſion, he hath brought us into a ſtate of Salvation,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>and hath called us with an holy Calling, not according to our works, nor for any merit of ours, but according to his own purpoſe, and grace, which was given us in Chriſt Jeſus, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the world began, and as he that hath called us is holy, ſo ſhould we be holy in all manner of converſation;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>for it is written, be ye ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as I am holy.</hi> Now there is a two fold likeneſs to God in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, <hi>viz.</hi> a conformity to his <hi>nature and will,</hi> in reference to which, we are engaged to crucify the <hi>old man</hi> with his deeds, to mortify the corruption of nature, with all thoſe ſinful affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and actions which flow from it, and to put on the <hi>new man,</hi> which after God is created in righteouſneſs and true holineſs.
<note place="margin">3 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</note> Which is called by St. <hi>Paul the new Creature,</hi> and by St. <hi>Peter,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51925:8"/>the divine Nature,</hi> which conſiſts not in any communication of the divine Eſſence to us, but in our partaking of thoſe divine Qualities, and diſpoſitions of knowledge, righteouſneſs and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, which do expreſs the perfections of God; and in our analogical reſemblance to him in his Attributes of Meekneſs, Humility, Patience, Long ſuffering, Juſtice and Faithfulneſs, Mercy and Charity, Love and Purity; and in our ſincere en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to pleaſe him, to do his Will, and keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which require us <hi>to do juſtly, to love mercy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Micah</hi> 6.8.</note> 
               <hi>and to walk humbly with God.</hi> To love him with all our hearts, and ſoul and ſtrength, and might; to diſcharge all the Duties that we owe to his Divine Majeſty, and to be fervent in ſpirit in his ſervice. To abſtain from all injurious practices againſt our Neighbours, to perform all kind and friendly offices to all men, to bear good will to them, to rejoyce at their happineſs, to pity their miſeries, and commiſerate them in adverſity; to pay all due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to them ſutable to their degree and quality; to ſhew all meekneſs to all men, &amp; candidly &amp; favourably to interpret their words and actions, mildly to reprehend their faults, and ſparing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly relate their miſcarriages, forgiving, and forgetting their greater offences, and conniving at their leſſer injuries, which make no great breach upon our intereſt or reputation; ſtudying by all fair means, as much as lieth in us, <hi>if it be poſſible, to live peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably with all;</hi> tho we we may ſometimes ſail in our purpoſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome men are of ſuch a turbulent, fiery, and malicious ſpirit, and ſuch profeſt enemies to peace, and love, that it is ſcarce <hi>poſſible</hi> to obtain their good-will, or to maintain a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly correſpondence with them.</p>
            <p>In regard to our own perſons, the holy God commands us <hi>to depart from all iniquity, to put away the evil of our doings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 1.16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>to ceaſe to do evil, to learn to do well; to watch and be ſober, to caſt off the works of darkneſs, and to walk as children of the light,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.13.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>honeſtly,</hi> and decently, as becometh thoſe to whom the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous light of the Goſpel hath appeared; ſhunning all thoſe vices of Gluttony and Drunkenneſs, Whoredom and Uncleanneſs, all luſtful and laſcivious dalliances, Strife and Envy, which are a ſtain and blemiſh to our Nature, and to our holy Profeſſion, and to live in the conſtant practice of univerſal Purity,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.24. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.8.</note> which obligeth us <hi>to depart from evil, to cleanſe our hands, and purify
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51925:9"/>our hearts, i. e.</hi> to reform and amend our lives and actions, out thoughts and affections, and through the aſſiſtance of Divine Grace, (which is never wanting to thoſe that endeavour to obey God,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1.</note> and do his Will) <hi>to cleanſe our ſelves from all filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of fleſh and ſpirit. (i. e.)</hi> from all bodily pollutions, ſuch are ſins of Intemperance, Fornication, Uncleanneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in reſpect of which, it becomes the duty of a Chriſtian to learn, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe that holy skill,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>to poſſeſs his veſſel in ſanctification and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour;</hi> for ſuch ſins as theſe are a real diſhonour to the body, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.2. And ſince God hath ſhewed his Art in the curious workmanſhip of it,
<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Os homini ſublîme dedit, coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> tuerj juſſit, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Materiam ſuperabat opus</hi> — Ovid. Met.</p>
               </note> which was not at firſt made without a conſultation of the whole Trinity, after what eminent manner, and majeſtick form they ſhould make it, the rare and admirable ſtructure whereof,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26.</note> being exquiſitely compoſed of Bones, and Muſcles, and Sinews, of Veins, and Arteries, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of members, excellent both for beauty and uſe, filled <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s Royal Soul with ſuch admiration of God's infinite Wiſdom and Power, that when he contemplated his own Body, he prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.14.</note> and ſaid, <hi>I am fearfully and wonderfully made, and curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly wrought,</hi> with various embroidery: and ſince God (I ſay) hath beſtowed ſo much pains and coſt upon the workmanſhip of the Body, and that it is a part of Chriſt's purchaſe, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Soul, is become a member of his, and a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for the Holy Spirit of Purity to reſide and dwell in; it is principally incumbent upon us, to keep it pure and clean, chaſt and holy, and free from all carnal pollutions,</p>
            <p>We ought to have a greater regard to our noble Souls (which are of an heavenly Original) to purify and preſerve them from ſpiritual wickedneſs, from extravagant paſſions, inordinate affections and deſires, from Pride and Covetouſneſs, raſh Anger and Contention, Envy, Hatred, Malice, and all Uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; for theſe Sins and Vices defile our Souls, and make us both afraid to dye, and unfit for judgment: Therefore the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle calls upon us <hi>to perfect holineſs in the fear of the Lord,</hi> and aſſures us <hi>that this is the revealed will of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>even our ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> that we ſhould be holy both in our hearts and lives, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in our thoughts and affections; outwardly in our words and actions, both intenſively and extenſively holy,</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:51925:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="3">3. For this end and purpoſe the Lord of Glory ſent his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Son into the World in great humility, to carry on this work of making us holy by his exemplary and virtuous life, and by his patient and meritorious death,</p>
            <p>Firſt, By his virtuous and exemplary life, he hath given us the moſt illuſtrious pattern in his own perſon in all the parts of holineſs, and ſet us the faireſt copy of the moſt ſublime and perfect virtue. For which cauſe we find him in Scripture dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified with eminent Titles, <hi>as of a Prince and Captain, a Maſter and Guide of holy life and obedience,</hi> he voluntarily undertook to ſubdue our Enemies, and hath encouraged us with a moſt boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful promiſe of a glorious reward, a Crown of Righteouſneſs, to follow his heroick Conduct, in a holy warfare againſt Sin and Satan: to fight manfully under his Banner againſt all the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our Souls; as <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſaith, <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Souldiers did, when his preſence and unparallell'd Gallantry inſpired them with Courage and Valour extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary
<note place="margin">— <hi>Fortis in armis, Caeſareis Labienus erat.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Example hath a great influence and efficacy; for as <hi>Pliny</hi> the younger hath obſerved,
<note place="margin">Melius hominis exemplis docen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, qua imprimis hoc boni ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent, qua approbant, quae prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiunt, fieri poſſe.</note> 
               <hi>Men are better inſtructed by Examples, which have in them chiefly this advantage, that they do prove the things may be done which they enjoyn.</hi> And as <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi> tells <hi>Lucilius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Homines plus Oculis, quàm auribus credunt,</hi> Epiſt, 6.</note> 
               <hi>Men give greater credit to their Eyes than to their Ears;</hi> to what they ſee, than to what they hear.</p>
            <p>The more Eminent any perſons are that give Examples, the more readily are they imitated.
<note place="margin">Et in vulgus manunt exempl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Regent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um.</note> Such as ſit in the Gate; as all uppermoſt in the world have many followers that conform to their manners, and practice. When the King of <hi>Nineveh</hi> put on Sackcloath,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jonah</hi> 3.6.</note> his Courtiers and Citizens complied with the faſhion. When <hi>Conſtantinus Mag.</hi> embraced the Faith of Chriſt, Heathen Superſtition began to creep into holes and corners, and Chriſtianity overſpread the face of the Empire.</p>
            <p>Now our deareſt Lord, being the greateſt, and wiſeſt perſon that ever lived, and his example the moſt perfect and tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that ever was, we ſhould endeavour (if we would live happily, and die comfortably, to conform our practice to his;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51925:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>becauſe he was the moſt exact mirrour of true Goodneſs and Virtue, of general Kindneſs and Charity, Patience and Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedneſs, Meekneſs and Humility; which he moſt lovingly invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth us to imitate him in.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.29.</note> 
               <hi>Learn of me, for I am meek and lowly in heart?</hi> His Patience in bearing the Affronts and Indignities of Sinners, his Contempt of all the Glories of this World, his Self-denial and Submiſſion to the will of God, his unwearied di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in his Service, his Peaceableneſs and Gentleneſs to all men, and readineſs to perform all kind Offices to men, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to their Souls, was written for our Admonition, to influence our practice, and lead us in the paths of Righteouſneſs, and to make us partakers of his Holineſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. Our Bleſſed Lord &amp; Saviour's patient, and meritorious Death, and Sufferings, were primarily intended to work Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs in us. The deſign of his coming in the Fleſh, was not only (as the Socinians ſay) to give us an example of Chriſtian Purity; but to lay down his life for us. We are aſſured of this from his own ſacred lips,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.28.</note> 
               <hi>The Son of Man came not to be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred unto, but to miniſter, and to give his life a ranſom for many;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6.</note> a redemption-price, ſo great and valuable, that there needs no further ſatisfaction to be made for any. St, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>that he gave himſelf a ranſom for all,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an emphatical word denoting the exchange of condition with another, the laying down of ones life to ſave another. And ſo did our deareſt Lord and Saviour,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2, 14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32.</note> he gave himſelf for us, and in our place and ſtead, <hi>that he might redeem us from all iniquity, and purify unto himſelf a peculiar people, zealous of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> good works.</hi> The price which he paid for our Redemption, was his own blood, not a few drops, for then what he ſhed at his Circumciſion, and bitter Agony, <hi>when he ſweat drops of blood,</hi> might have ſufficed, but it was his hearts blood. <hi>Ye were not redeemed with corruptible things, as Silver and Gold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18, 19</note> 
               <hi>from your vain converſation,</hi> (and courſe of life, which is unprofitable for your ſouls, and inſufficient for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and Salvation,) <hi>but with the precious Blood of Chriſt, as of a Lamb without blemiſh, and without ſpot. Precious</hi> in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of Angels and Men, but moſt of all <hi>precious</hi> in regard of the Glory and Dignity, of the Qualifications and Endowments, of the Gifts and Graces of the Perſon that ſhed it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>In whom are hid all the treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledge,</hi> in whoſe mouth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51925:10"/>no guile was ever found, who needed not to offer Sacrifices for his own Sins, being a perſon ſo perfectly holy, harmleſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled: No! it was for us and for our Salvation, that he died, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.25. <hi>He was delivered by the determinate counſel and fore knowledge of God,</hi> for our offences,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2.23.</note> to make full ſatisfaction to his Father for them, and to reconcile us to God. By his own free and ſpontaneous act, <hi>he laid down his life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>and gave himſelf for our Sins:</hi> Not only to take away the Guilt, with all the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and conſequences thereof, <hi>Once in the end of the World hath he appeared to put away Sin,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.26. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19.</note> to the abolition of Sin, <hi>by the Sacrifice of himſelf, by whoſe obedience many are made righteous;</hi> but alſo to eaſe guilty ſouls of the pain and anguiſh of Conſcience, which doth fill them with dreadful fears and terrors, <hi>and a certain fearful looking for of wrath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14.</note> 
               <hi>and fiery indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> The Blood of Chriſt doth purge your Conſcience from dead works, and not only juſtify and abſolve the true penitent Sinner; but alſo meritoriouſly purify the Soul from inherent corruption, and ſanctify it by infuſing holineſs: So that body, ſoul and ſpirit becomes one frame of Holineſs to God, to ſerve him here in the <hi>Beauty of Holineſs,</hi> and to enjoy communion with him in his Ordinances; till he is pleaſed to fit him for the full fruition of himſelf in the <hi>Holy of Holies in Heaven.</hi> This is the effect of Chriſt's Blood which was ſhed, to put a ſilence to the clamours and accuſations of Conſcience, and alſo to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cify the wrath of God for Sin. <hi>Jeſus being the</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>Who delivers us from the wrath to come,</hi> and is now actually delivering us by his prevailing Interceſſion, and the ſupplies of his Grace, enabling us to ſubdue the power of Sin and temptation, and will moſt certainly compleat and perfect our deliverance at his ſecond coming. So that now the penitent Believer may ſafely make that bold challenge which the great St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth; <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of God's Elect?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33</note> 
               <hi>It is God that juſtifieth, and abſolveth them, who is he that condemneth? It is Chriſt that died;</hi> and by his Death hath made a ſufficient at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement to God for all our Sins, and waſhed them away in his Blood, which is a Fountain opened for Sin, and for Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Laver to waſh away the pollution and filth of all our Sins, <hi>and to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſneſs;</hi> he is a propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation for our Sins; and not for ours only,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2, 2.</note> but for the Sins of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51925:11"/>the whole World,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25, 27.</note> 
               <hi>He delivered himſelf up for the Church, that he might ſanctify and cleanſe it, i. e.</hi> Purify all its members from the guilt, filth, and power of Sin; endue them with a principle of Holineſs, and conſecrate them to God <hi>a glorious Church, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having ſpot or wrinkle;</hi> free from the ſmalleſt remainder of ſin and miſery.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>For this purpoſe the Son of God was manifeſt to deſtroy the works of the Devil,</hi> the original word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that he might diſſolve thoſe chains, wherewith Satan holdeth all his Vaſſals in bondage.</p>
            <p n="4">4. So great was the care of our Lord to make men truly good and virtuous, that when he left the World, he ſent the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>the Promiſe of the Father,</hi> to ſuperintend the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the Church,
<note place="margin">Vicarius Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti in Eccleſia.</note> whom <hi>Tertul.</hi> calls <hi>Chriſt's Vicar;</hi> a Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor borrowed from certain Church-Officers, who are ſo deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated as our Civilians ſay,
<note place="margin">Quaſi vice fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentes Recto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> 
               <hi>to attend the Offices of the Church in the Rectors abſence.</hi> To oppoſe the Torrent of Vice and Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, to inſtruct people in the fundamental Principles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to guide, direct, and encourage them in the paths of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and Virtue; and by a continual reſidence upon his Cure, to be ever ready to perform the Duties belonging thereunto. Even ſo the Holy Spirit was ſent to ſupply Chriſt's room in the Church:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 16, 7.</note> 
               <hi>If I go not away, the Comforter will not come unto you; but if I depart, I will ſend him unto you.</hi> He was not to enter upon his Oeconomy or Diſpenſation, till after Chriſt's Aſcenſion, and Glorification, as we learn from <hi>John</hi> 7.39. <hi>The Holy Ghoſt was not yet given, becauſe that Chriſt was not yet glorified.</hi> Princes do liberally beſtow their gifts and favours at the time of their Inauguration;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.9.</note> and the Prince of Peace, being <hi>aſcended up on high,</hi> and triumphing gloriouſly over all his Church's Enemies, poured down a plentiful effuſion of gifts and graces unto men. As St. <hi>Peter</hi> acquaints his Auditors; <hi>That Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the power of God exalted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2.33.</note> 
               <hi>and having received of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the promiſe of the Holy Ghoſt; he hath ſhed forth this, which ye now ſee, and hear.</hi> The deſign and end of his coming, is, as our Saviour ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.8.</note> 
               <hi>To reprove the world of Sin, of Righteouſneſs, and of Judgment.</hi> To convince us of the evil and obliquity of our ways and doings; and reclaim us from Sin and Error, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate us unto God's Image, infuſing holineſs into our ſouls, and giving us a right to eternal Salvation,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>by the waſhing of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51925:11"/>and the renewing of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> changing of our corrupt Natures, creating good Diſpoſitions, and pious Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in us, ſanctifying us with Divine Graces,
<note place="margin">Dr. Bar. Creed.</note> and begetting ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous inclinations in us; <q>reverence towards God, charity to Men, ſobriety and purity as to our Selves, with the reſt of thoſe amiable and heavenly virtues of the Soul, which is the work of Sanctification, leading and governing us in our Actions and Converſations, that we may actually do and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form thoſe things which are acceptable in the ſight of God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the Offices of the Holy Spirit, who is therefore denominated <hi>Holy,</hi> becauſe he is the Author and efficient Cauſe of holineſs in us? and hath the ſpecial Name of Spirit given him, both becauſe of his Spiritual Eſſence, and in regard of his Spiritual diſpenſations; and thoſe Graces which he beſtows up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every faithful Soul, which are heavenly and ſpiritual: for the performance of which,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20.</note> he is to abide with his Church for ever. <hi>Lo! I am with you always even to the end of the world:</hi> to enlighten your Underſtandings, to ſanctifie your Wills &amp; Affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to aſſiſt you in Devotion, to ſtir up in you good Deſires, and to lead you in the way of all truth and obedience to Gods holy Will and Commandments.</p>
            <p n="5">(5) For this purpoſe the great Ordinance of the Goſpel Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry was inſtituted, and perſons in ſacred Orders appointed to make men truly holy: to diſpoſe and fit them for Death and Judgment, Heaven and Happineſs, to teach and tread the way to Glory.</p>
            <p n="1">(1) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to teach the way to Heaven, rightly to cut out to every man his portion, and <hi>to divide the Word of Truth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15.</note> The titles which are given them in Scripture, import the buſineſs they are to perform and do: They are <hi>Miniſters, Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, Embaſſadors,</hi> Miniſters of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.12. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.18, 19, 20. <hi>Acts</hi> 20 18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.9.</note> and Stewards of the myſteries of God, to whom he hath committed the Miniſtry of Reconciliation, the word of Power. They are <hi>Overſeers and Comptrollers</hi> of his Family, <hi>Embaſſadors for Chriſt,</hi> to pray, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech, and court men in their great Lord and Maſters ſtead, to be reconciled to God; <hi>Labourers and Co-operators</hi> with God in the work of Converſion and Edification. <hi>He,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.21, 22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15.</note> the principal Agent. <hi>They,</hi> Officers under him, ordained and ſent by him, and furniſhed with Gifts and Abilities to negotiate his great Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51925:12"/>
               <hi>He made them able Miniſters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.</note> fitted by a ſupervening act and influence of Grace, to diſcharge the truſt which he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in them to the ſouls of men. He ſtrictly charged them to preach <hi>all the counſel of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20.27.</note> whatſoever he requires of any one, in order to eternal bleſſedneſs, even the whole doctrine of Chriſtianity, which teacheth us <hi>to deny all ungodlineſs, &amp;c.</hi> to reprove, rebuke, and exhort with all long ſuffering and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11.</note> and <hi>as knowing the terror of the Lord to perſuade men,</hi> to believe the dreadful comminations and threatnings of God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in his Word,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>againſt all ungodlineſs and unrighteouſneſs of men;</hi> and accordingly to frame their lives innocently, and holy, that at the dreadful day of Judgment, which the Prophet calls <hi>a day of wrath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.15. <hi>He alludes to it in the ruin which he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told ſhould fall upon the Jews by the Chalde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>a day of trouble and diſtreſs, a day of waſting and deſolation, a day of darkneſs and gloomineſs, a day of Clouds, and thick darkneſs;</hi> and the Apoſtle, <hi>a day of terror;</hi> becauſe there will be a very ſtrict ſcrutiny, a narrow ſearch made into the <hi>thoughts, words, and actions</hi> of men, done in the fleſh; nothing but holineſs will then ſtand in any ſtead: therefore the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel are commanded to uſe the moſt prudent and effectual courſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18.</note> 
               <hi>to open mens eyes and to turn them from darkneſs to light, and from the power of Satan unto God that they may re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceive forgiveneſs of ſins, and inheritance among them that are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by faith;</hi> which grace doth purifie the heart from ſin &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, They muſt not connive at, or comply with, the luſts of men, as <hi>Ahabs</hi> Prieſts did; but handle the Word of God ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, with zeal and courage, not fearing the faces of men, in the work of the Lord; who hath charged them at their peril <hi>not to be diſmaid at the preſence and frowns of great men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</hi> 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous ſinners:</hi> yet at the ſame time, when they do ſhew their zeal, againſt their <hi>ſins;</hi> to manifeſt their reverend eſteem, and love of their <hi>perſons;</hi> and tender affection to their <hi>ſouls,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing thoſe that oppoſe themſelves with all gentleneſs, and winning inſinnuations, and reſtoring them in the ſpirit of meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; which is the moſt probable way to enamour them with the love of Vertue, and to ſave their Souls.</p>
            <p n="2">(2) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>To tread the way to heaven, and to walk upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cal.</hi> 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>according to the truth of the Goſpel.</hi> So paſſionately deſirous is God of mens happineſs, that he would have his Miniſters to be <hi>Shining Lights,</hi> as <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt was; ſhewing the power
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51925:12"/>of Godlineſs in their lives, that by their good Converſations, their People might be drawn to imitate them in the practice of all Chriſtian Graces.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.12.</note> St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts his Son <hi>Timothy to be an example of Believers in word, in Converſation, in Charity, in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, in faith, in purity.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>of Believers,</hi> not of moral honeſt men only; but of Gods Jedidians,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>the excellent of the earth,</hi> in whom he delighteth, of thoſe firſt-born Souls,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17.</note> thoſe bright and ſparkling <hi>Jewels</hi> of whom the world is not worthy, thoſe darlings of heaven that are the <hi>Apple</hi> of Gods Eye,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.38. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.9.</note> thoſe precious Sons of <hi>Sion,</hi> who are <hi>the lot of Gods inheritance, and the glory of Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.23.</note> To ſuch noble and vertuous perſons as theſe are the Miniſters of the Goſpel to ſhew themſelves patterns, in Sacerdotal exemplarineſs, and in the habits &amp; exerciſe of grace,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.18.</note> and in holineſs of life, which is a ſhining light that hath influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and powerful operation upon others to excite them to bring glory to God. For this reaſon they are ſtiled, <hi>Preſidents, Shepherds, Guides,</hi> becauſe they are not only to preach Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Sermons, but to live heavenly lives, to adorn the doctrine of God our Saviour, by the purity and luſtre of their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations: For the greateſt part of Mankind are like Sheep,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.24. <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.17.</note> which go rather as they are led then as they are taught. A good Example is greatly influential to Vertue, to provoke unto love and to good works, as a bad one is an occaſion of much harm;
<note place="margin">— faciles imitandis Turpibus &amp; pravis omnes ſumus.</note> we having a great proclivity to follow ill Examples. Thoſe therefore that are to teach others, that are to be the lights of the World, ought <hi>to take heed to themſelves,</hi> that their lives and actions may command a reverence from men,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16.</note> and induce them to conform to their pattern and practice; a holy life being a great advantage to Religion, and the beſt preparation for Death and Judgment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Particularly; The readineſs and preparation I am ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of does conſiſt in the ſeveral acts and duties of the Chriſtian Religion: which muſt be performed by us with all diligence, zeal, and vigour, <hi>viz.</hi> in the ſpeedy ſetling our domeſtick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, and moderating our affections to this world, in making our peace and reconciliation with God, and Men, in doing all the good we can whileſt we live, in keeping Conſcience clear and free from offence; in bearing with patience the troubles we
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51925:13"/>meet with; in living under a conſtant ſenſe of Gods all-ſeeing Eye, and inſpection over us, and poſſeſſing our ſelves with fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent thoughts of Death and Judgment. So that duly to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our ſelves for a bleſſed Eternity, does not conſiſt in one tranſient act, but is to commence as ſoon as we come to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency of reaſon, and underſtanding, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.1. and muſt be carried on, through the ſeveral periods of our lives, till God is pleaſed to diſſolve the vital union between the Soul and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and make a ſeparation between them.</p>
            <p n="1">(1) <hi>The ſpeedy ſettling of our domeſtick concerns, and diſpoſing of our temporal affairs, while we have opportunity to do it deliberate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and adviſedly, with prudence and diſcretion, is one part of this preparation for Death and Judgment.</hi> Death is a debt which we all owe to God and Nature, and which we are ſure to pay whenſoever it pleaſeth the God of Nature to require it from us: But ſince we know not the time when, nor the manner how, we ſhall die and depart this life;
<note place="margin">Omnibus eſt eadem lathi via, non tamen unus eſt vitae cunctis; exitii<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> modus.</note> it is not only wiſdom, but our duty to diſpatch this work; leſt we ſhould be taken away (as experience ſhews us many are) by ſome ſudden caſualty or unexpected ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reption. But ſuppoſe we go off the Stage of this world, delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately and by ſlow degrees, ſome previous ſickneſs or ſenſible decays of Nature, forewarning us of our approaching diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; 'tis not fit then to have the diſpoſition of our ſecular affairs upon our hands, to diſturb and diſquiet our Minds, and to rob us of our precious time, every minute of which muſt be beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the beſt advantage, and to the true intereſt of our Souls: for <hi>what</hi> they are when they leave the body and enter into a ſtate of ſeparation from it, <hi>that</hi> they ſhall be to all eternity; therefore it ſhould be our chiefeſt care to get them waſhed clean in the blood of the immaculate Lamb, from all their impurities, that whatſoever defilements they have contracted during their union with their Bodies, through the luſts of the fleſh within, or the wiles of Satan from without, theſe being purged away; they may appear ſpotleſs before the great Tribunal, and ſtand with exceeding great joy before the Impartial Judge. It is not fit when we come to die, to have the ſettlement of our Eſtates then to take up our laſt moment, which ought to be employed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51925:13"/>in renewing our repentance, and in making our peace with God, and ſolemnly preparing for a comfortable paſſage into the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal world.</p>
            <p>There are very ſew (if any) of us, whoſe outward circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances are ſo mean and low, but that we have ſome of the Gifts of Fortune to diſpoſe of at our death; Some Eſtate more or leſs to bequeath among our Friends and Relations when we leave the World. Thoſe of us that have the faireſt Inheritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the fulleſt Baggs and Barns, can take nothing away with us when we die; but are at the courteſie of our ſurviving Friends for a Shrowd and a Coffin to intomb us in the Earth: For as <hi>Job</hi> ſaid, when the Chaldaean and Sabaean Robbers had taken away all his goods, <hi>Naked came I out of my Mothers womb,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>and naked ſhall I return.</hi> So may we ſay with the Son of <hi>Syrac, As we came forth of our Mothers womb, naked ſhall we return, to go as we came; and ſhall take nothing of our labour, which we may carry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in our hands.</hi> Holy <hi>David</hi> affirms the ſame of the rich man, tho the glory of his Houſe is increaſed, <hi>when he dieth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm</hi> 49.17.</note> 
               <hi>he ſhall carry nothing away; his glory ſhall not deſcend after him;</hi> All his Wealth, and Power, and Grandure ſhall die with him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nudos fudit in lucem— Nudos recepit terra,</hi> Seneca <hi>Epiſt,</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>VVe muſt carry out no more than we brought in;</hi> So that it concerns us to make our Wills with great Juſtice, and Piety; and to take care that they be penn'd with clearneſs, and plain expreſſions, to prevent all Animoſities, and Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances, Wranglings, and Suits of Law amongſt our Children, and Legatees: For we are obliged to provide for the Quiet, Peace and Proſperity of thoſe that are to ſucceed us in our Poſſeſſions, that it may go well with them, when we are dead and gone.</p>
            <p>Now, foraſmuch as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>To every thing there is a ſeaſon, and a time to every purpoſe under Heaven;</hi> The moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and convenient ſeaſon for the diſpatch of this weighty Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, is the day of Health, while we have our wits about us, while our underſtanding is clear, and our memory perfect; and that we can duly conſider which way God may be beſt ſerved by our Bequeſts, Vertue encouraged, and Juſtice may be done to every man, and the Poor in ſome meaſure be provided for, according as God hath enabled us, ever remembring, that what we have,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51925:14"/>comes ſolely from his bounty, who is the Soveraign Lord, and true Proprietor of all that we have. We, but Stewards only, and the Poor his Proxies and Receivers; therefore we muſt not forget them in our Wills: but remember that Precept of <hi>Solomon, With hold not good from them to whom it is due,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.27.</note> 
               <hi>when it is in the power of thy hand to do it:</hi> becauſe ſuch actions are works of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Bounty to the Poor, and acts of Righteouſneſs to God: and they that give nothing at their departure hence,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 16.9.</note> betray their truſt; for the good things of this life are committed to their care and management, upon ſuch conditions and reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that they ſhould uſe them comfortably while they live, and diſpoſe of them wiſely and charitably when they die, leſt they give a bad account of their Stewardſhip, and have reaſon to expect a ſevere ſentence from their Lord:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>For he ſhall have judgment without mercy, who ſhewed no mercy. Deſideravit guttam, qui non dedit micam.</hi> This piece of Wiſdom we may learn from the Example of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who did diſpoſe of his Eſtate among his Children, ſome time before his death, reſerving only the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of it to himſelf during his life. This preparation for death in the day of Sickneſs and Viſitation, is not to be then neglected. 'Tis adviſed by <hi>Jeſus</hi> the Son of <hi>Sirac, My Son, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy ability do good to thy ſelf,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccluſ.</hi> 14.11, 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>and give the Lord his due offering; remember that death will not be long in coming, and that the Covenant of the Grave is not ſhewed unto thee. Do good to thy friend before thou dye: Put not off to thy Will and Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but according to thy ability, ſtretch out thy hand, and give unto the Poor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus in the day of health it is moſt convenient to diſpatch this work; but in the day of Viſitation, and the approaches of Death,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccluſ.</hi> 33.23.</note> 'tis an indiſpenſible duty, not to be neglected. <hi>At the time when thou ſhalt end thy days, and finiſh thy work, diſtribute thine Inheritance.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 48.22. <hi>ch.</hi> 49. 1 <hi>K.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3, 4</note> So did <hi>Jacob</hi> in that prophetical Teſtament of his. And <hi>David</hi> alſo, when his days drew nigh that he ſhould die, he diſpoſed of his Kingdom to his Son <hi>Solomon,</hi> and charged him, ſaying, <hi>I go the way of all the Earth,</hi> (i. e. I die) <hi>be thou ſtrong, and ſhew thy ſelf a man,</hi> (of Wiſdom, Courage, and Conſtancy) <hi>and keep the charge of the Lord thy God, to walk in his ways, and to keep his Statutes, &amp;c. that thou mayeſt proſper in all that thou doeſt, and whitherſoever thou turneſt thy ſelf, that the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51925:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lord may confirm his word which he ſpake concerning me, ſaying. If thy Children take heed to their ways, to walk before me in truth, with all their heart, and with all their ſoul: There ſhall not fail thee a man on the Throne of Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>And when David had finiſhed his charge, he ſlept with his Fathers, and was buried in the City of David.</hi> And after him this was expreſly commanded by God himſelf, to the good King <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> as a preparation for death. <hi>In thoſe days was he ſick unto death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 20.1.</note> 
               <hi>and the Prophet</hi> Eſay <hi>ſaid unto him, Thus ſaith the Lord, Set thine houſe in order, for thou ſhalt die, and not live:</hi> i. e, Make thy Will, and ſettle the Concerns both of thy Family, and thy Kingdom, to prevent all Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Quarrels after thy deceaſe; for thy Diſeaſe is mortal in its kind, if God do not by his power prevent it: therefore diſpoſe of thy temporal Affairs; and as for the ſpiritual Eſtate of thy Family, imitate the example of <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> adviſe, inſtruct,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19,</note> exhort and admoniſh them <hi>to keep the way of the Lord, and to do Juſtice and Judgment.</hi> There are ſome Divines, who give this relation of our Lord and Saviour's laſt Will and Teſtament, that upon the Croſs, a little before he gave up the Ghoſt, he bequeathed his <hi>Soul</hi> into the hands of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; his <hi>holy Mother,</hi> to his beloved Diſciple St. <hi>John; his Body,</hi> to <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea; Paradiſe,</hi> to the penitent Thief that was to die with him; and to his <hi>Crucifiers,</hi> his heartieſt Prayers and Interceſſions.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4.</note> Now <hi>theſe things were written for our learning and inſtruction,</hi> to teach us to imitate them, and to prevent the ill conſequences of inteſtate Eſtates, to ſettle our minds at eaſe, and free from diſturbance, and to put our Souls into a prepared frame and diſpoſition for our departure. Thus, by diſcharging a good Conſcience, we may be ready to meet our Lord, and freely depart in peace.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) <hi>This readineſs doth conſiſt in moderating our love <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this World, and not overvaluing any earthly comfort.</hi> We ſerve a very liberal and bountiful Maſter,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6, 17.</note> 
               <hi>Who gives us richly all things to enjoy,</hi> and with holdeth no good thing from us, but that which would be a temptation and a ſnare unto us: only he hath not allowed us to ſet our affections upon this world, nor any of the enjoyments of it; for this is not our place of reſt and abode. <hi>Whilſt we are at home in the body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>we are abſent from the Lord,</hi> may better be rendred, <hi>Whilſt we converſe or ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journ
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51925:15"/>in the body,</hi> So long as we tabernacle in the fleſh, we are but like the Iſraelites in the Wilderneſs, Strangers, and Sojourners, paſſing to the Heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> detained from the bleſſed Viſion and Fruition of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.14.</note> and the poſſeſſion of that happineſs which makes Heaven. <hi>Here we have no continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing City,</hi> no ſettled abiding place. This notion the wiſer Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens had of this preſent World, who looked upon it as an Inn, not as their home. <hi>Nature having deſigned it to us as a Diverſory to lodge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Commorandi enim natura di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſorum nobis, non habitandi locum dedit.</note> 
               <hi>but not to dwell in.</hi> For it is not a fit place for us, nor can our ſtay in it be very deſirable, becauſe it is fleeting and vaniſhing, full of vanity and vexation; all its ſplendor and glory depends meerly upon our fancy. Our Hiſtorians tell us, that the <hi>Peruvian</hi> Mines of Gold and Silver, their precious Stones and Pearls, were of ſuch low and mean eſteem with thoſe barbarous Indians, that they preferred our trifling Bawbles before them; and made that their valuable Treaſure, which we make little or no account of.</p>
            <p>In the Reign of the Great and Wiſe <hi>Solomon,</hi> Silver, (which is now the adored Idol of the World, and for which men ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture not only their deareſt lives, but even pawn their precious Souls to obtain) was not at all regarded;
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 9.20.</note> 
               <hi>it was not any thing accounted of, it was but as Stones in his days.</hi> This glorious Prince ſurpaſſed all the Kings of the Earth in Riches,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 4.22, 23, 26.</note> and Wiſdom He had the greateſt flow and confluence of this World. <hi>His Proviſions for one day were</hi> 30 <hi>meaſures of fine flower,</hi> 10 <hi>fat Oxen, and</hi> 20 <hi>Oxen out of the Paſtures, beſides Harts and Roe Bucks, and Fallow Deer, and fatted Fowl, he had</hi> 40000 <hi>Stalls of Horſes for Chariots, and</hi> 1200 <hi>Horſemen</hi> for the Guard, and preſervation of his Perſon, for the defence of his people, and for the gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur of his Government; <hi>The yearly income of his Traffick</hi> (be-beſides that which Merchants imported, and the Kings of <hi>Arabia</hi> brought to him) <hi>was ſix hundred and threeſcore and ſix Talents of Gold:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 9.13.</note> 
               <hi>many of his Shields and Targets, and all his Drinking Veſſels were of pure Gold.</hi> He reſolved to gratify himſelf with delicious Meats, and pleaſant Wines; and if it were poſſible for him to arrive at ſatisfaction in this mortal ſtate, he made mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent Works for delight,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.3, 4, 5, 7, 8.</note> and erected ſtately Houſes, and plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Vineyards, and made Gardens of pleaſure, and planted Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51925:15"/>and Trees in them of all kind of Fruits for profit, he gathered himſelf Gold and Silver, vaſt Riches, and the peculiar Treaſures of Kings, and of the Provinces, <hi>i. e.</hi> the moſt valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Jewels and Rarities both of other Princes, and of his own Dominions; he gat him Men ſingers and Women-ſingers, the moſt ſweet and melodious Voices, and all other delightful things, as Muſical Inſtruments of all ſorts; he denied not himſelf any thing that was pleaſing to his Eyes, or grateful to his Senſes, or that his heart deſired, neither was he hindred from the free and comfortable Enjoyment of all his Labours, either by Wars abroad, or Tumults at home, or perſonal Afflictions, or any outward Calamity, or imbittering Occurrents, and he had a heart to uſe, and taſte the ſweetneſs of all his labours, which the eager covetouſneſs of wretched Miſers, will not ſuffer them to do, who reap no more benefit by their Riches, than to look upon them, and to ſay the property thereof is <hi>Mine.</hi> So true is that of the Royal Preacher, <hi>He that loveth Silver,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall not be ſatisfied with Silver; nor he that loveth abundance, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe: When Goods increaſe, they are increaſed that eat them, and what good is there to the Owners thereof, ſaving the beholding them with their Eyes:</hi> Which is a poor benefit indeed, unable to make the Worldling compenſation for his cares of getting, and fears of loſing them, a Priviledge which is common to all others, who may every day ſee more goodly ſights, the radiant luſtre of the Sun, adorned with Light as with a beautiful Garment, and ſmiling upon the Earth with a moſt pleaſant and amiable Countenance, the ſparkling Glories of the heavenly Bodies, in their Conſtellations, the lovely and fragrant Flowers of the Field, the Rarities and Treaſures of Nature, and all the Pomp and Gallantry of Princes and Nobles, all which are more pleaſing ſights to the Beholders. But mark what Character he gives of all outward things, after that he had taken a ſerious Review of all his Wealth and Labour, and found himſelf diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed in them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.11.</note> 
               <hi>I looked</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>on all the labours that my hands had wrought, and on the labour that I had laboured to do, and behold all was vanity and vexation of ſpirit;</hi> a diſappointment of all my hopes and deſires of ſatisfaction; <hi>This was my portion of all my labour.</hi> Alas, all things here below are of too narrow an extent, to ſatisfie the vaſt and capacious Deſires of our Souls,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51925:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>which are enlarged with enjoying; and therefore the inſpired Pen men of the holy Scripture have advis'd us, <hi>That we labour not to be rich,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.19. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>nor lay up for our ſelves Treaſures upon Earth, but that we ſet our affections upon things above;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Grace and Glory, and the Inheritance which is incorruptible, and undefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and fadeth not away, reſerved in Heaven for us; <hi>and not on things on the Earth;</hi> the Pleaſures, Honours and Profits of this World, which we are prone to deſire inordinately, and to purſue immoderately, tho' we are charged to the contrary; <hi>Love not the World,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>neither the things that are in the World; if any Man love the World, the love of the Father is not in him: Know ye not that the Friendſhip of the World is enmity with God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>James</hi> 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever will be a Friend of the World, is the Enemy of God;</hi> in open hoſtility with him, and unfit to ſee his Face in Death or Judgment; therefore our Saviour warned his Diſciples <hi>to take heed and beware of Covetouſneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lake 12.15. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> or an inordinate deſire of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things; <hi>a Mans Life conſiſteth not in the abundance of the things which he poſſeſſeth;</hi> he may live as eaſily and comfortably with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it; Nature is content with little, and Grace with leſs: Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance is not neceſſary to render our Lives happy; the Poor are as merry and chearful, as vigorous and healthy, as well ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and contented with a ſmall pittance, as the Wealthy and Opulent with their Superfluity, which ſerves only to adminiſter to Pride and Vanity,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.11.</note> 
               <hi>to make them wiſe in their own conceit,</hi> to puff them up with Haughtineſs, and Arrogancy, Inſolency and Imperiouſneſs of Spirit, and to betray them to ſin and ſolly: <hi>They that will be rich, fall into temptations and a ſnare, and into many fooliſh and hurtful luſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9,</note> 
               <hi>which drown men in deſtruction and perdition;</hi> which take up their time, and fill their heads with ſolicitous Cares and Fears, engroſs their Affections, encum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber their Lives with toilſome Labours about them, expoſe them to a great many Sorrows, which pierce their Souls, and render Death and Judgment exceeding formidable to them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſince the love of this World is ſo dangerous a thing, let us not with <hi>Martha</hi> be careful and troubled about many things, and leave <hi>Mary</hi>'s <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num Neceſſarium</hi> wholly unregarded; but rather ſpend our Days and Years in this mortal ſtate, in adorning our Souls with Evangelical Graces and Vertues, to fit us for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; for if we had the Riches of both the <hi>Indies,</hi> we can take
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51925:16"/>nothing away with us, when we depart hence;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>Naked came we out of our Mothers Womb, and naked ſhall we return:</hi> We muſt everlaſtingly part with all that we have when we dye, and leave it, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, to the Man that ſhall come after us; <hi>and who knoweth whether he ſhall be a wiſe Man or a Fool,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecoleſ.</hi> 2.18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>yet shall he have rule over all our labour,</hi> and gather all that we have heaped up; but works of Righteouſneſs will accompany us into the other World; and now is the time for us to be rich in good Works, to grow in Grace and Holineſs; <hi>To give all diligence to add to our Faith, Vertue; to Vertue, Knowledge; to Knowledge, Temperance; to Temperance, Patience; to Patience, Godlineſs; and to Godlineſs, Brotherly Kindneſs and Charity; for if theſe things be in us and abound,</hi> and our Minds fit looſe to the Affairs of this Life, we ſhall be ready and willing to leave them, whenſoever our Lord ſhall pleaſe to call us hence.</p>
            <q>(3.) <hi>This Readineſs and Preparation for Death and Judgment, does confiſt in making our Peace and Reconciliation with God and Men.</hi>
            </q>
            <p n="1">(1.) With God, which is a thing of infinite moment; for ſo long as we continue in enmity with him, and maintain a Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion againſt his Crown and Dignity; he is engaged for the Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of his own Soveraign Power and Juſtice, to be our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and to execute his ſevere Judgments upon us; and we have no Security that he will not do it ſpeedily, without giving us farther time to conſider our ways, and throw down our Arms of Hoſtility againſt him: For the Pſalmiſt aſſures us,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.11, 12, 13,</note> 
               <hi>That God is angry with the wicked every day,</hi> (even while his Providence ſeems to ſmile upon them, and they think themſelves moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and confident.) <hi>If he turn not, he will whet his Sword, he hath bent his Bow, and made it ready, he hath prepared for him the Inſtruments of Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God is loth, for the Glory of his Patience and Long ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, forthwith to proceed againſt us; <hi>For my Names ſake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 48.9.</note> 
               <hi>will I defer mine anger; and for my Praiſe, will I refrain;</hi> He forbears us becauſe he is ſlow to anger, <hi>he knows our frame</hi> (and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion to evil) <hi>and remembers</hi> (the Weakneſs and Mortality of our Nature) <hi>that we are but Duſt,</hi> unable to bear the weight of his Indignation, and therefore he is pleaſed to fore-warn us of our danger, by ſome ſignal Tokens thereof; <hi>as the whetting
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51925:17"/>of his Sword, and the bending of his Bow;</hi> thereby to awaken in us a ſerious Conſideration of his anger, and a great care to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it, and a very earneſt deſire and endeavour to be at peace with him; the which we may obtain by Repentance and Faith in Chriſt, and by fervent Prayers and Supplications for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of our Sins.</p>
            <p n="1">[1] By cordial and ſincere Repentance; which is (a Divine Remedy) the means which God hath appointed us to uſe for the obtaining of his Favour; the Doctrine of Repentance was never taught in the School of Nature, neither could be learned from the Writings of the grave Heathens, tho' their wiſe Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers in their Works have given us ſome imperſect deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of it; But as <hi>Tertul. de poenit.</hi> hath obſerved, <hi>They were as far from underſtanding the true Reaſon of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">à ratione ejus tantum abſuerunt quantum à rationis autore.</note> 
               <hi>as from underſtanding the God of Reaſon.</hi> They have given us many excellent Rules for the practice of Moral Vertues, but were not able to inſtruct us in the nature of that Peace and Reſt which is Eternal; all that they aſpired to, was Peace and Serenity, Tranquility and Compoſedneſs of Mind, which they called Happineſs; but was only a Moral Attainment; and they that lived moſt Regularly, according to the Dictates
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>of Right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and Directions of Nature, found moſt Eaſe and Peace in their own Boſoms. Certainly <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Plato</hi> had not ſuch diſturbed and diſtracted Minds as <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas;</hi> neither had <hi>Tully</hi> and <hi>Cato</hi> ſuch black and guilty Souls as <hi>Cethegus</hi> and <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line;</hi> neither had <hi>Plutarch</hi> and <hi>Seneca</hi> thoſe Gripes and Twinges thoſe Fears and Horrours which <hi>Nero</hi> and <hi>Caligula</hi> felt; they beheld a Beauty and Comelineſs in the face of Vertue; Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitude and Deformity in Vice and Wickedneſs, and diſcovered that ſin was againſt their Reaſon and true Intereſt. <hi>Nature taught them not to ſin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">à naturâ ſequitur ut meliora probantes, pejorum poeniteat.</note> 
               <hi>to renounce and forſake Sin;</hi> but it never read them Lectures of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: God himſelf made known the firſt Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries of it to the World, and publiſhed his gracious intentions to accept of a ſincere Repentance, as the Soveraign Means to reconcile us to Himſelf: He ſent his dear and only Son to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it by his Doctrine, and confirm it by his Miracles, and to make way for it by his Death and Sacrifice. So that if God had
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51925:17"/>not been in ſerious earneſt, to have Sinners reconciled to him by Repentance; he would never have ſent the Son of his love to have obtained Peace for us by the Blood of his Croſs. <hi>Tully</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> were wholly ſilent in their Writings how ſo great a Work might be effected; but the Goſpel hath diſcovered the Counſels and Purpoſes of Grace and Mercy, agreed upon by all the Perſons in the Godhead at the Council-Board of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, (if I may ſo ſay) for the Reſtoring of loſt Man <hi>by a new and living way, which Chriſt hath conſecrated for us, and opened unto us, that we might have acceſs to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The chief Articles and Conditions whereof, are Repentance and Converſion to God, and Renovation of Mind, which are indiſpenſibly neceſſary, to fit us for the Appearance of Chriſt, and everlaſting Happineſs, which is to be obtained by him; and he therefore began his Prophetical Office with a Sermon upon Repentance, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Repent</hi> ſignifies not only ſorrow for Sin, but a change of Mind, Will and Affections, as may be ſeen at large in the Parable of the Prodigal Son,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 15.</note> where it is fully deſcribed in all the material conſtitutive and principal lines and parts of it, viz. <hi>Penſive Thoughtfulneſs and Conſideration,</hi> a manly and ſerious application of our Minds, to take an impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Re-view of our ſelves, in which God himſelf doth place the firſt ſigns of our Recovery, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.14. &amp; 28. <hi>Serious and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate Reſolution</hi> to amend our ways and doings; ſuch as we find in the Penitent King of <hi>Iſrael, I thought on my ways,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.59, 69.</note> 
               <hi>and turned my feet to thy Precepts; I made haſte and delayed not to keep thy righteous Judgments.</hi> 'Tis dangerous for us to trifle and delay in ſo momentous and weighty a matter; therefore while God waits to be gracious, let us not abuſe his Goodneſs and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, but without delay reſolve to mind and proſecute the things which belong to our Peace, before they be hid from our Eyes; and to the end that we may appeaſe the juſt Diſpleaſure of our Heavenly Father, and be re-inſtated into his favour; it is requiſite that we make an ingenious <hi>Confeſsion</hi> of all our former Tranſgreſſions, with ſhame and ſorrow of heart, and great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, accompanied with actual <hi>Reformation</hi> and Amendment, and a ſincere deſire and endeavour to be univerſally good and holy, to yield an <hi>intire Obedience</hi> to all God's Commandments; If theſe Ingredients do conſtitute our Repentance, <hi>God is faithful
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51925:18"/>and juſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>John</hi> 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>to forgive us our ſins, and to cleanſe us from all unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs:</hi> He will not exact the forfeiture of us, but freely and fully pardon us, and remember our ſins no more. <hi>When the wicked man turneth away from all his ſins,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.21.</note> 
               <hi>and keepeth my Statutes, and doth that which is lawful and right, he ſhall ſurely live, he ſhall not dye; all his tranſgreſsions that he hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they ſhall not be mentioned unto him; in his righteouſneſs that he hath done, he ſhall live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have Gods gracious Promiſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55 7.</note> That when <hi>any wicked man</hi> (whether he be Jew or Gentile) <hi>doth forſake his ways and thoughts; and returns unto the Lord, he will have mercy upon him, and abundantly pardon him:</hi> For his Mercies are as the great Mountains, firm and ſtable; he will not alter the Word that is gone out of his Mouth. Thoſe that repent (tho' their Sins are of a ſcarlet and a crimſon dye, great and many) he will certainly pardon, and receive into favour. Tho' it be a very difficult thing for a Man to retrieve himſelf, that hath been long accuſtomed to vicious Habits,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 12.23.</note> and hath debauched his Reaſon, gratified his Luſts and Paſſions, debilitated all the Powers of his Soul, and cauterized his Conſcience through a long continuance in ſin; tho' it be (I ſay) a hard thing for ſuch a one to caſt off the Yoke of Cuſtom, and to reform himſelf; yet the thing is
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 14.7, 8, 9.</note> poſſible to be effected; nay, it is abſolutely neceſſary:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.3.</note> 
               <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, Except ye be converted, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as little Children, ye cannot enter into the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh; except ye be born again, ye cannot ſee the Kingdom of God:</hi> All Births are painful,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.21. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.19.</note> both the Natural and Supernatural; but nothing is too hard for Omnipotency: He can <hi>cauſe dry Bones to live;</hi> and if we ſet our ſelves in earneſt to amend our ways and doings, and to implore the help of his Grace, he will ſend his holy Spirit to invigorate and aſſiſt us with Divine Aids, and infuſe every Grace into the Soul, which conſtitutes the <hi>Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> The Converſion of a Sinner is a work purely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>from above;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23.</note> We are <hi>born again, not of corruptible Seed, but of that which is incoruptible, and are ſanctified and cleanſed by the waſhing of Regeneration,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>and renewing of the H. Ghoſt,</hi> and ſo made meet for our Lords Appearance.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:51925:18"/>
            <p n="2">[2.] <hi>By Faith in Chriſt.</hi> This Peace of Reconciliation with God, may be obtained by a firm and ſtedfaſt belief, that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath appeaſed his Fathers Anger, ſatisfied the Demands of his Juſtice, ſlain the Enmity, eſtabliſhed a ſteady Friendſhip between God and us; and purchaſed eternal Life and Salvation for us. God the Father hath promiſed him in the Covenant of Redemption,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25.</note> 
               <hi>to be a Propitiation through Faith in his Blood;</hi> and it is by the Blood of his Croſs, that he made Peace, as the Apoſtle affirmeth, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.20. for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhedding of Blood there could be no Expiation, or Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Sins: Therefore he became obedient to the accurſed Death of the Croſs, that by the bloody Sacrifice of himſelf, there <hi>once offered,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14.</note> 
               <hi>he might perfect for ever them that are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> and do all that was neceſſary for their acceptation with God, and the forgiveneſs of their Sins. But altho' he hath done this for us, yet it is <hi>Faith</hi> on our part, which muſt lay hold of the Value and Merit of his Sacrifice and Suffering, and apply the Benefit which he hath purchaſed for us. God, is the principal Efficient; Chriſt, the Meritorius; and Faith, the Inſtrumental Cauſe of our Juſtification; the Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof, is by Faith, and not by Works; <hi>By the Deeds of the Law there ſhall be no Fleſh juſtified,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20</note> and acquitted from Condemnation in the Court of Heaven, and accounted righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, <hi>in the ſight of God?</hi> for by the Law cometh the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſin, and a more exact and perfect Diſcovery of the nature and turpitude thereof, than the Light of Nature could afford: But there is another way of becoming righteous, which is of God's Ordination and Appointment, and which alone he will accept; <hi>by Faith: Being juſtified by Faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>we have Peace with God,</hi> with whom before we were at Enmity, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle teſtifies: <hi>But now we are reconciled,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.14. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.18, 19</note> by the Blood of his Groſs, and the Merit of his Death; for <hi>he is our Peace, and hath reconciled us unto himſelf; by Jeſus Chriſt, and hath given to us the Miniſtry of Reconciliation, to wit, that God was in Chriſt, reconciling the World to himſelf;</hi> and by <hi>Faith</hi> in him, we become righteous in the ſight of God;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.22. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9.</note> 
               <hi>not by any works of righteouſneſs which we have done,</hi> but by a lively operative Faith, <hi>which is made perfect by Works, and purifieth the Heart,</hi> and bringeth forth the good Fruits of Sanctification and new Obedience in Life and Converſation.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:51925:19"/>
            <p>This is that Divine Grace which renders God propitious to us, and our Perſons and Religious Services acceptable to him. <hi>Without which it is impoſſible to pleaſe him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6.</note> This is the Shield wherewith we ſhall be able to quench the fiery Darts of the Wicked,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.19.</note> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> the Devil, who is denominated <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed One,</hi> becauſe it is a Name that fitly denotes his ſpiteful ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious nature, his deſire to vex and annoy us with his violent Temptations, wherewith he and his wicked Inſtruments fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſault us; this is that part of our ſpiritual Armour by which we become victorious, over the Fears and Terrors, the Hopes and Joys, the Temptations and Deſires of this World; which are the great Obſtructions and Hinderances of our Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience:
<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>This is the Victory that overcometh the World, even our Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the aſſiſtance of this heavenly Vertue, we are enabled to live above the World, and deſpiſe the Pomps and Vanities of it; becauſe it repreſents unto our Minds
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1.</note> inviſible Glories and Felicities, all the Riches and Treaſures of Heaven, and the future Recompences of Reward: <hi>For this cauſe we faint not, tho' our outward man decay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16.18</note> 
               <hi>our inward is renewed day by day; whilſt we look not at the things that are ſeen, but at the things which eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, nor have entred into the heart of Man to conceive: For the things which are ſeen, are temporal; but the things which are not ſeen, are eternal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is that Fruit of the Spirit which gives us Union and Communion with Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. <hi>John</hi> 3.15, 16.</note> and entitles us to Eternal Bliſs, to live for ever with the Lord. Whoſoever believes on him, and commits the Care of his Soul unto him, relying on him alone for Salvation; hath ſuch an Intereſt in him, that he is not afraid of being condemned by the ſevere Judge at his Appearing: <hi>He that over-cometh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall inherit all things; and I will be his God,</hi> (to love and glorifie him) <hi>and he ſhall be my Son,</hi> to inherit all the Joys and Happineſs of Heaven, and to live with me for ever; <hi>but the fearful and the unbelieving ſhall have their parts with the Abominable, and Murtherers, and Whoremongers, and Sorcerers and all Liars, in the Lake which burneth with Fire and Brimſtone, which is the ſecond Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">[3.] By Prayer; this is the moſt effectual means which God hath conſecrated for receiving the higheſt Bleſſings, for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:51925:19"/>of Peace with him, and to compleat our Reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Haec vis Deo grata eſt.</hi> Tert.</note> Salvation is not to be obtained without great vehemency in Devotion: This violence which we offer to God in fervent Prayer is very grateful to him.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>The effectual fervent prayer of a righteous man</hi> is very prevalent with God for obtaining of what is deſired. When God had determined to deſtroy <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> and the neighbouring Cities, by raining down Fire and Brimſtone from Heaven upon them to conſume them for their filthy luſts; <hi>Abraham</hi> by his powerful interceſſions had moſt certainly averted Gods indignation from thoſe wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed people, if there could have been found but Ten Righteous Perſons among them. Hereby <hi>Jacob</hi> in his conflict with the Angel of the Covenant, wreſtled ſo vigorouſly that he obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Victory, and had the name <hi>Iſrael</hi> given him:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.28.</note> For ſaith the Text, <hi>as a Prince thou haſt power with God and with Men and haſt prevailed.</hi> And <hi>Elias,</hi> an eminent Prophet, prayed earneſtly that it might not rain, and it rained not on the Land of the Ten Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for the ſpace of Three Years and ſix Months: and he prayed again, and the Heavens gave Rain, and the Earth brought forth her Fruit.</p>
            <p>Temporal Bleſſings, which appertain to this mortal life, God hath promiſed upon certain conditions, reſtrictions, and limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>i. e.</hi> that if he in his infinite Wiſdom ſee them good and neceſſary, convenient and advantagious for us. Spiritual Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings which tend to make us happy in the future World he hath promiſed abſolutely: and in particular, Peace of reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation with God, and eternal Salvation, he is ready to grant to every humble ſupplicant;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.32.</note> 
               <hi>their Soul ſhall live that ſeek the Lord.</hi> They ſhall have inward life, joy, and conſolation here, and everlaſting Life and Glory hereafter;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.13.</note> 
               <hi>for whoſoever ſhall call on the name of the Lord ſhall be ſaved:</hi> but for theſe Belſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings he will be ſought unto both <hi>publickly</hi> and <hi>privately.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">(1) <hi>Publickly,</hi> in the Church, which is the Houſe of Prayer wherein the Primitive Chriſtians met together in multitudes, like a great Army to beſiege Heaven, and take it by ſtorm;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coimus in Coetum &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregationem ut ad Deum qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſi manufactâ praecationibus am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biamus.</hi> Tert.</note> 
               <hi>for the Kingdom of Heaven ſuffereth violence, and the violent take it by ſtorm; i. e.</hi> by ardent Prayers and fervent Devotions: they did ſend up their joint Petitions with ſuch holy
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:51925:20"/>fervors, that St. <hi>Jerom</hi> faith their <hi>Amen</hi> was like a clap of Thunder. Certainly their Zeal is a ſhame and reproach to our coldneſs and indifferency to publick Prayers, which hath been the general practice of Men of all Ages and Religion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, who have thought it their duty to beleaguer the Univerſal Parent and Soveraign of the World; and to pay him their thankful ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments. And therefore ſuch as deny or neglect ſo faced and ſolemn a part of Divine Worſhip, and ſo excellent a means of Holineſs, may juſtly be ſuſpected of Atheiſm and Impiety.</p>
            <p>Be intreated therefore (dear Chriſtians) as you value the Church, of which you are Members; as you deſire the favour of God and the light of his countenance which is better than life; to attend frequently the publick Aſſemblies, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form your parts in the Churches Prayers with devotion and fervency;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87.2.</note> 
               <hi>for God loveth the gates of Sion, more than all the</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate <hi>habitations and dwellings of Jacob:</hi> it is the place which he hath peculiarly choſen to exhibit himſelf in, to all that call upon him there for the remiſſion of their ſins:
<note place="margin">48.3.</note> 
               <hi>God is known in her palaces for a ſure refuge:</hi> there is the moſt proper and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent place for us Chriſtians publickly to meet in, to beſeech the Father of Mercies to be at peace with us. But leſt we ſhould play the Phariſee, and court the obſervation of the World with a formal and pompous ſhew of Religion, our deareſt Lord hath directed us alſo,</p>
            <p n="2">(2) To the more frequent exerciſe of Religious Adoration in private with our Families; and yet more ſecretly in our Cloſet retirements; where we may with greater freedom ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg our Guilts, with all the aggravations and circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of our Sins to our gracious Father, in order to obtain par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and reconciliation with him: to lay open our particular wants and neceſſities, and pour out the deſires of our Souls in all the threnes and ſad accents of godly ſorrow; in all the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitential tears of Contrition, and meltings of Repentance; in all the endearments of Love, and ardors of Affection. And to avoid Hypocriſie,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.6.</note> our Saviour hath directed us, <hi>when we pray to enter into our Cloſets, and having ſhut the door, to pray to our Father which is in ſecret, and he will reward us openly.</hi> There we may think that we hear him kindly ſaying unto us, as the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:51925:20"/>Bridegroom doth to his Spouſe the Church:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>O my Dove thou art in the clefts of the Rocks, in the ſecret places of the ſtairs, let me ſee thy countenance, let me hear thy voice, for ſweet is thy voice, and thy countenance is comly.</hi> Abſent not your ſelves (dear Souls) from my preſence by reaſon of your deformities, be not aſhamed to appear before me, but come with broken and contrite hearts, with an humble boldneſs and confidence into my preſence, and make your ſupplications unto me; for your prayers and praiſes, your perſons and Services are accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to me, and amiable in my ſight. <hi>For I the Lord am gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and merciful, long-ſuffering and abundant in goodneſs and truth, forgiving iniquity, tranſgreſſion, and ſin;</hi> of all kinds and degrees whatſoever, the ſin againſt the H. Ghoſt excepted. So great is Gods mercy and clemency to relenting ſinners, that he pardons not only ſingle acts, but confirmed habits of ſin; and thoſe alſo of ſeveral kinds and natures. So that if we would ſeriouſly reflect upon the tranſcendent excellency of his kind and merciful nature, and the tender love he bears to the Souls which he hath created, this will quicken us to make our humble ſupplications to him, to be at peace with us; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſince he himſelf hath declared,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 45.16.</note> 
               <hi>that none ſhall ſeek his face in vain:</hi> And that both our Saviour, and his Apoſtles, have encouraged us with aſſured promiſes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.7.</note> 
               <hi>that whatſoever we ask the Father in his name, he will give it us. Ask and it ſhall be given, ſeek and ye ſhall find, knock and it ſhall be opened unto you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.8. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.14.</note> 
               <hi>Draw night to God</hi> (in humble adoration) <hi>and he will draw nigh to you,</hi> in the manifeſtation of his grace and favour. <hi>This is the confidence that we have in him, that if we ask any thing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will he heareth us:</hi> for he is more ready to give than we to ask. <hi>The Lord is very pittiful;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86.5.</note> full of bowels and of tender mercies. <hi>He is good, and ready to for give, and plenteous in mercy unto all them that call upon him.</hi> Having therefore theſe promiſes we are encouraged <hi>to pray in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6; 7.</note> 
               <hi>and in every thing by Prayer and Supplication to make known our requeſts unto God:</hi> for by ſo doing we may obtain peace of reconciliation with him; even that peace which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all underſtanding, and which ſhall keep our hearts and minds through Jeſus Chriſt, and preſerve in our boſoms ſuch a calmneſs and tranquility of Soul, and peace of Conſcience, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:51925:21"/>fervour of affection, as will make us fit to die, and <hi>ready</hi> to receive with joy and gladneſs the Son of Man, when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to judg the world in righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>But if we refuſe to ſeek the Lord while he may be ſound, and let ſlip the preſent ſeaſon of Grace, the acceptable time, and the day of Salvation, in which he will be intreated, and will not mind the things which belong to our peace in the day of our viſitation: If we paſs our alotted time, and the terrors of Death ſurprize us, he may then give us <hi>hearts that cannot repent and ſeek him;</hi> and Conſcience will then upbraid us with our neglects, and fill us with bitter anguiſh, when we ſhall call to mind how many holy opportunities of publick and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Devotion we have neglected; how many hours we have prodigally ſpent upon vain emploiments, ſinful pleaſures, and carnal delights; which God intended we ſhould have beſtowed in prayer and communion with him. Let us therefore often think of the day of Death, when our Body ſhall return to the Earth from whence it originally came, and the Spirit to God who gave it. Let us awaken our ſelves to a lively ſenſe of our approaching change, that we may ſee the neceſſity of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring for it, and lay up betimes a ſtock of Grace againſt that day comes. Let us not put off Devotion as a work proper for a Death-bed; for if we die not ſuddenly, God only knows, whether we may die ſenſibly: For our Underſtandings may be diſturbed; our Reaſon fail us; an Apoplexy may ſeize and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pifie and benum our Spirits in ſuch a degree, that we may on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceive with our animal Faculties. Some painful or acute Diſeaſe may ſenſibly afflict us, and cauſe a great diſorder in our Souls, and diſtract our Thoughts from minding our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Eſtate. Our hearts which have been all along ſubtile and dilatory, may deceive us at the laſt hour. God may ſubſtract his aids and aſſiſtance from us, and prove inexorable, or deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us over to a reprobate mind: So that our ſafeſt and wiſeſt courſe is, to lay up a good treaſure for our ſelves while there is time in our hands, againſt our final change cometh. A life of ſtrict Virtue and Devotion will not then fail us: but we may look back upon it with comfort and ſatisfaction. It muſt needs ſave us many ſorrowful ſighs and tears, and penſive thoughts of heart. But our Conſcience will never upbraid us
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:51925:21"/>with any bitter reflections for having done our duty; neither will it be any regret or trouble to us <hi>to remember that we did ſerve our Creator in the days of our youth;</hi> but now we ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly reap the benefits of an early piety. Let us therefore now acquaint our ſelves with God that we may be at peace, and be ready to receive him at his coming. Having thus made our peace with God, it is incumbent upon us in the ſecond place</p>
            <p n="2">(2) To make our peace with Men, to reconcile our ſelves to our Brethren whom we have wronged and injured in any kind whatſoever: this is neceſſary to be done in order to the fitting every one of us for Death and Judgment; for when we come to die, we would willingly with good old <hi>Simeon depart in peace</hi> without any ſparks of anger or malice; wrath or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure abiding upon our minds unexſtinguiſhed; or any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt gain to cleave or ſtick cloſe to us: for in the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment God will require a ſtrict account of our obedience to his Commandments, and there is not any duty of Chriſtianity, which he hath inculcated with greater plainneſs, then this <hi>of peace one with another:</hi> for it is one of the greateſt earthly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, and doth moſt lively repreſent the peaceful ſtate of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; where the bleſſed Angels and Souls of juſt men made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, live in perfect peace and amity. Now that we may be here in a great meaſure fitted for that bleſſed Society;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.31.</note> we are commanded <hi>to put off all bitterneſs, and wrath, and anger, and clamor, with all malice; and to put on kindneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.8, 12, 14.</note> 
               <hi>humbleneſs of mind, meekneſs, long ſuffering, and clemency towards each other, and above all to put on charity; i. e.</hi> mutual chriſtian love,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.35.</note> which is the proper livery of Chriſts Diſciples. <hi>By this ſhall all men know that ye are my Diſciples if ye love one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are likewiſe prohibited all ſeuds and quarrels, and are charged <hi>not to revenge our ſelves, but to give place unto wrath:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.19. 17. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.11.5.13. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.4.</note> not to retaliate injuries, <hi>to recompence no man evil for evil; but to ſtudy to be quiet, to be at peace among our ſelves, to ſeek peace and enſue it;</hi> yea, to be at ſome pains to obtain it, when it ſeems to fly from us; <hi>to follow peace with all men. Follow,</hi> in the original, is an emphatical word, which imports an eager, unwearied purſuit of peace and comfortable aſſociation with all perſons, in all things good and lawful; as far as it is poſſible
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:51925:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>for us:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.19.</note> And in order to the obtaining thereof, <hi>to follow the things which make for peace:</hi> to endeavour all things that will promote it, by performing all kind Offices, and doing good to all men; ſhewing them all due reſpects, and affable deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, courteous ſalutations, eaſie acceſs, cherful countenance, ſoft words, and friendly diſcourſe; candidly interpreting their words and actions, mildly reproving their faults, patiently bearing their haſty paſſions, burying their affronts and injuries in oblivion; the which in the opinion of <hi>Solomon,</hi> the wiſeſt of men, is an effectual means to obtain peace, and preſerve an inviolable amity and friendſhip among men;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 17.9.</note> 
               <hi>he that covereth a tranſgreſſion ſeeketh love.</hi> Theſe, and ſuch like things, <hi>are the things which make for peace,</hi> which we muſt purſue with zeal and vigour;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.18.</note> 
               <hi>that if it be poſſible we may live peaceably with all men;</hi> that nothing may be wanting in our endeavours to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the friendſhip and good will of men. And to fit us for the preſence and ſociety of the Prince of Peace, it is neceſſary that we make reſtitution to all perſons whom we have wronged by fraud or circumvention; injuſtice or violence; oppreſſion or deceit. That we ſubmit our ſelves to all perſons whom we have juſtly offended, acknowledge our faults, crave their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and readily forgive thoſe that have offended us; unleſs we do ſo, we are not fit to die and appear in judgment.</p>
            <p n="1">[i] It is indiſpenſibly neceſſary that we make reſtitution as far as we are able to all perſons whom we have wronged by oppreſſion and violence, deceit or fraud. Now by Reſtitution I mean with Theologiſts, <hi>an act of commutative juſtice, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the injury done is repaired, and the perſon wronged is put in poſſeſſion of his goods, injuriouſly taken away from him;</hi> or <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by due compenſation is made, or equivalent ſatisfaction given to him, from whom any thing is unjuſtly taken or detained, or who is unjuſtly damnified by another.</hi> Bp. <hi>Andrews</hi> on the 8th Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment.</p>
            <p>There are indeed ſome caſes wherein it is impoſſible to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form this incumbent duty: For corrupted honour cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired; nor abuſed chaſtity be reſtored. He that in proud wrath, anger and malice, hath taken away the precious life of another, cannot poſſibly reſtore it to him again, but muſt hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily beg pardon of God (whoſe ſole Prerogative it is to diſpoſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:51925:22"/>of every mans life at his pleaſure) as <hi>David</hi> did in the caſe of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> whom he had contrived and cauſed to be ſlain by the Sword of the Children of <hi>Ammon:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.14.</note> 
               <hi>Deliver me from Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiltineſs, O God, thou God of my ſalvation, and my tongue ſhall ſing aloud of thy righteouſneſs.</hi> And foraſmuch as no reparation can be made to the deceaſed Perſons Mournful Friends, the Offender muſt humbly beg Pardon of them alſo; and make due Satisfaction to the Creditors, and Children, and Relations of the Perſon ſlain, ſo far as it appears that they are damnified in their Temporal Eſtate, by the immature Death of their dear Friend, who was cut off out of the Land of the Living, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out time to repent, and opportunity of making his peace with God.</p>
            <p>In like manner he that hath taken away the good Name of another by Slander or Detraction; and hath blaſted his Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation by opprobrious Defamations, cannot prevent the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief that may enſue thereupon; all that he can do is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs his fault to the Perſon injured, and endeavour to ſtop the ſpreading of the infamous Report, by timely unſaying what he hath ſpoken in paſſion or prejudice, againſt the Rule of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which obligeth to give every man his due, <hi>Honour to whom Honour.</hi> In theſe and ſuch like Caſes, Reſtitution hath no place.</p>
            <p>But in Oppreſſion, Bribery, and unjuſt detention of what is anothers, to which we have no legal right or title, where the practice of this Vertue is abſolutely neceſſary; St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſets down this for a Canon, <hi>Non remittitur peccatum, niſi reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuatur ablatum,</hi> the Sin of unjuſt getting is never pardoned, unleſs reſtitution be made of what is unjuſtly gotten, if the Offender be able. Therefore it is neceſſary to do it, in point of Duty and Obedience to God who hath commanded it, and as a means of Pardon and Salvation; our Repentance cannot be ſincere without it, as the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> aſſures us:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.21. <hi>and</hi> 33.15.</note> 
               <hi>If the wicked man turn from all his ſins that he hath committed, and keep my ſtatutes, and do that which is lawful and right; if he reſtore the pledge, give again that he hath robbed, walk in the Statutes of Life, without committing iniquity, he ſhall ſurely live, he ſhall not dye:</hi> If he do not this, the Commination threatned, ſhall not be reverſed, <hi>He ſhall ſurely dye.</hi> Evident then it is, that a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:51925:23"/>well grounded peace cannot be obtained with the perſon injur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without reſtitution; nor with Almighty God, whoſe Laws (which oblige men to love, fidelity and juſtice) are tranſgreſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in every ſin we commit againſt our Neighbour; and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly in the caſe before us;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Levit.</hi> 6.2, 3, 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>If a Soul ſin, and commit a treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs againſt the Lord, and lie unto his neighbour in that which was delivered him to keep,</hi> (by denying a thing depoſited in truſt with him) <hi>or in fellowſhip,</hi> (or commerce in trading) <hi>or in any thing taken away by violence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 61.8.</note> 
               <hi>force, and rapine,</hi> (God hating Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery) <hi>or hath deceived his Neighbour ſecretly,</hi> (of which kind of injuſtice <hi>Zacheus</hi> the Publican cleared himſelf, by offering a Four fold Reſtitution of what he had gotten of any man wrongfully:)
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>or have found that which was loſt, and ſweareth falſly; then it ſhall be becauſe he hath ſinned, and is guilty, he ſhall reſtore that which he took violently away, or the thing which he hath deceitfully gotten;</hi>
               <note place="margin">De male quaeſitis vix gaudet tertius haeres.</note> 
               <hi>or that which was delivered him to keep; or the loſt thing which is found; he ſhall reſtore it in the principal,</hi> (for Reſtitution to Man muſt accompany Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance towards God,) <hi>and ſhall add the Fifth part more there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and give it unto him to whom it appertaineth, and he ſhall bring his Treſpaſs Offering unto the Lord, and the Prieſt ſhall make an atonement for him before the Lord; and it ſhall be forgiven him in any thing that he hath done in treſpaſſing therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Law was again inculcated with additional directions to whom compenſation is to be made, either in kind or in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivalency, <hi>in Numbers</hi> 5.6, 7, 8. and largely commented up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the learned <hi>Ainſworth</hi> out of <hi>Maimonides</hi> his Treaty of Robbery.</p>
            <p>Now if God did ſo ſtrictly inſiſt upon the performance of this duty from the Jews, and encouraged them to it with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of pardon and remiſſion; of temporal proſperity and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal glory; and expreſly told them that he would not accept their Oblations, if they did not confeſs their ſins with grief and remorſe; and make full ſatisfaction according as the Law directed: then we may rationally infer, that he will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of our Repentance without the like practice: if we would be at peace with him, we muſt offer unto him the beſt and moſt acceptable ſacrifice;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.18.19.</note> which is <hi>a broken ſpirit and a contrite
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:51925:23"/>heart.</hi> Therefore our Saviour (who came not to deſtroy the Law and the Prophets, nor to abrogate the obſervation of them in his Kingdom, but to fulfil, ſupply and perfect them) hath made this an Evangelical Duty.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>If thou bring thy gift to the Altar, and there remembreſt that thy Brother hath ought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee,</hi> (any matter of complaint, for any wrong or inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry done by thee to him) <hi>leave there thy gift before the Altar, and go thy way; firſt be reconciled to thy Brother, and then come and offer thy gift.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> chargeth us,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>not to go beyond or defraud our Brother in any matter, and to owe no man any thing but love; for he that loveth another hath fulfilled the Law;</hi> this is the Golden Rule, to do as we would be done by: Wherefore it concerns us to have ſpecial regard to the diſcharge of this duty of Reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as far as we are able; and if we want ability to do it, as the ſacred Word and Law of God commands, we are to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt our Repentance and remorſe of Conſcience; to teſtifie the ſincerity thereof with compunction and tears; and ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly promiſe that if ever God make us able we will actually do it. And in this caſe we need not doubt but that God will accept <hi>of a willing mind;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12.</note> and every merciful and good man whom we have injured, will pity, pardon and forgive us, and reſtore us to his favour.</p>
            <p n="2">[2.] For the compoſing of our mind in order to our waiting for the coming of our Lord by Death or Judgment, it is alſo neceſſary, that as we ſubmit our ſelves with all humility to all perſons whom we have juſtly offended, acknowledg our faults and crave their pardon, ſo alſo cordially forgive thoſe that have wronged us.</p>
            <p>Tho' we find it a work of great difficulty to bring down our big Spirits, and to bow our ſtubborn Wills to make an humble and ingenuous acknowledgment of our faults, and ask the forgiveneſs of thoſe whom we have juſtly diſpleaſed; becauſe as <hi>Salvian</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Totum durum eſt, quicquid impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur invitis.</note> 
               <hi>every thing is hard to an unwilling mind;</hi> yet it is abſolutely neceſſary, for without emptying our hearts of all rancour, malice, ill will and deſire of revenge, we cannot obtain peace with men; nor remiſſion of our ſins, and reconciliation with God: He hath declared
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:51925:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>that no religious duty which we perform will be pleaſing and acceptable to him ſo long as we are not in charity with our Neighbour, as appears from the forequoted Scripture; <hi>If thou bring thy gift to the Altar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.23.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. go firſt and be reconciled to thy Brother,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, do thy endeavour at leaſt to appeaſe his anger and make him friends with thee, <hi>then come and offer thy gift.</hi> If he receive thy ſubmiſſion thou haſt gained thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; if he continue the Enmity the fault is his, and he ſhall anſwer it to Almighty God, whoſe Law he violates in denying his pardon to the Penitent. <hi>If thy Brother treſpaſs againſt thee, rebuke him; and if he repent, forgive him; if he treſpaſs againſt thee ſeven times a day, and ſeven times (i. e.</hi> as often in a day) <hi>turn again unto thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>ſaying, I repent; thou ſhalt forgive him;</hi> and lay aſide all thoughts and deſire of Revenge: This is a Doctrine directly contrary to the principle of the Stoicks, (a Sect of Philoſophers who pretended to be moſt ſublime and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined in their Morals) which was this, <hi>That a wiſe man ought not to pardon another mans faults, nor to commiſerate his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, for this is to invite injuries by a ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid patience.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Magni animi injurias deſpicere. Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Ira.</hi>
               </note> But the wiſe <hi>Seneca</hi> was of another mind, who ſaith, <hi>That it is the character of a great Soul to deſpiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Chap. </seg>34</label> 
               <hi>and that nothing is more glorious then to change enmity into amity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The World may think a man ſtupid and without ſenſe of honor, that paſſeth by wrongs. But <hi>Cato</hi> a wiſe Heathen is commended by <hi>Seneca</hi> for not reſenting an affront or blow giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en him by a rude fellow in the <hi>Bath,</hi> to whom he ſaid, when he came to make ſatisfaction,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 32.</note> 
               <hi>I remember not that thou didſt ſtrike me;</hi> as thinking it a wiſer part not to acknowledg the wrong then to repay it. And a wiſer man than he, affirmeth that the ſlower a perſon is to anger, and the readier to forgive, the more underſtanding he hath, and is more worthy of praiſe and honour.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.11.</note> 
               <hi>The diſcretion of a man deferreth his anger, and it is his glory to paſs over a tranſgreſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Prince of Peace came into the world to ſet up his his Kingdom &amp; introduce his holy Religion, he enacted Laws of Peace &amp; Love; of gentleneſs and forbearance, of forgiveneſs, as moſt agreeable to his own nature and the deſign of his coming.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:51925:24"/>He charged his Diſciples <hi>to love their Enemies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>to be kindly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate one towards another; to render to no Man evil for evil, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to follow that which is good.</hi> To bear no grudge or ill will, to harbour no thoughts of Revenge, for that is God's Prerogative. <hi>Dearly beloved, avenge not your ſelves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.19.</note> 
               <hi>but rather give place un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to Wrath: for it is written, Vengeance is mine, I will repay ſaith the Lord.</hi> It ſo properly belongs to Him, that none but His Miniſters who are commiſſioned by Him, may execute it. He ſeverely threatned the <hi>Edomites</hi> and <hi>Philiſtines</hi> for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeful uſage of the <hi>Jews,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 25.14. 15, 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>I will lay my vengeance upon</hi> Edom <hi>by the hand of my People</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and they ſhall do in</hi> Edom <hi>accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my anger and fury, and they ſhall know my Vengeance, ſaith the Lord; behold I will ſtretch out my hand upon them, and will execute great Vengeance upon them in furious Rebukes;</hi> (or fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of wrath and without pity,) <hi>and they ſhall know that I am the Lord, when I lay my Vengeance upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But tho' God is ſometimes forced to vindicate his own Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in Acts of vindictive Juſtice: yet in regard of his ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry proceedings with Men; he is frequently ſtiled <hi>the God of Love and Peace, of Patience and Conſolation, the Father of pities, rich in Mercy, full of bowels;</hi> ready to turn from his anger, eaſie to be intreated, and willing to forgive thoſe who are guilty of the greateſt treſpaſſes againſt him: This is his glory and delight, <hi>becauſe he is merciful and gracious,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>long ſuffering and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant in goodneſs, keeping mercy for thouſands, forgiving iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, tranſgreſſion and ſin.</hi> Now this kind and indulgent diſpoſition of Mind, which is the perfection of the divine Nature,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 4.11. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.31, 32.</note> the holy Apoſtles recommend to our imitation and practice; <hi>beloved if God ſo loved us we ought alſo to love one another, let all bitterneſs, and wrath, and anger, and clamour, and evil ſpeaking, be put away with all Malice; and be kind one to another, be tender hearted for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving one another, even as God for Chriſts ſake, hath forgiven you:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is mighty kindneſs in our heavenly Father to offer us eaſie tearms of Peace, and to beſeech us <hi>to be reconciled to God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20.</note> the conſideration hereof ſhould melt us into love and tenderneſs towards our offended Brother, for the wrongs and injuries which he hath forgiven us are infinitely greater, and of a more provoking nature, then thoſe which he requires us to forgive our Brethren; our offences againſt him are like <hi>Beams;</hi> theirs
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:51925:25"/>againſt us, but as <hi>Motes;</hi> ours for Number and Magnitude are <hi>Ten thouſand Talents;</hi> theirs for paucity and meanneſs, but a <hi>hundred pence,</hi> and ſince he hath ſo frankly forgiven us, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Ingenuity ſhould engage us to be very eaſie to forgive thoſe that have offended us freely and fully, unfeignedly and cordially from our very Hearts.</p>
            <p>This the great King in the Parable inſiſteth much upon to his ungrateful Servant:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.22.</note> 
               <hi>I forgave thee all that Debt thou owedſt me, becauſe thou deſiredſt me; ſhould'ſt not thou alſo have had compaſſion on thy Fellow Servant, even as I had pity on thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Saviour gave us his admirable Pattern of Charity and Forgiveneſs, he ſhewed greater love to us, whilſt we were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Enemies to him; then ever any of us have done to our Neighbour: and when he was upon the Croſs in the height of his bitter Paſſion, in the agony of Death: he Prayed for his mortal and moſt malicious Enemies; and earneſtly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded with his Father for his Crucifiers:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.34.</note> 
               <hi>Father forgive them, for they know not what they do.</hi> Now ſo worthy a Precedent ſhould Rouſe our induſtry and influence our Practice; and we are the greateſt Monſters of ingratitude in the World, if we are not provoked by an Example ſo illuſtrious in it ſelf, and ſo advantagious to us, <hi>to go and do likewiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The benefits which accrew unto us thereby are very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable; the inconveniencies which attend the neglect of ſo doing are very dangerous and hurtful.</p>
            <p n="1">(1) The benefits which we gain by forgiving injuries are very conſiderable, ſuch are freedom from all thoſe unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Paſſions of envy, hatred, malice and deſire of Revenge, which are continually fretting and vexatious to our Spirits, and eat out the peace and comfort of our Lives, whenſoever we do cordially forgive a Treſpaſs, we find a great Calm on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in our Boſoms; our Souls are at eaſe, and our Thoughts are no longer diſturbed with meditating of Revenge; the offence is to us, as if it had never been committed: Envyings, Strife and Contentions ceaſe, together with the ſources of them; anger, malice, pride, emulation; in the room whereof ſprings up charity, kindneſs, gentleneſs, meekneſs, humility, long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, patience, and other God like Vertues, which are the Riches and Beauty; the Glory and Ornament of a Chriſtian;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:51925:25"/>and render him lovely and amiable in the Eyes of his Enemies; and Venerable in the eſteem of all good Men; and all his Duties, and Services pleaſing and acceptable to God, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contribute to the obtaining remiſſion of his ſins with God, as our Saviour himſelf certifies us;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.14.</note> 
               <hi>If ye forgive Men their Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, your heavenly Father will alſo forgive you;</hi> not that our forgiving our Brethren without the concurrence of other divine Graces and holy Duties, is alone ſufficient to entitle us to the remiſſion of our Sins; but to ſhew us that without this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving of our Brethren, Almighty God will not forgive us; as alſo to repreſent the excellency and neceſſity of this Duty, which is very grateful to him, and of great Power in order to the commending us to his Grace, and favourable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, and a principal part of that Obedience which we owe to him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1, 2.</note> and which he will reward with eternal Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: <hi>Bleſſed is he whoſe Tranſgreſſion is forgiven, whoſe Sin is covered, bleſſed is the Man unto whom the Lord imputeth not Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and in whoſe Spirit there is no guile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2) The inconveniencies which do attend the neglect of this Duty are very dangerous and hurtful, the implacable and irreconcilable Perſon encreaſeth his own ſorrows; vexeth and cruciateth his own Soul, makes his anguiſh more ſharp and piercing: To uſe the words of a great and good Man;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arch Bp. Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotſon's Sermon on Mat</hi> 5.44.</note>
               <q>
                  <hi>The very deſign of Revenge is troubleſom, and puts the Spirits into an unnatural fermentation and tumult; the Man that meditates it, is always reſtleſs, his very Soul is ſtung, ſwells and boiles, is in pain and anguiſh, hath no eaſe, no enjoyment of it ſelf ſo long as this paſſion reigns:</hi>
               </q> It entails enmitie and miſchief upon him that is guilty of it, from his Adverſaries; who will not fail to add weight unto his ſhoulders, and multiply freſh inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and affronts upon him, which will gall his very Soul, and make his Life painful and uneaſie to him, and which is moſt of all afflictive and deplorable, he puts a bar to the remiſſion of his own ſins. <hi>If ye forgive not Men their Treſpaſſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.15.</note> 
               <hi>neither will your Father forgive your Treſpaſſes, one Man beareth hatred to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and doth he ſeek pardon of the Lord?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 28.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>he ſheweth no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to a Man which is like himſelf: and doth he ask forgivneſs of the Lord?</hi> God will ſurely keep his ſins in remembrance,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.2.</note> and repay him in his own kind and <hi>meaſure,</hi> he that is pitiful
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:51925:26"/>and merciful to his offending Brother, ſhall find mercy from God; he that will not forgive, ſhall not be forgiven; but ſhall be judged with impartial juſtice according to the ſeverity of the Law, without the leaſt mixture of Mercy; <hi>he ſhall have Judgment without mercy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi> 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>that hath ſhewed no mercy.</hi> God will deal with him according to the demerit of his ſins, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point him his portion with the reprobate Angels, whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample he imitated in implacable malice and revenge, this will be the dreadful ſentence of malediction;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41.</note> 
               <hi>depart from me thou curſed Sinner into everlaſting Fire prepared for the Devil and his Angels:</hi> miſerable companions for diſtreſſed Souls, but their condemnation is juſt and agreeable to their own requeſts, for as oft as they ſaid the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> they in effect prayed for their own <hi>Damnation;</hi> and beſought God <hi>to forgive them their Debts, as they forgave their Debtors, i. e.</hi> that he would not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them, becauſe they will not forgive their offending Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole then it does appear, that as abiding anger, malice, and uncharitableneſs, renders us unfit to die and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in Judgment; ſo forgiveneſs and mercy, diſpoſe and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare us for the coming of our Lord; let us therefore take the Wiſe-Mans advice;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecclus</hi> 28.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>Remember our End and let enmity ceaſe; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member Corruption and Death, and abide in the Commandments, and bear no malice to our Neighbour:</hi> tho' our Blood flows now warmly in our veins, and our ſpirits are brisk, and we enjoy a perfect ſtate of Health, and therefore delay and put off many things that are neceſſary to fit us for our final change; yet it will not be long but we muſt put off this tabernacle and put on cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: when Death approacheth us, we ſhall then with <hi>Balaam deſire to die the death of the Righteous, and that our latter End may be like his,</hi> peaceable and happy; that we may ſee the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity of Gods choſen, and the glory of his Saints in Heaven; the which we ſhall never attain unto, unleſs we quit our ſelves of all uncharitableneſs, and root out the malignant diſtemper of mind, and all thoſe bad diſpoſitions, thoſe keen and tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous paſſions which hitherto have rufled us, and diſturbed the tranquility and repoſe of our Souls; therefore the great Men of the World (who have been prone to remember affronts and injuries with the higheſt reſentments) when they come to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:51925:26"/>Die, look upon Forgivneſs and Charity as neceſſary prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for their change; do give their general Amneſty to all that have offended them, either out of Fear or Obedience to him who is the fountain of Love and Goodneſs; who paſſeth by innumerable indignities, and poureth down ſhowers of bounty and mercy upon them that provoke him to wrath and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt them every day.</p>
            <p>A chief part of our readineſs and preparation to meet our Lord, conſiſts in doing all the good we can while we live with unwearied diligence and expedition; <hi>For there is no work,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.10.</note> 
               <hi>nor device, nor knowledge, nor wiſdom in the Grave:</hi> Now is the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for us to lay up for our ſelves Treaſures in Heaven; for if once Death put a period to our Lives, the time of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for Eternity is at an end: our Souls will be for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver what they are when they leave the Body; ſo that it ought to be our chiefeſt care to improve the preſent ſeaſons of Grace; and to ſecure to our ſelves a right and title to that <hi>exceeding great and eternal weight of Glory, which is reſerved in Heaven,</hi> for all thoſe that are rich in works of Piety, Juſtice, and Charity.</p>
            <p>This is one main end of our being ſent into the World, to do good <hi>to all Men in general,</hi> becauſe they are partakers of the ſame common nature with us; allied to us by cognation of Blood; ſprout from the ſame common ſtock, are like us in the contexture and frame of our Bodies; and inſpired with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Souls, which are endowed with reaſon and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as well as ours, they lively repreſent us in all the natural Characters and Features of Body and Soul, and are diſcriminat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from us only in ſome ſmall circumſtantial matters; they are lyable to the ſame Fortunes and diſtinguiſhing Titles of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Dignity, purchaſed with the ſame precious Blood, comprehended in the ſame Covenant of Life and Peace, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the ſame common Salvation, and Heirs of the ſame Promiſes and Heavenly Inheritance. <hi>In particular,</hi> we are to do good to the Houſe-hold of Faith, <hi>i. e.</hi> to the Catholick Church of Chriſt extended from one end of the Earth to the other, which he hath redeemed with his Blood; beſeeching Almighty God to inſpire her with a Spirit of Truth, Unity and Concord, to preſerve her from all falſe Doctrines, Hereſie, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:51925:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>Schiſm. <hi>More eſpecially yet</hi> ſhall we pray (after the Examples of thoſe Holy Men <hi>Jeremiah</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi>) for <hi>Sion</hi> the City of our Solemnities, for the Church of which we are Members; <hi>that peace may be within her walls,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 122.6.</note> 
               <hi>and proſperity within her palaces:</hi> That God, by whoſe name we are called would not leave us, <hi>but be a wall of fire round about us;</hi> an impregnable and invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble defence in this time of our neceſſity, by his Power and Providence; <hi>and the Glory in the midſt of us;</hi> by his gracious Preſence and Holy Ordinances in their power and purity; in the glorious appearance of Holineſs, Peace, and Bleſſedneſs: <hi>That he would ſtrengthen the Bars of</hi> Sions <hi>Gates, and bleſs all her Children within her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That he would maintain his truth, and preſerve the beauty of our Religious Government, and abate our heats and animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, that we may not by our peeviſh differencies and unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary diviſions open a gap for the common Enemy to invade us; but may agree in this <hi>great and good work,</hi> to defend and promote the honour and intereſt of our Reformed Religion, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe that are deeply engaged to deſtroy it; and pray earneſtly that all who profeſs it may live in Unity and Godly Love one with another; and wherein we differ, to do it with more moderation, peace and charity: this is to do good to the publick. And in this time of difficulty, we that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined together in the ſame ſacred and ſecular intereſt, ought to unite in mutual interceſſions: <hi>to lift holy hands in prayer, and to cry mightily unto God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſ.</hi> 62.6, 7.</note> who would have his People <hi>not to hold their peace for</hi> Jeruſalem<hi>'s ſake, nor give him reſt till he hath made her a praiſe in the earth;</hi> this the Apoſtle adviſeth and directeth us to do;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>as we have opportunity let us do good unto all men, eſpecially unto them who are of the houſhold of faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are to be as ſerviceable as we can to the Church and to the State, to every particular man that is a proper object of beneficence; but eſpecially to the poor Members of Chriſt, whom we are to prefer above others; for the good we do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them our Lord will accept as done unto himſelf:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 9.41.</note> 
               <hi>Whoſoever ſhall give to drink to one of theſe</hi> little <hi>ones a cup of cold water on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in the name of a Diſciple, he ſhall in no wiſe loſe his reward.</hi> Tho' they are little in the eſteem of the World, and mean in their own Eyes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.10.</note> as <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> were, <hi>duſt and aſhes,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:51925:27"/>leſs than the leaſt of Gods mercies,</hi> yet they are very dear to Chriſt, <hi>more precious than fine Gold,</hi> Job 23.10. <hi>His Jewels, Mal.</hi> 3.17. made up of the precious graces of the Spirit, all glorious within, being beautified with divine vertues; Faith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 16.3.</note> Love, Meekneſs, Humility, <hi>&amp;c. The excellent ones;</hi> the delight and joy of his heart, whom he values as his chiefeſt treaſure, and chargeth his Angels to miniſter unto, and take care of, and therefore they ſhould be the objects of our tendereſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard; for he will reward us.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>He is not unrighteous to forget our work, and labour of love, which we have ſhewed towards his name; in that we miniſtred to the Saints and do miniſter.</hi> To this end and purpoſe God hath intruſted us with ſeveral ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages and gifts of Nature and Fortune, with more or leſs of Riches, Power, Wiſdom, Strength, Authority, Reputation, and Eſteem with great Men, Intereſt in the World, Skill in Arts and Sciences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that we may employ them all for the uſe and benefit of others: And we live in effect to no purpoſe if we do not exerciſe our Talents this way, and become very ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable ad beneficial to mankind.</p>
            <p>God hath laid the practice of doing good ſo near the heart of Piety he hath enforced it with ſo many affectionate and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſive Arguments and gracious Promiſes, and terrible Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, that we may ſafely conclude from thence, that a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal part of our preparation for Heaven lies in doing good to the Souls and Bodies of Men; inſtructing their Ignorance, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving their Prejudices, ſatisfying their Doubts, relieving their Fears, ſupplying their Wants and Neceſſities; feeding the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, cloathing the Naked, being hoſpitable to Strangers, and fruitful in all good works. This was our bleſſed Saviours con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Employment, his meat and his drink, and his dayly buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; <hi>He went about, doing good;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 10.38.</note> He laid hold on all opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and diligently ſought out diſtreſſed Objects to exerciſe his large charity upon. He hath made it an eſſential part of his Religion, and hath given us many Precepts,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.20. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.33. <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.30.</note> quickening us to the doing of much good. <hi>Lay up for your ſelves treaſures in Heaven; give Alms; provide your ſelves Bags which wax not old; a treaſure in the Heavens that fadeth not. Give to every man that asketh of thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 16.9.</note> 
               <hi>Make to your ſelves frieeds of the Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of unrighteouſneſs.</hi> And by his Apoſtles he hath command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:51925:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>us <hi>to diſtribute to the neceſſity of the Saints,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6, 7, 8.</note> to do it. cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and bountifully; becauſe God more regardeth the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Giver, then the quantity of the Gift; and in the next Life he will proportionate his rewards according to the good Works, which we do in this Life; therefore the Apoſtle earneſtly preſſeth us,;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.32.</note> 
               <hi>To abound in every good Work, to ſhew mercy with cheerfulneſs, to put on Bowels of mercy, to be kind and tender hearted one towards another,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>to be rich in good Works:</hi> rich in Faith, in Knowledge, in Works of Liberality, Mercy and Charity; theſe are <hi>Solomon's durable Riches</hi> which will follow us when we die, into the Eternal World; wealth will not do this, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6, 7. it will attend us no further than the Grave; and if we diſpenſe it not well and wiſely, but hoard it up as the unprofitable Servant did his Talent in a Napkin, <hi>the ruſt and canker thereof will be a Witneſs againſt us,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us of our unmercifulneſs in doing no good with it; it will kindle the wrath of God againſt us, and gall our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences with a vexatious remembrance of our Sin and Folly.</p>
            <p>But good Works will certainly follow us into the future Life; <hi>bleſſed are the Dead which die in the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13.</note> ſo <hi>ſaith the Spirit; for they reſt from their Labours and their Works follow them;</hi> to Witneſs for them before the great Judge of the quick and dead, and (I had almoſt ſaid) to appeaſe his Wrath,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 2 13. <hi>Dr. Ham. in locum. Mat</hi> 5.7.</note> and to prevent their Condemnation; for St. <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>mercy rejoyceth againſt Judgment.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, triumpheth over it, <hi>for the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful ſhall obtain mercy,</hi> our Saviour doth not ſay, that they ſhall Merit mercy at the hand of God, but obtain mercy; the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is plain, for when we have done all we are unprofitable Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and have not at all benefitted the infinitely Glorious and Bleſſed God by our ſervices, but only done that which was our Duty, and therefore muſt expect to receive our reward from Gods free mercy and not of merit,
<note place="margin">Non properito accipis Vitam aeternam, ſed tantum pro gratiâ Auguſt.</note> St. <hi>James</hi> is very expreſs, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.14. That we muſt be perfect and entire, wanting no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as to all the integral parts of Chriſtianity, to render us truly acceptable to God, yet this we may firmly relie upon, that no one ſingle <hi>Vertue</hi> can better qualifie us for mercy, or more effectually prevail with God to ſhew us mercy, then this of <hi>mercifulneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 8.14.</note> which is <hi>an Odour of a ſweet ſmell, a Sacrifice ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:51925:28"/>and well-pleaſing to God:</hi> the conſideration whereof ſhould induce us upon all occaſions and opportunities <hi>to do good; to be rich,</hi> copious <hi>in good Works; ready to diſtribute, willing to communicate, laying up in ſtore for our ſelves,</hi> (not for our heirs and executors) <hi>a good foundation againſt the time to come, that we may lay hold on eternal Life.</hi> 
               <q>A Life,
<note place="margin">Bp. Reynolds.</note> which may be held when the laſt general conflagration ſhall have melted all the Treaſures of the World, our good works will abide that Tryal, the Inheritance unto which they follow us is incorruptible, undefiled, and that fadeth not away, reſerved in the Heavens for us.</q> But we muſt quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our ſelves for it upon Earth, by making it the whole buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and trade of our Lives to do good: which is to act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the frame of our Natures, and to comply with the beſt of thoſe inclinations which God hath planted in us; and to do a moſt delightful and pleaſant Work, (even in the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Epicurus</hi> himſelf, the great Patron of pleaſure) which is accompanied with ſatisfaction in the preſent performance of it, and in the after reflection doth yield a huge refreſhment to our Minds, and a ſpring of peace and joy to our Souls, which far exceeds all ſenſual and bodily delights, and will moſt of all be ſweet and comfortable to us when the pains of Death are upon us, and our Souls are ready to take their flight into the eternal World; therefore if we would have our Paſſage eaſie at our Death, we muſt treaſure up now a ſtock of Comfort againſt the evil day; good Works will certainly ſupport us in the Agony of Death, and ſtand by us in the day of Judgment, and plead for us before the Righteous judge, and obtain for us a glorious Reward; a Kingdom, not purchaſed by our Works;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.34, 35, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> but prepared for us from the foundation of the World, and freely beſtowed upon us for our obedience to his Holy Laws in being kind and merciful to his ſuffering Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</p>
            <p n="5">(5) The preparation which our Lord requires to fit us for his coming, conſiſts in keeping Conſcience clear and free from of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, either by abſtaining from all filthineſs of fleſh and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, or by a ſincere endeavour (if the mind and Conſcience be defiled) to get the guilt of ſin done away by Godly ſorrow, which worketh Repentance unto Salvation: for ſo St. <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:51925:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>directs us, (alluding to the purifying under the Law by the ſprinkling of Blood.)
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>To get our hearts ſprinkled from an evil Conſcience, and to hold Faith and a good Conſcience.</hi> To this he aſſiduouſly applied himſelf with all his might;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 24.16.</note> 
               <hi>Herein do I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe my ſelf, to have alway a Conſcience void of offence towards God and Man.</hi> He made it his conſtant ſtudy, and the daily buſineſs of his life continually to live inoffenſively, and to do his duty concſcienciouſly both to God and Men. He felt the ſweetneſs and comfort of it in his Soul, when he was by the malice of the Jews impriſoned at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and brought before the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> where he makes this ſolemn profeſſion; <hi>Men and Brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 23.1.</note> 
               <hi>I have lived in all good Conſcience before God:</hi> Tho' <hi>Tertullus</hi> impleaded him with all the inſinuative Arts of Learning and Eloquence; he is able to make his own defence, ſully to anſwer the charge laid againſt him, and his home and powerful reaſonings of Temperance, Righteouſneſs and Judgment to come, made his Judg to quake and tremble.</p>
            <p>See here the great advantage a good man hath of his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, and what inviſible ſupports a good Conſcience af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords in the day of danger and adverſity:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hor. Car. L.</hi> 3. <hi>Od.</hi> 3.</note> Neither the tumults of the People, nor the face and indignation of Tyrants can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate his courage; Inocency and Virtue animate him with bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and confidence againſt all their accuſations and terrors, and lay the firmeſt foundation of a durable contentment and ſatisfaction: therefore <hi>Seneca</hi> repreſents the mind of a wiſe man by the ſtate of the ſuperior Regions, which were free from ſtorms and tempeſts, always ſerene and temperate. <hi>A good man is never without joy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ep.</hi> 59.</note> 
               <hi>his contentment groweth not, but from the Conſcience of Vertue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This made <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> when they were caſt into Priſon and thruſt into the inner Dungeon,
<note place="margin">Sanctorum ſors eſt, &amp; non me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſté ferenda.</note> and their Feet maſt faſt in the Stocks, ſing divine Hymns and Songs of praiſe to God. This was holy <hi>Job</hi>'s comfort under all thoſe piercing afflictions which beſell him: the loſs of all his Subſtance, and Children, and deſertion of his neareſt Friends and Relations. In theſe ſad and miſerable circumſtances, when there was none to pity and comfort him, the conſcience of his own innocence and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity ſupported his Spirit:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 27.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>I will never remove my integrity from me, my righteouſneſs will I hold faſt and will not let it go,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:51925:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>mine Heart, (i. e.</hi> my Conſcience) <hi>ſhall not reproach me ſo long as I live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſupported and comforted the Primitive Believers in all their Tribulations and Perſecutions, which were too great for human patience to bear: <hi>Our rejoicing is this,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>the teſtimony of our Conſcience, that in ſimplicity and godly ſincerity, not with fleſhly wiſdom, but by the grace of God we have had our converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A good Conſcience is a continual Feaſt,</hi> a Jubilee,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 15.15.</note> in that dark diſmal time, when Death is breaking that Vital Union, and making a ſeparation between Soul and Body, and the man is <hi>walking through the valley of the ſhadow of Death;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 23.4.</note> which is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry full of terrors and dangers: this will relieve his fears, fill him with unſpeakable Joys, and enable him to grapple with the King of Terrors with courage and conſtancy of mind: and to ſay with the bleſſed Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6, 7, 8</note> 
               <hi>The time of my departure is at hand, I have fought the good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the faith;</hi> upheld and maintained it, in and by my Miniſtry; and lived in the exerciſe of the grace of Faith. <hi>Henceforth there is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſneſs, which the Lord the Righteous Judge ſhall give me</hi> (of his free grace) <hi>at that day.</hi> My Soul ſhall enjoy it at my diſſolution, my whole man at the general reſurrection: Such a comfortable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture as this, free from the ſtings &amp; accuſations of Conſcience, is worth the moſt ſolicitous care &amp; earneſt endeavour of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans whole life; for when he comes to die, Conſcience will admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter unſpeakable Conſolations to him, make him lift up his head with joy, and with a cheerful countenance to ſtand before the Son of Man, and to ſay with <hi>Hezekiah, Remember now, o Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.3.</note> 
               <hi>I beſeech thee, how I have walked before thee in truth, and with a perfect heart, and have done that which is good in thy ſight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But on the contrary, the caſe of a wicked man will be very deplorable, when he falls into any calamity or affliction,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 15.24.</note> pain or Sickneſs, <hi>when the days of darkneſs are at hand:</hi> Conſcience is then moſt active, upbraiding him with the greatneſs, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and aggravations of his ſin; Guilt lies throbbing on his Soul: <hi>Trouble and anguiſh make him afraid, they ſhall prevail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, as a King ready to the Battle.</hi> Who goes forth to fight, with all the ſtrength and power of his Kingdom, attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:51925:30"/>with his Guards and Battalions of diſciplined Soldiers, and with all his Engines and Military preparations for ſlaughter and deſtruction; which ſtrikes a dread and terror into his Enemies; which fills them with fears and anxious thoughts what the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent &amp; iſſue may be. Such are the troubles and agitations of Conſcience in wicked men, and that not only of the weaker fort, but of ſuch alſo as are cloathed with Purple, and inveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Imperial Power. The mighty Monarchs of the world, ſuch as <hi>Nero, Tyberius, Caligula, &amp;c.</hi> who are above the reach of human Juſtice, theſe are not exempted from the diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets and ſtings of Conſcience; the Gripes and Convulſions of Self-conviction, and the apprehenſions and fears of a Caeleſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Tribunal, which they ſhall not eſcape, tho' they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rided and laughed at it in the day of health: But the dread and horror thereof encreaſeth upon them, as they draw near to the end of their days; and this will be the caſe of every one of us, if we do not now get our Conſciences purged from dead works, and the guilt of all our ſins cancelled by a cordial ſorrow for, and moral revocation of it: Therefore it very near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerns us to make a ſtrict and ſevere inſpection into our Conſciences, to ſtate our Account right between God and our Souls: For if any ſin remain uncroſſed, it concerns us as much as our everlaſting happineſs is worth, to ſet about it with all poſſible ſpeed and diligence, to give no reſt to our Eyes, nor ſlumber to our Eye lids, till we have by an actual repentance, and revocation of all that we have done amiſs, totally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged them, and gotten all our ſins blotted out, that they may not be found upon record againſt us; <hi>When the times of refreſhing come from the preſence of the Lord:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.1.</note> For Conſcience re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters all that we do, be it good or evil. And when the Son of Man ſhall come in the glory of his Father, and the Book of Conſcience ſhall be opened, and according to what is found written therein, we ſhall be judged, ſentenced, and rewarded; for Conſcience will be with us in Death and Judgment, either to comfort, juſtifie, and acquit us; or to terrifie, accuſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn us.</p>
            <p n="6">(6) That we may be ready for the coming of our Lord, it is neceſſity that we bear with patience and conſtancy, the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious troubles and tryals which we may meet with in this Life;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:51925:30"/>for as <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, <hi>Affliction cometh not forth of the duſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>neither doth trouble ſpring out of the ground, but Man is born unto trouble as the ſparks flie upward.</hi> Croſſes and Troubles befall us not by chance or accident, but are fore-ordained by the Wiſdom, and diſpenced by the providence of God, or by his allowance; <hi>Can a bird fall in a ſnare upon the Earth, where no Gin is for him?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 3.5. <hi>John</hi> 16.33.</note> nor induſtriouſly prepared and laid to take him; <hi>in the World we ſhall have tribulation,</hi> reproach and injuries from Men, the loſs of Goods and good Name; diſappointments in Children, Friends and Relations,; provocations to anger and revenge; ſickneſs and diſtempers in our Bodies; troubles within, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietudes anxieties of mind, which are little Deaths; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prologues, but preparatives to Death:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 14.22.</note> 
               <hi>We muſt through much tribulation enter into the Kingdom of God;</hi> even as the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> went through many hardſhips in their peregrination through the Wilderneſs to the Land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> ſo muſt we in our Pilgrimage through this World, to the Inheritance which is above, reſerved in Heaven for us. Therefore patience is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary for us, to enable us to bear our burdens, to perſevere in our Duty, and to wait for our promiſed reward. <hi>We have need of patience, that after we have done the will of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.36.</note> 
               <hi>we may receive the promiſes:</hi> Now many of the promiſes are of a long date and diſtance from us, the reward is given to thoſe that hold out unto the end, wherefore the Apoſtle adviſeth us; <hi>To ſtrengthen our ſelves with all patience and long ſuffering with joyfulneſs;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.11.</note>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1, 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>and to run with patience the race that is ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, looking unto Jeſus the author and finiſher of our Faith:</hi> who for that joyful and glorious ſtate, which was faithfully promiſed by his Father, to be the reward of his Sufferings; <hi>endured the Croſs</hi> with all the concomitants of it, <hi>deſpifing the ſhame</hi> and diſgrace poured on him by his Enemies, <hi>and is ſet down</hi> as a glorious and triumphing conqueror over Sin and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, Death and Hell, <hi>at the Right Hand of the Throne of God;</hi> the extraordinary example of ſo innocent and eminent a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ought to be regarded by us, and engage us to comply with duties of this Nature: His whole Life was one continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al exerciſe of meekneſs and patience, and that we might not be diſcouraged from doing our duty, and faint in our mind; the Apoſtle directs us, <hi>to conſider him that endured the contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:51925:31"/>of ſinners; i.e.</hi> of the Inſtruments and Abettors of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, who reviled his perſon, ſlandered his Doctrine, and blaſphemed his Miracles; yet he did obediently ſubmit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the will of God, patiently endured what was his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers good pleaſure to impoſe upon him; and did mildly bear the injuries and reproaches of his Enemies, without any inward fretting or vexing his Spirit, without any immoderate anger, hatred or revenge towards them. And all this to leave us an Example that we ſhould follow his ſteps, as in all other Graces; ſo eſpecially in this of patience, which is the beſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy to eaſe us under our burthens, and to deliver us from them; for they cannot be very injurious to us, if we calmly and mildly bear them.
<note place="margin">Horace.</note> 
               <hi>Levius fit patientiâ quicquid corrigere eſt nefas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This carried the noble Army of Martyrs through their bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſufferings, without diſcovering the leaſt ſign of impatience, and enabled them to bear the calamities and miſeries of this Life, while they waited for the rewards and felicities of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World; for if God in his Providence is pleaſed to order us our Portion of troubles here, his deſign herein is to exerciſe our Graces, to wean us from the World, to prepare us for Death,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.12. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.5.</note> and fit us for Heaven; therefore, <hi>we ſhould poſſeſs our Souls in patience; be patient in Tribulation, endure Afflictions as good Soldiers of Jeſus Chriſt, and endure unto the end:</hi> for he that bears troubles patiently, is well prepared to die peaceab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and to meet his Soveraign Lord and Judge comfortably. I conclude this point with St. <hi>Peters</hi> Counſel; <hi>Beloved, think it not ſtrange concerning the fiery Tryal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.12.13.</note> (which is ſent by God for the tryal and exerciſe of your Grace,) <hi>but rejoyce in as much as ye are partakers of Chriſts ſufferings; and made confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to him your head, that when his Glory ſhall be revealed, ye may be glad alſo with exceeding joy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">(7) A brisk and lively apprehenſion of God's all ſeeing Eye upon, and inſpection over us in all our ways, will conduce much to the fitting us for our great change. It was <hi>Seneca</hi>'s Advice to <hi>Lucilius,</hi> whatſoever he was doing, to imagine that <hi>Cato,</hi> or <hi>Scipio,</hi> or <hi>Loelius,</hi> or ſome of the Roman worthies did behold him, and then he would do nothing diſhonoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able;
<note place="margin">Epiſt.</note> 
               <hi>Do all things ſaid he, as if another looked on, it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:51925:31"/>very profitable to have a Guard over a Mans ſelf:</hi> and to conceive that ſome vertuous and excellent perſon, whom we have an high eſteem and reverence for, is a ſpectator of our actions, and hath an inſight into our very Thoughts, ſuch an apprehenſion as this, would be a great awe upon us to ſpeak and act wiſely and worthily.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> his perſon and preſence was very awful to the Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians. <hi>Ahab</hi> ſtood in fear of <hi>Elias. Joaſh</hi> was good as long as <hi>Jehojada</hi> lived. <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi>'s piety, ſanctity and graces, commanded regard and reverence from <hi>Herod:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 6.20.</note> 
               <hi>He feared</hi> John, <hi>as knowing that he was a good man, and a holy, and obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him: i. e.</hi> behaved himſelf reverently in his preſence, and ſtudied to pleaſe him in his demeanor and reſpectful carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age: was careful to avoid all occaſions of his diſcontent, and was very much delighted with his preaching: <hi>Heard him glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and did many things</hi> in obedience and conformity to his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; both in his private converſation, abſtaining from ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſins and impieties; and in his adminiſtration of publick Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, enacting ſeveral good Laws for the regular ordering of his Kingdom, and the reforming of abuſes, and for correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and reſtraining of ſeveral Vices and Immoralities. And St. <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle, by his gravity, preſence, and ghoſtly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and counſel, wrought ſo effectually upon a common Thief and Cut-throat, that he laid down his weapons of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility, trembled and wept bitterly,
<note place="margin">Euſeb. Eccl. Hiſt.</note> and in the words of my Author, was re-baptized in his own tears, and becomes a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert, a publick Miniſter of the Church of God, and an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of much good.</p>
            <p>Now if the preſence of a vertuous perſon whom we venerate hath ſo great an influence upon mens practice, certainly the belief of Gods obſerving Eye upon us will be of greater force to make us <hi>ſtand in awe and ſin not:</hi> Now that he is thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with us, we are Infidels if we believe it not, becauſe it is confirmed to us by plentiful teſtimonies: The Scripture aſſures us, <hi>That his Eyes are upon all our ways,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>they are not hid from his face, neither is our iniquity hid from his eyes: That no man can hide himſelf in ſecret places that he ſhall not ſee him.</hi> Some indeed have flattered themſelves with the hopes of ſecrecy and impunity. As particularly the Adulterer;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 16.17. <hi>Chap.</hi> 23.24</note> 
               <hi>Who ſaith in his
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:51925:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>heart no eye ſeeth me?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 6.23.</note> 
               <hi>I am compaſſed about with darkneſs, the walls cover me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">18.19.</note> 
               <hi>and no body ſeeth me, what need I to fear? the moſt high will not remember my ſin, ſuch a man only feareth the eyes of men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 24.15.</note> 
               <hi>The eye of the Adulterer waiteth for the twilight, ſaying, no eye ſhall ſee me:</hi> No common eye of men ſhall take notice of me, being under a cover of darkneſs: No eye of the Magiſtrate who is a Miniſter of Juſtice to puniſh evil doers; No, not the eye of God himſelf ſhall ſee me: But <hi>He knoweth not that the Eyes of the Lord are ten thouſand times brighter then the Sun, beholding all the ways of men, and conſidering the moſt ſecret parts.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Job</hi> 31.4.</note> 
               <hi>All the ways of man are before the eyes of the Lord, and he pondreth all his goings: he ſeeth all our ways, and counteth all our ſteps: the very ſecrets of our heart are not hid from him;</hi> much leſs our ſecret actions; every thing that we do, be it never ſo retiredly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>is naked and open to his eyes,</hi> which pierce to the very marrow of our bones, and penetrate to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of our intrails, and clearly and fully diſcern our ſecret atheiſm and unbelief, our hypocriſie and diſſimulation, our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, inclinations, and the bent of our Natures: The beauty and comlineſs, the defects and blemiſhes of a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked body are not more plain and viſible to an accurate obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, neither were the interior parts of Beaſts offered in Sacrifice, when they are excoriated, imbowelled and divided <hi>per ſpinam Dorſi,</hi> more obvious to the heathen Magicians, whoſe duty it was to obſerve the colour, ſhape, defects, and other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, whereby they might know how to order their Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations; then <hi>our ways and goings</hi> are to Gods pure and pierc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eyes, who beholds our cloſeſt artifices and ſubtileſt diſguiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, as clearly as he ſees our open and ſcandalous offences: <hi>For the darkneſs hideth not from him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 139.12.</note> 
               <hi>the night ſhineth as the day, the darkneſs and the light are both alike to him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job,</hi> 34.21, 22</note> 
               <hi>His eyes are upon the ways of man;</hi> fixedly and intentively; <hi>and he ſeeth</hi> (critically and curiouſly) <hi>all his goings; there is no darkneſs nor ſhadow of death where the workers of Iniquity may hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seneca</hi> told <hi>Lucilius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 41. <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.10. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 7.9.94.12.</note> 
               <hi>God is near unto us, he is with us, an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of our good and evil actions,</hi> the ſearcher of our hearts, who knows the ſecret motions, counſels, and affections of our Souls, and keeps acquaintance with our thoughts, and is fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:51925:32"/>with all our purpoſes and deſigns. Now if we do believe this great truth, it muſt doubtleſs be of unſpeakable uſe to us for the regular and orderly government of our lives; and make us as circumſpect and cautious of our thoughts, words, and works, as if we viſibly ſaw him ſtanding before our eyes, writing down every action of our life in order to call us to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for it. This conſideration had ſo great an influence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on holy <hi>Davids</hi> practice, that he aſſigns it as the motive of his obedience; <hi>I have remembred thy name and have kept thy Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.55. <hi>&amp;</hi> 168. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>I have kept thy Precepts and thy Teſtimonies, for all my ways are before thee;</hi> this is a powerful Amulet againſt ſin and a great preſervative of vertue, a means to make us ſincerely upright in all our ways, and to tremble to commit any ſin or wickedneſs in the ſight of our all-ſeeing Judge, before whoſe preſence we ſhall not be afraid to appear hereafter; if we ſet him before our Eyes here, as an obſerver and witneſs of our actions,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.8.</note> for thereby our hearts will be over-awed with a ſenſe of his omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſence, ſo that we ſhall walk very cautiouſly and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectly before him, having reſpect to all his Commandments, and with a concern to pleaſe him in all things; by this means death and judgment will not be formidable to us.</p>
            <p n="8">(8) That we may be ready for a comfortable paſſage into the eternal World, it is neceſſary that we poſſeſs our Souls with frequent Thoughts of Death and Mortallity. This is the earneſt and pathetical charge of the merciful and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate God, who is very heartily concerned for the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting happineſs of Men, by his eminent Servant <hi>Moſes,</hi> (whom he was pleaſed to make choice of to be the Commander and Governour of a numerous People) he beſpeaks them in a moſt affectionate and obliging manner, to remember the days of old, what great things he had done for them; in choſing them for his People, and delivering them from the hand of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> by a mighty hand and an out ſtretched arm, in preſerving them at the Red Sea, and in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in ſubduing the Nations about them; and in giving them poſſeſſion of the Land of Promiſe, flowing with Milk and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: he intreats them to conſider the tranſitorineſs of their condition, and to withdraw their affections from Farthly Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. <hi>O that they were wiſe to conſider their latter end,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.29.</note> to ſtudy
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:51925:33"/>and apply their minds to that holy wiſdom which would fit them for Life eternal.</p>
            <p>We are now Gods peculiar People, he is as ſolicitous for our happineſs and ſalvation as once he was for the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and with the ſame tender affection doth he importune us to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our end, and to what Eternity we are going, whether to bliſs or miſery; we are but Sojourners and Pilgrims here, <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 13, 14.</note> no continuing City,</hi> no certain abiding place; our condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion here is fleeting and vaniſhing,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.14.</note> we know not whether we ſhall continue here till to morrow; <hi>for what is our Life? it is even a Vapour,</hi> exhaled from the Earth by the influence of the heavenly Bodies,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.20.</note> 
               <hi>that appears for a little time, and then va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth away,</hi> like <hi>a Tale</hi> that is told, which is at an end, e're we conſider it; or as <hi>a Dream,</hi> when one awaketh ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which diſappears: being then that we are ſuch weak crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.4.</note> we ſhould pray with <hi>David, Lord make me to know my end and the number of my days, that I may know how frail I am,</hi> and how near to death; <hi>ſo teach us to number our days that we</hi> (paſſing by the cares the glories and pleaſures of this World) <hi>may apply our hearts with all diligence unto true wiſdom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">90.12.</note> which is to be wiſe unto Salvation. For the attainment whereof, and for the more effectual impreſſing upon our minds, deep and ſerious thoughts of our mortal ſtate; it is expedient that we viſit ſick and dying perſons as oft as opportunity invites us: not only to condole with them, and to afford them our pity and compaſſion in their affliction,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 6.14. <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.21. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.2, 3.</note> which is ſome alleviation of their miſery; to adminiſter ſeaſonable comforts to them, to give them ghoſtly advice and counſel, to bear with patience the chaſtiſements of the Lord, and humbly to reſign themſelves to his wiſe diſpoſal: but alſo to ſtir up in our ſelves ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Pious and Devout Conſiderations of our approaching Change.</p>
            <p>In the preſence of dying Perſons, there is repreſented both to our eye and mind many objects, that will naturally ſuggeſt to us holy Meditations, ſerious and awful Thoughts of Death and Eternity. There we may ſee the perſon viſited ſtrugling with ſtrong pains of bitter Agonies; and Death ſit in his ghaſtly countenance, we may hear the rueful Groans of his expiring nature, and obſerve him exerciſed with Soul-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:51925:33"/>with great terrors of mind, and with powerful convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſin, and dreadful apprehenſions of the wrath of God, unfit perhaps to die, and yet paſt all hopes of continuing long in this tranſitory life.</p>
            <p>There we may ſee the mournful looks of the ſpectators, and hear the bitter lamentations and cries of Wife and Children, and obſerve the trickling tears of dear Relations. For if <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the Great wept when he heard of the death of <hi>Darius;</hi> and <hi>Caeſar</hi> at the relation of <hi>Pompey</hi>'s; and <hi>Titus Veſpaſian</hi> at the miſerable deſtruction of the Jews; how ſhall they refrain from tears at the ſight of a dying Friend ſtrugling with the pains of Death, and perhaps doubting of his ſalvation? Such a ſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacle as this will adminiſter to us ſuch thoughts as theſe. This perſon is now about putting off his Earthly Tabernacle, his Soul is entring into the Confines of Eternity, and his Body ere long will be a prey to Death, and be laid down in the cold and ſilent Grave, where the Worms ſhall be its companions till it hath put on rottenneſs and corruption. The Angels will convey the immaterial Soul to the Bar of Judgment to receive ſentence to its eternal ſtate. This is a viſible inſtruction to me really to converſe with ſickneſs and weakneſs; and to think that it will not be long but I ſhall feel and endure mortal pains and the miſeries of a Death bed; I ſhall breath ſhort, feel cold ſweats &amp; dying pangs: My Body which I am now ſo indulgent and tender of ſhall be wrapped in a Shroud, be nailed up in a Coffin,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.12.</note> and carried forth as the Widow of <hi>Nain</hi>'s Son was, upon the ſhoulders of men, to be intombed in the Grave the Houſe of all living; and my immortal Soul ſhall expire, and go to God who gave it, to be rewarded and ſentenced accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the things done in the body.</p>
            <p>Such ſerious thoughts as theſe will be a ſovereign Antidote againſt all Sin and Wickedneſs; and diſpoſe and prepare us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand, that when the critical moment comes we may not run the great hazard of miſcarrying for ever: For in the day of Death we play the laſt Game for everlaſting Felicity or endleſs Miſery, ſo that we had need to do it wiſely and warily, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe an uncorruptible Crown of Life and Glory depends upon it; the winning whereof will make us unſpeakably happy, and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:51925:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>the loſing of it eternally miſerable, beyond all humane appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion. Thus have I ſhewed at large, both generally and particularly, wherein this preparation does conſiſt, becauſe the burden of the Text lies upon it.</p>
            <p n="2">(II) I proceed now to the ſecond thing in order of method, which is to manifeſt the urgent neceſſity of this <hi>readineſs,</hi> and the great obligations which lie upon us to be always prepared for death, and the Son of Mans coming: The omniſcient God, (who certainly knows what is beſt for our preſent good, and future happineſs) hath very warmly preſſed it home up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our hearts, by many Precepts and Commands: the work it ſelf is difficult, the time allotted us to do it in is very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious; life it ſelf is very ſhort and uncertain, and Death ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitable, and if we be not prepared for our change by inherent holineſs and ſanctification, we ſhall fall ſhort of happineſs. So that upon theſe accounts it is abſolutely neceſſary that we be always in readineſs.</p>
            <p n="1">(1) The omniſcient God (who certainly knows what is beſt for our preſent good and future happineſs) hath very warmly and earneſtly preſſed it home upon our hearts by many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, which he hath inculcated in the Scriptures; that we (knowing our Duty) may yield a cheerful and and filial obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Throughout this whole Chapter of the Text, we are taught that the coming of our Lord will be very ſudden, like <hi>Lightning</hi> which in the twinkling of an eye,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 27.</note> darts through the Air, and ſurprizes the Inhabitants of the Earth before they are aware of it, or can avoid it; that it will be at a time when the ſpirit of ſecurity hath ſeized the hearts of Men, and they are given up to ſenſuality and debauchery, wholy unconcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at all Gods invitations and warnings; and unmindful of the great things which belongs to their everlaſting Peace.</p>
            <p>This was the caſe of the old World, and of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 37, 38. <hi>Luke</hi> 17.28, 29, 30.</note> in the day of <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Lot; They did eat, they drank, they bought, they ſold, they planted, they builded;</hi> they went on ſecurely in their luxurious courſes, and lived in a careleſs regard of their Duty, <hi>till the day that</hi> Lot <hi>went out of Sodom;</hi> when God rained down fire and brimſtone from Heaven upon them, and deſtroyed them all; even ſo ſhall it
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:51925:34"/>be, in the day when the Son of Man is revealed. Now the time of his coming being concealed from us, lays the greateſt obligation upon us to be Vigilant, <hi>watch therefore,</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 42. <hi>Mark</hi> 30.33, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>watch and pray,</hi> for ye know not when the time is, for the Son of Man is as a Man taking a far journey, who left his Houſe, and gave authority to his Servants, and to every Man his work, and commanded the Porter to watch; watch ye there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for ye know not when the maſter of the Houſe cometh, at even, or at midnight, or at the cock-crowing, or in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; leſt coming ſuddenly he find you ſleeping, and what I ſay unto you <hi>I ſay unto all, watch.</hi> The deſign of which precept is to engage all of us to abſtain from all ſin, and to be diligent and induſtrious in doing of our duty, that at what time ſoever our Lord cometh, we may be <hi>ready:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 21.34, 35, 36.</note> 
               <hi>Take heed to your ſelves leſt at any time your hearts be overcharged with Surfeiting, and Drunkenneſs, and the cares of this Life, and ſo that day come upon you unawares;</hi> the day of particular or general Judgment: <hi>For as a ſnare it ſhall come upon all that dwell on the face of the Earth; watch ye therefore and pray always that ye may be able to ſtand before the Son of Man;</hi> to ſtand with cheerfulneſs and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, without fear of condemnation in the laſt Judgment, <hi>for the ungodly ſhall not ſtand in judgment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.5.</note> nor be able to lift up their heads before the preſence of the ſevere Judge; <hi>becauſe they have not been diligent to be found of him in peace, without ſpot or blemiſh.</hi> The deſign of our Lord in the Parable of the Ten Virgins is to preſs upon all Chriſtians the urgent neceſſity of a conſtant preparation for his coming; and not to content themſelves with having Lamps, and making a bare profeſſion of Religion, but to keep <hi>Oyl in their veſſels with their Lamps; i. e.</hi> truth of grace, fruits of the ſpirit, and works of mercy: <hi>To have their Lamps trimmed, their Loins girded about, and their lights burning, as thoſe that look for their Lord.</hi> Herein lay the Wiſdom of the prudent Virgins, they provided Oyl in ſtore to repleniſh their Lamps; a good ſtock of faith, and love, and other divine graces to feed and maintain their profeſſion, and they trimmed their Lamps, and took care to prepare themſelves for the Bridegrooms coming, by which means they being found <hi>ready;</hi> were at his coming admitted by him into the place of Nuptial entertainments.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:51925:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>But the indiſcretion of the improvident and formal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, lay in pleaſing themſelves with an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>falſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction,</hi> they traded for the <hi>goodly Pearl, the rich Treaſure hid in a Field,</hi> but they did it ſo unſeaſonably and coldly, that they were not ſenſible of their miſtake, till it was too late to retrieve and amend it. The Bridegroom came when they were not in a readineſs to receive him, and ſo the door was ſhut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and tho' they cryed with earneſt intreaties and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geminations, <hi>Lord, Lord, open to us,</hi> yet there was no admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for them, they were for ever excluded. Which diſmal Fate of theirs, teacheth us this uſeful inſtruction, To improve the preſent ſeaſons of Grace, and to work while it is to day; <hi>For when the Night cometh no Man can work;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 9 4.</note> as the Tree falleth ſo it lieth; <hi>if it fall toward the South, or toward the North, in the place where the Tree falleth, there it ſhall lie;</hi> which Scripture is thus interpreted by a learned Author.
<note place="margin">Olympiodor in Eccles.</note> 
               <hi>In whatſoever place therefore, whether of light or darkneſs, whether in the work of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, or vertue, a Man is taken at his death; in that degree and rank, doth he remain either in light with the juſt, and Chriſt the King of all; or in darkneſs with the wicked, and Prince of the World.</hi> There is no rectifying the errors of this Life, in the next, the day of Grace ends with this Life; here all the Eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Graces of a Chriſtian are to be acquired; in the future ſtate he ſhall receive his reward <hi>according to the things done in the Body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. Victoris Erabdum.</note> 
               <hi>whether they be good or bad:</hi> After we are gon from hence, <hi>There remains no place for repentance, no effect or benefit of ſatisfaction, here Life is either loſt, or obtained; and at the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of death, thou haſt a paſſage hence to immortality:</hi> So that whatever is done by us to obtain the favour of God and a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed immortality, muſt be done in this World. <q rend="margQuotes">The time of this Life,
<note place="margin">Dr. Sherlock. upon Death.</note> is all the preparation time that ever will be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded to us to work out our Salvation:</q> There is no middle ſtate or place (as they of the Roman communion, do fondly fancy) to do it in: we conſiſt but of two parts, <hi>Body and Soul;</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> hath aſſured us that when we die,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccles.</hi> 12.7.</note> 
               <hi>the body returns to the Earth</hi> from whence it originally came, <hi>Fundamentum ex pulvere, et in pulvere finis ejus, and the Soul to God that gave it.</hi> The holy Angels conveyed <hi>Lazarus</hi> his Soul at his death into <hi>Abraham</hi>'s boſom; immediately upon its ſeparation from the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:51925:35"/>Body, ſo ſaith the Spirit, <hi>from henceforth,</hi> from the inſtant of their dying, <hi>the dead are bleſſed; and reſt from their labours,</hi> from all the labours of their Chriſtian calling, their Race is at an end, their courſe is finiſhed, and the crown is to be received: All the Divine graces and Religious diſpoſitions of mind, which are requiſite to fit the Soul for Heaven, and make it happy when it leaves the Body, muſt be obtained and exerciſed in the Body; <hi>So that to day, whilſt it is called to day, we muſt ſeriouſly mind and proſecute the things which belong to our peace;</hi> and give obedience to the Commands of God, which are reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and eaſie; advantagious to our intereſt, and do claim a Priority in our affections and endeavours, for ſo we are directed <hi>to remember now our Creator, and to ſeek the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, and his righteouſneſs in the firſt place;</hi> for by ſo doing we not only ſecure to our ſelves the temporal Emolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this Life, ſo far as the wiſdom of God ſeeth them good for us, but diſpoſe and prepare our ſelves for eternal Glory; and our obedience ſhall not miſs of a ſuitable reward.</p>
            <p n="2">ii. The ſolemn work of preparation for Death and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is difficult, it is not every one that ſaith, <hi>Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, but he that doth the will of his Father which is in Heaven;</hi> that ſincerely endeavours to fulfil the whole will of God by faith and holyneſs. The truth &amp; pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of piety lies not in a mouthful of good words; <hi>be ye warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, be ye filled, be ye cloathed;</hi> nor in a meer outſide Form of worſhip, but in practice; 'tis not enough for us to live inof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſively and harmleſly, to abſtain from that which is evil, but we muſt actually do good, and abound in fruits of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs. 'Tis a great work to die well, and unleſs we do lay up an ample ſtock of ſpiritual preparations, we ſhall never be able to go ſafely through the dark paſſage of death to Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Aſſure your ſelves, dear Souls, that a few penitent reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, forced promiſes, death-bed ſorrows, mournful tears, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy looks, formal prayers, and crying God's mercy, and asking him forgiveneſs, will not ſerve the turn and prove effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual; no we muſt put forth the moſt painful efforts of our Souls, in mortifying our earthly Members, in conquering vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous habits, in regulating diſordered appetites, in governing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws of reaſon and religion all the faculties of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:51925:36"/>our Souls, in eradicating ſtrong prejudices from our Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, in bending our obſtinate and rebellious Will, in regulating unruly Affections, in taming wild extravagant Paſſions, in guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our Hearts from vain Thoughts and inordinate Deſires, in ſubduing powerful Luſts which war againſt the Soul; in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting temptations, and repelling the fiery darts of the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Enemy of our Salvation, in fighting manfully under Chriſt's Banner againſt Sin, the World, the Devil, and the rebellious Fleſh, in curbing its impetuous and eager deſires, in bridling our Tongues from idle, obſcene, and unſavoury talk, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting our ſteps in the ſtraight path of holineſs; in ſuſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Croſſes, Afflictions and Troubles with a generous patience and unſhaken conſtancy; doing our duty faithfully to God, conſcientiouſly waiting upon him in his Ordinances, ſtudying to know his Pleaſure, to do his Will, to obey his Commands, to promote his Intereſt &amp; advance his Glory in the World. We ſhall have need of ſincere Repentance, Faith unfeigned, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaken Patience, univerſal Charity, ſeraphyck Love, invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Conſtancy, an humble ſubmiſſion to the Will of God to bring down the Joys of Heaven into our Souls, perſeverance unto the end, and a well grounded hope of partaking with the Saints in joys unſpeakable and full of glory; unleſs our Souls be habited and attired with theſe goodly vertues we ſhall be very unfit to die and to appear in Judgment. Now to obtain theſe heavenly Graces is the work which we are to apply our ſelves unto with diligence and vigour: For every Vertue hath its peculiar difficulty:
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.11. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.3.</note> Faith is called the <hi>work</hi> of Faith. 'Tis a difficult thing to believe the Exiſtence of things; <hi>which eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, neither is the heart of man able to conceive</hi> the immortality of the Soul, and the exiſtence of it in an immaterial world. It's hard to believe firmly all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and threatnings of the Word; to rely upon Chriſt alone for Salvation; perfectly to ſubmit our Underſtandings, and to reſign our Wills to his holy will. Repentance is a work not eaſily wrought upon the Soul; though it be highly reaſonable that when we have done contrary to our duty, we ſhould be cordially ſorry for it; reſolve to do ſo no more, and labour to undo what we have done amiſs by godly ſorrow and compun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of heart; humble confeſſion to God, and reſtitution to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:51925:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>Men: yet experience ſheweth that it is very hard to do this. <hi>Gan the Aethiopian change his skin, or the Leopard his ſpots:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.23.</note> 
               <hi>then may ye alſo do good that are accuſtomed to do evil,</hi> Hence it is called <hi>renovation,</hi> a <hi>new creation, regeneration,</hi> a <hi>new birth,</hi> in which there is pain and difficulty. <hi>Charity</hi> is a laborious exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of many good works; it conſiſts in the performance of ſeveral kind Offices: The Chriſtian muſt exert that <hi>labour</hi> of love mentioned by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Temperance</hi> is a vertue not eaſily attained; it requires preſence of mind, and great wiſdom, to regulate unruly Appetites, and to govern un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Luſts, which are fired by a ſmall ſpark of temptations; and to withſtand the allurements of pleaſure, to refuſe the courtſhips and ſolicitations of jolly Companions, to ſhun the ſnares of their wild examples, and to bear with evenneſs and equanimity of mind the ſcoffs and ſarcaſms of thoſe patrons and encouragers of Vice and Vanity, who can have no kindneſs for thoſe that will not run with them the ſame risk of madneſs and extravagance.</p>
            <p>The like might be ſhewed concerning <hi>meekneſs, humility, ſelf-denial</hi> and <hi>reſignation</hi> to the Divine Will; <hi>patience, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedneſs,</hi> and all other Divine Graces which are from above, from the Father of Lights, who is the giver of Grace and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and hath placed them out of our reach, that we might take pains to acquire them by fervent Prayer and Devotion, and exert great diligence in the practice of them. For ſince it is appointed for Men to die but <hi>once,</hi> we ſhould do all we can to prepare our ſelves to die happily; and as St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>in the Lord,</hi> that we may live for ever with the Lord.</p>
            <p n="3">iii. The time allowed us to prepare for Eternity is precious, for it is very ſhort, if we meaſure time according to the lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt extention of it; for all that ſpace of this preſent life which is allowed us to do the works of our Callings in is exceeding ſhort; but if we take it for the <hi>opportunity</hi> of time, or the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſeaſon</hi> for the making our Calling and Election ſure, and ſecuring our everlaſting ſtate, 'tis much ſhorter. Of all the outward bleſſings and comforts which God is pleaſed to beſtow upon us in this life, he is not ſo frugal and provident in any of them as he is in the diſtribution of our time. He confers upon
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:51925:37"/>us the comfortable accommodation of this world in great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance: but Time he proportions to us in a continual ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of days, and hours, and minutes, ſo that we never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy two of them together, but as one paſſeth away he gives us another: and yet how profuſe and laviſh are we in the expence of them. A conſiderable part of our time we have waſted in childiſh vanities, and when we came to maturity of years, and conſiſtency of reaſon, we ſpent no ſmall part of it in gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying inordinate appetites, and in ſenſual pleaſures. So that before we ſeriouſly conſider the end for which we were crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the major part of our time is elapſed beyond revocation; and we croud up this ſolemn work of preparation for Eternity into a narrow compaſs. It concerns us therefore to redouble our diligence, to redeem the time, and to encreaſe in all Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>adding to our faith, vertue; and to vertue, knowledge, &amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5, 6, 7. <hi>To reach forth</hi> (with the bleſſed St: <hi>Paul) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe things that are before;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.13, 14</note> to ſtretch as hard as we can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that meaſure of holineſs which we have not yet attained; <hi>to preſs toward the mark,</hi> that we may win the prize of eternal Glory: and the rather ſhould we exert the greateſt vigour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have but little time to do the work of him that ſent us,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.29, 30, 31.</note> in. <hi>The time is ſhort;</hi> furled like Sails when the Mariner hath finiſhed his Voyage and is come into the Haven; ſo that we ſhould be careful to improve it to our beſt advantage, which is a ſpecial point of wiſdom: <hi>commendable avarice,</hi> as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nulla niſi temporis honeſta eſt avaritia.</hi> We are allowed to <hi>covet</hi> earneſtly <hi>the beſt things,</hi> amongſt which this precious jewel of time may be reckoned; and therefore not to be waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in fruitleſs paſtimes, and carnal contentments; in earthly pleaſures and overmuch ſecular negotiations of this life; much leſs in wicked projects or ſinful practices, but in adorning our Souls with ſuch virtuous diſpoſitions as will fit us for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, and the ſociety of the Saints in the future ſtate of Glory: When we come to die, one of thoſe days or hours which we have vainly waſted will be of more value to us then all this world.</p>
            <p>It is ſcarce poſſible for us in the day of health and proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to conceive how valuable Time will then appear to us. We ſhall ſadly repent that we have ſpent any part of it in worldli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:51925:37"/>ambition, idleneſs, ſenſual gratifications or ſinful luſts. We ſhall heartily wiſh that we had improved every mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute of it in the ſpiritual and everlaſting concernments of our Souls; and to be ſure (if we have any preſence of Mind, and the uſe of our Reaſon) we ſhall then imploy every minute of it (which is free from diſturbances and interruptions) in finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our laſt preparatory work on Earth, in order to our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing before our great Judge: It will be our wiſdom to do that now with all our might which we ſhall then be ſo intent upon, becauſe a few ſands more will bring us to that ſtate in which we ſhall remain for ever, and leave us in Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            <p n="4">iv. The urgent neceſſity of ſuch a ſolemn preparation as I have deſcribed, will farther appear if we conſider that life it ſelf (which is the moſt valuable treaſure, the richeſt Jewel in this World) is very ſhort and uncertain, and Death inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Life is very ſhort: The moſt fading and vaniſhing things in Nature are made uſe of by the Penmen of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to ſet forth the brevity of the life of man: 'Tis repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>a Dream,</hi> which for a little while affects the Fancy;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 20.8.</note> but when the man awakes (if not before) it vaniſheth away: By <hi>a Flower</hi> of the Field, or the <hi>Graſs</hi> of the Earth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 73.20.90.6.103.15.</note> which in the Morning is green and flouriſhing, but in the Evening is cut down, dried up, and withered. <hi>As for man his days are as graſs, as a flower of the field ſo he flouriſheth;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 14.2.</note> 
               <hi>he cometh up like a flower, and is cut down, he fleeth as a ſhadow and continueth not:</hi> His life ſlips away ſuddenly, like <hi>a Tale</hi> that is told; his beauty, ſtrength, and all his excellencies conſume away like <hi>a Moth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 13.28.7.6.9.25, 26.</note> which by eating and fretting a Garment ſpoils the glory of it. Sometimes the life of man is compared to <hi>a Weavers Shuttle,</hi> which is an Inſtrument of a very ſwift motion, and paſſeth the Loomb or Web ſpeedily. Sometimes it is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>a ſwift Poſt,</hi> which rideth upon fleet Horſes, and haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en his ſpeed by land. To <hi>ſwift Ships</hi> of <hi>Ebeh,</hi> a River in the Eaſt where <hi>Job</hi> lived; which by the force and ſtrength of its Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, added ſwiftneſs to the Veſſels which ſailed faſt upon it. And foraſmuch as an <hi>Eagle</hi> (of all the Fowls of the Air) is the ſwifteſt and ſtrongeſt of wing,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 40.31</note> 
               <hi>they ſhall mount up with
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:51925:38"/>wings as Eagles,</hi> which ſoar aloft in the Air, ſo high, that the eye of man cannot ſee them; yet themſelves are ſo quick-ſighted, that they can diſcern their prey at that vaſt diſtance, and ſowce down upon it like a Thunderbolt, hunger adding ſwiftneſs to their wings: therefore <hi>Job</hi> makes uſe of that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem to ſet forth the ſhortneſs of the life of man,</p>
            <p>Among the Evangelical Writers, we find St. <hi>Paul</hi> comparing it to <hi>a Race.</hi> And to the end we may perform our Chriſtian Courſe well, he adviſeth us to imitate the Roman and Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian Racers, who when they were to run for the Prize, put off their cumberſom cloaths, that they might run with briskneſs and agility, ſo as to obtain the reward, which was a leafy Crown, made up of Bay's or Lawrel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A fading, corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and periſhing one: but we Chriſtians run for an incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible Crown,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</note> an immortal Inheritance, that ſadeth not away, laid up in ſtore for us. Wherefore we are the more obliged <hi>to lay aſide every weight,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>and the Sin which doth ſo eaſily beſet us, and run with patience the Race that is ſet before us;</hi> for it is but ſhort, and will ſoon be over. <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, Thou haſt made my days as an hand breadth,</hi> which is one of the leaſt meaſures, whether we take it in the largeſt dimenſion and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panſion of the hand, or in the more reſtrained limitation; the breadth only of the hand: in both which reſpects it is very ſhort; an <hi>inch long,</hi> ſaith
<note n="*" place="margin">In Carmine Lyrico, Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch &amp; Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca.</note> 
               <hi>Alcaeus,</hi> much ſhorter yet in the grave Moraliſts Opinions, who ſtile it but <hi>a Point. Punctum eſt quod vivimus, &amp; adhuc puncto minus.</hi> But St. <hi>James,</hi> who ſpake by a more excellent ſpirit,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Job</hi> 14.1.</note> repreſents it more diminutively, in that he calls it <hi>a meer Appearance.</hi> What is your life? it is even <hi>a Vapour that appeareth for a little while, and then vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth away,</hi> Man that is born of a woman is of few days. Few in compariſon of the Antidiluvian Patriarchs from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Noah,</hi> who lived near a thouſand years; fewer yet in regard of the years of <hi>Abraham,</hi> whoſe life was prolonged but to one hundred threeſcore and fifteen years,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.7, 8.</note> and yet <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith of him, <hi>that he died in a good old Age, an old man, and full of years.</hi> In <hi>Moſes</hi>'s time it was limited to <hi>threeſcore years and ten,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 90. <hi>A Pſalm of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſes, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and if by reaſon of ſtrength men come to fourſcore years</hi> (which is a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and extraordinary favour) <hi>yet is their ſtrength then but labour and ſorrow;</hi> and through weakneſs and infirmities of Age, they
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:51925:38"/>are a burden to themſelves, unable to bear the aches and pains, and indiſpoſitions and diſeaſes incident to their ſickly natures, and unfit to perform the acts and offices of Religion and Repentance towards God, and in a little time they are cut off, and gone to their long homes, where they can never have any more opportunities of Repentance: <hi>In a moment</hi> (which is the ſhorteſt parcel of time that we can imagine) <hi>they go down to the Grave,</hi> and on a ſudden vaniſh away. Lo! this is the length of the ſhort life of man; and ſince we muſt ſhortly put off this Tabernacle of Fleſh and Bones, it concerns us as much as our Souls are worth, to prepare them with grace and holineſs, that they may be fit for the appearance of Chriſt, and be precious and lovely in his eyes; and that we may not be terrified and affrighted at his coming, as thoſe Kings of the Earth, and great Men, and rich Men, and chief Captains, and mighty Men, whom St. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of in the Revelation:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 6.15, 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>Who ſhall then hide themſelves in the Dens, and in the Rocks of the Mountains; and ſay to the Mountains and Rocks fall on us, and hide us from the face of him that ſitteth on the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb; for the great day of his wrath is come, and who ſhall be able to ſtand?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is very uncertain; <hi>Man knoweth not his time, as the Fiſhes that are taken in an evil Net; and as the Birds that are caught in the ſnare, ſo are the ſons of men ſnared in an evil time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.9.12.</note> 
               <hi>when it falleth ſuddenly upon them.</hi> Death often comes when perſons are moſt ſecure and careleſs, and leaſt expect it. <hi>Dives</hi> (the repreſentative of the Voluptuous World) promiſed himſelf long life, ſecular proſperity, and the fulleſt ſatisfactions that the creature could afford. To that end he reſolved to make the largeſt preparations for many years Feſtival living: He ſaid to himſelf, <hi>This will I do, I will pull down my Barns,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 12.18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>and build greater, and there will I beſtow all my Fruits, and my Goods; and I will ſay to my Soul; Soul, thou haſt much Goods laid up for many years, take thine eaſe, eat, drink, and be merry.</hi> But alas! all his projects failed him, and his deſigns were diſappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; for he never ſaw the light of another day. <hi>God ſaid unto him, thou fool, this night thy Soul ſhall be required of thee: Then whoſe ſhall all thoſe things be which thou haſt provided?</hi> And for ought the wiſeſt of us know, this may be our own caſe;
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:51925:39"/>while we are ſeeking after the fulneſs of earthly contentments and delights, our Souls may be ſeparated from the embraces of their Bodies, and all our hopes periſh. Do not our lives depend upon many uncertainties, diſeaſes, and fatal accidents? See we not,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 120.</note> ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi> to <hi>Lucilius,</hi> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">How many incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities do torment us; ſometimes we complain of our heads, then of our breaſt and throat; ſometimes we are pained in our Nerves, and vexed in our feet; to day the Flux, to morrow a Rheum diſturbs us; ſometimes too much blood, ſometimes too little; every way we are troubled. <hi>Nihil ſatis eſt morituris, nihil morientibus;</hi> There is nothing that contenteth us that are to die, nay that die every day: for we daily approach our laſt hour, and there is not a day or hour that driveth us not into the Grave, where we muſt reſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It is obſerved by <hi>Gallen</hi> and <hi>Hippocrates</hi> that Man is more liable to diſeaſes and diſtempers, and his life is more endanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them then any other Creature;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12.</note> the reaſon may be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath ſinned more then they; <hi>for by ſin, Death</hi> (with all its antecedents, fore runners and harbingers) <hi>entred into the world, and ſo paſſed upon all men, for that all have ſinned.</hi> There is not the leaſt diſeaſe incident to our frail nature, but hath been armed with power ſufficient to conquer and overcome. Some die by Fevers, as <hi>Veſpaſian, Antonius, Julius</hi> the 2d. and <hi>Boniface</hi> the 9th;
<note place="margin">Platina &amp; Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aut in vit.</note> others by Apoplexies, as <hi>Valentinian</hi> the Emperor, Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the 2d. occaſioned by his intemperate eating of Melons. Sometimes by Gouts, as <hi>Septimius Severus, Julius</hi> the 3d. <hi>Sozimus</hi> the Syrian, and <hi>Sixtus</hi> the 4th; others by the Stone and Cholick, as <hi>Gregory</hi> the 11th. and <hi>Pius</hi> the 5th; Some by Pluriſies, as <hi>Gelaſius</hi> the 2d. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> others by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent pain and anguiſh, as <hi>Craſſus</hi> the Orator, <hi/> ſome have ended their days in tranſports of Joy, as <hi>Philippides</hi> the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>median, when his Lauriat Poems were preferred; and <hi>Diaggo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi> of <hi>Rhodes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bp. Taylor's great Ex. part</hi> 3. <hi>diſc.</hi> 20.</note> and <hi>Chilon</hi> the Philoſopher, embracing their Sons crowned with Olympick Lawrels; others have expired in exceſs of ſorrow.</p>
            <p>Many have loſt their lives by overmuch fulneſs, repletion and ingurgitation of meats and drinks; but more have periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by pinching Famine. O the havock and deſolation which
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:51925:39"/>it made at the Sieges of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Samaria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5.25. <hi>Joſeph de bello Jud. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 7, 8.</note> when the poor miſerable Jews did for very penury eat their Girdles, Shoes, and the Skins that covered their Shields, and an Aſſes Head, which hath but little meat upon it, and that alſo, both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholſome and unclean by Law, was ſold for 80 pieces of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, which amount to about 5 <hi>l.</hi> of our Money; a vaſt price for ſo ſmall a pittance,
<note place="margin">Mille modis lethi miſeros <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> una fatigat.</note> and the 4th part of a Kab, or quart of Peaſe, for 5 pieces of Silver.</p>
            <p>Death is every day making its approaches near to us with ſpeedy and undiſcerned ſteps, it follows us, and will arreſt us e're we be aware of it; but when, or how, we know not, every breath we draw may be our laſt, and the next ſtep we take, may be into the Grave. Who ſees not then the abſolute neceſſity of being always ready for his departure hence? <hi>No man dies ſo cheerfully as he that hath prepared and compoſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for it by a foregoing preparation.</hi> Death will not wait for us one moment, and therefore it is extremely dangerous to flatter our ſelves with hopes and expectations of long life, and that we ſhall repent hereafter; for we have not one day, or hour, or minute at our diſpoſal. <hi>Qui poenitenti veniam ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondit, peccanti craſtinum diem non promiſit.</hi> Death ſpares none, neither for age nor manners. We ſee the Roſe-buds are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered as well as the ripe Roſes. Many young perſons are ſnatched away in the flower of their time and ſtrength.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 10.22. <hi>ch.</hi> 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>The Grave is without order, there are ſmall and great in it. Goliah</hi> not too bigg, <hi>David</hi>'s Child not too little to fill a Tomb.</p>
            <p>So that upon this account we ought to live in a conſtant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of Death, and the coming of our Lord, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of every day in ſuch ſort, as if it did lead to the conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of our lives,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed are thoſe Servants whom the Lord when he cometh ſhall find ſo doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">(3.) As Life is very ſhort and uncertain, ſo Death is inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and therefore the preparation for it is indiſpenſibly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary: the very Heathens wondred not to ſee Bodies com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of earthly materials diſſolve into duſt and aſhes. <hi>What man is he that liveth and ſhall not ſee death?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ</hi> 89, 48,</note> There is an <hi>Ero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſis</hi> in the words, a Figure peculiar to the Idioms of the <hi>Hebr.</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> Tongues; we frequently meet with it in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:51925:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>as in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 58.3. <hi>Who can declare his Generation? i. e,</hi> None can,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.13.</note> becauſe he is eternal. Again, <hi>To which of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ſaid he at any time, thou art my Son, &amp;c. i. e.</hi> He never ſaid ſo to any of them. So in theſe words of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogation bears the force of a poſitive affirmation; <hi>There is no man living ſhall eſcape death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 3.13, 14, 15.</note> for it is the end of all men: <hi>Of Kings and Counſellors of the Earth, of Princes and great War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, of Oppreſſors and Priſoners, of Captives and mean Perſons, of Maſters and Servants, of Small and Great,</hi> all go to the place of Silence, <hi>where the wicked ceaſe from troubling, and the weary be at reſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">17 <hi>v.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Your Fathers (that have been in all Ages before you) where are they?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>and the Prophets</hi> (that Preached to you, and warned you of your danger) <hi>do they live for ever?</hi> Theſe are all laid down in the duſt, and we muſt all follow in our order; <hi>i. e.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27.</note> 
               <hi>It is appointed unto men once to dye;</hi> none ſhall eſcape the irreverſible decree, ſave thoſe that ſhall be found alive at the coming of Chriſt.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.51, 52.</note> 
               <hi>Behold, I ſhew you a myſtery, we ſhall not all ſleep, but we ſhall all be changed, in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye, at the laſt Trump; for the Trumpet ſhall ſound, and the dead ſhall be raiſed incorruptible, and we ſhall be changed:</hi> which change ſhall be either by their dying for a ſhort time, and then reviving again, as the <hi>Sleep</hi> there mentioned ſeems to imply; or elſe by the mighty power of God, their natural and corruptible bodies ſhall be changed into ſpiritual and incorruptible bodies, which change ſhall be equivalent to death; but all other perſons <hi>ſhall ſee death,</hi> and undergo the common fate of all mankind. Neither <hi>Achitophel</hi>'s Policy, nor <hi>David</hi>'s Piety, nor <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Wiſdom, nor <hi>John Baptiſt</hi>'s Zeal for God, nor <hi>Tertullus</hi> his Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Tongue, nor <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Philoſophy, nor <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory, nor <hi>Bathſheba</hi>'s Beauty, nor <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Strength, nor <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus</hi> his Harp could charm Death, nor prevent its all-ſubduing Conqueſts. <hi>Death knocks at the Palaces of Princes as well as poor mens Cottages.</hi> What is become of all the Egyptian, the Perſian, the Grecian, and the Roman Monarchs, the Renowned <hi>Ceſars, Julius</hi> and <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> celebrated in Hiſtory for War and Peace? Where are the Egyptian <hi>Ptolomies,</hi> the Syrian <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi>'s, the Theban <hi>Labacides</hi>'s, the famous <hi>Conſtantines,</hi> the pious <hi>Theodoſiis</hi>'s, and all thoſe Religious and Valiant Kings that have filled the Brittiſh Throne, and awfully ſway'd the Scepter of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:51925:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>this Kingdom in their ſeveral Ages, from <hi>William</hi> the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, to <hi>William</hi> our glorious Deliverer? all that remains of them is an imperfect Hiſtorical account of all their Vertues and Heroick Acts recorded in our Engliſh Annals.</p>
            <p>What is become of thoſe wiſe and experienced Generals, <hi>Joſhua, Othniel, Ehud, Barak, Gideon, &amp;c. Achilles, Hannibal, &amp;c.</hi> whoſe noble Exploits we read of in the Book of <hi>Judges,</hi> in <hi>Joſephus</hi>'s Hiſtory, and in <hi>Plutarch</hi>'s Lives? they have all been conquered by the King of Terrors.</p>
            <p>Where are now the Seven Angels of the Aſiatick Churches, the Biſhops of <hi>Epheſus, Smyrna, Pergamos, Thyatira, Sardis, &amp;c.</hi> where Chriſtianity was once in its zenith, and flouriſhed moſt gloriouſly? What is become of thoſe extraordinary Lights of the African Churches, <hi>Panaenus, Clemens Alex: Origen, &amp;c.</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably furniſhed with divine and human learning? as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the reſt of the Fathers of the Greek and Latin Churches, <hi>Irenaeus, Tertul. Chryſ. Auguſt. Jerom.</hi> and multitudes more who enlightned the World with the knowledge of divine things, and ſhined as lights in their lives and converſations? Theſe are all extinct in the Duſt and mouldred to Atoms: as are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo thoſe Triple Mitred Popes, that from the time of <hi>Gregorius Magnus</hi> (the laſt of the good, and firſt of the bad) to this day, have filled the Roman Chair, and affected the Title of <hi>Oecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menical Biſhops,</hi> and claimed an exorbitant Power and Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy over the Church of Chriſt, and made <hi>Europe</hi> to tremble with their dreadful Fulminations: But they have all found that there is a Hell for the Unrighteous, and a Heaven for the Juſt, but no Purgatory, ſave that of the Blood of Chriſt <hi>which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth from all ſin.</hi> Theſe are manifeſt proofs that Death is not to be avoided. 'Tis our wiſdom then to prepare for it; for by that means, tho it be formidable to Nature, yet the ſting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is taken away, and we may be rather ſaid to fall aſleep then to die; to ſleep in Jeſus, and go to a bleſſed and glorious immortality.</p>
            <p n="5">v. Holineſs, which is the beſt preparation for Death and Judgment, the nobleſt qualification for Happineſs, is abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary; for none but holy Souls ſhall ſtand with comfort before the Judgment Seat of Chriſt: only they that have walked uprightly, and wrought righteouſneſs, ſhall ſtand in
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:51925:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>God's preſence.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 15.1, 2.24.3, 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>Who ſhall aſcend into the hill of the Lord, who ſhall ſtand in his holy place? he that hath clean hands, and a pure heart;</hi> (whoſe life and actions are holy and unblamable,) <hi>who hath not lift up his eyes to vanity, nor ſworn deceitfully; he ſhall receive the bleſſing from the Lord,</hi> Grace and Glory; and all other good things which are promiſed to them that walk uprightly; <hi>and Righteouſneſs,</hi> together with the bleſſed fruits and rewards of it, and thoſe benefits which flow from it, <hi>from the God of his ſalvation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.8.</note> Our Saviour pronounceth Holy Men bleſſed; <hi>Bleſſed are the pure in heart;</hi> who are they? who can ſay I have made my heart clean, I am pure from my ſin? The very beſt of Chriſtians are not able to ſay ſincerely and truly, that they are free from all guilt and pollution of ſin in heart and life. Such only then come under this denomination, who being purified from all filthineſs in the precious Blood of Chriſt, are of a ſincere and upright heart and converſation: though they be not legally pure and free from all ſin, yet the bent of their heart is after holyneſs; or to ſpeak in the words of a Reverend Divine upon this Beatitude,
<note place="margin">Mr. Norris.</note> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">They are ſuch as relate not only to the external conduct of their lives, but alſo the inward frame and habitude of their mind, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form not only their actions but their wills and deſires, thoughts and affections to the rule of the divine Law, and to the dictates of the internal light of God in the Soul. Such as ſanctifie the Lord in their hearts, and compoſe the inward receſſes of their Souls into an awe and reverence of the Divine Preſence, ſet a law to their intellectual powers, and ſuffer not the leaſt thought or paſſion to violate the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der either of Reaſon or Grace.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Such holy Souls as theſe ſhall have the happineſs <hi>to ſee God</hi> in the Beatifical Viſion of him in Glory. They have an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect view of him in his Creatures, and in his Ordinances. <hi>They now ſee</hi> (as St.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) <hi>through a Glaſs darkly,</hi> but hereafter they ſhall ſee him <hi>face to face;</hi> and be abundantly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with his preſence and glory to all eternity; and their joy ſhall no man take from them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.22. neither ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny be ſharers with them in it but ſuch only as are qualified for heaven by univerſal holineſs;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.27.</note> 
               <hi>for there ſhall in no wiſe enter into it any thing that defileth it:</hi> no cloſe Hypocrite, no ſcandalous
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:51925:41"/>Sinner, no unclean perſon that hath not by a holy life ſeparat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf from all ſin and wickedneſs, and dedicated himſelf to God, ſhall enter into that holy place:
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>Know you not that the unrighteous ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God? Be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, neither Fornicators, nor Idolators, nor Adulterers, nor effeminate perſons, nor abuſers of themſelves with mankind, nor Thieves, nor Covetous, nor Drunkards, nor Extortioners,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19.</note> nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſinners that are guilty of <hi>the works of the fleſh,</hi> ſhall without ſincere repentance <hi>enter into the Kingdom of God; of which I tell you before,</hi> (before the day of Death and Judgment come, when you will experimentally find what is here ſaid to be true,)
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph</hi> 5.5. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.6.</note> That no ſuch workers of Iniquity <hi>ſhall have any inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance in the Kingdom of Chriſt and of God.</hi> But ſuppoſe they ſhould be admitted into that bleſſed place, they would there find nothing that would be grateful to them: For the joys of Heaven are all pure and ſpiritual, and upon that account can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly afford any ſatisfaction to their carnal minds. The immaterial felicities of the upper world agree not at all to their ſenſual deſires, neither would they find any complacency in thoſe pure and refined delights, becauſe there is no ſuitableneſs in them to their conſtitutions and inclinations, which are who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bent to the groſs and tranſient ſatisfactions of this world, which periſh in the uſing, like crackling of Thorns under a Pot, that make a blaze for a little while and then ſuddenly vaniſh away. All the Beatitudes of Heaven, both in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and degree, are congruous only to the diſpoſitions of the Saints, and ſuitable to their natures, to the divine principle of purity communicated to them by God; they are not at all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the minds of wicked men: and it is as unreaſonable to think that ſuch men can enter into heaven without vertuous habits and holy diſpoſitions, and divine graces, as to think that a Lamp can burn without Oyl to maintain the flame. Heav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en is the habitation of the Holy God, of ſpotleſs Angels, and glorified Souls; 'tis the Region of the pureſt Vertue, and the moſt perfect Holineſs. If ever therefore we deſire to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, and to enjoy God in that blifsful place, we muſt make it our chiefeſt buſineſs <hi>to purifie our ſelves even as he is pure;</hi> for there is no enjoying him, but by becoming like him;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14.</note> 
               <hi>without holineſs no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi> We can have no union to,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:51925:42"/>no communion with, or enjoyment of God, either in Grace or Glory, without Holyneſs; that we may therefore be ready to meet our Lord, we muſt <hi>follow, i. e.</hi> vigorouſly purſue <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.22. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>Faith, Charity, Peace, and that which is good: for ſo an entrance ſhall be adminiſtred unto us abundantly into the everlaſting Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Having thus ſhewed wherein this preparation and readineſs for Death and Judgment doth conſiſt, and alſo manifeſted the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſible neceſſity of it, I proceed to conſider</p>
            <p n="2">2. The cogent Motive or Argument which our Lord pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds to quicken our zeal and diligence in making our ſelves ready to meet him, in theſe words; <hi>For in ſuch an hour as you think not the Son of Man cometh:</hi> wherein we may obſerve three things to haſten and invigorate our preparations.</p>
            <p n="1">(1) The deſignation of the perſon to whom the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the laſt Judgment is committed, <hi>the Son of Man.</hi> (2) The certainty of his coming, he <hi>cometh.</hi> (3) The aſſignation of the time when he will come; <hi>in ſuch an hour as you think not.</hi> Theſe three things being duely conſidered wil make us very zealous in our preparations for the coming of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">i. The deſignation of the Perſon, to whom the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the laſt Judgment is committed, is a very proper mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to quicken us in this important work; <hi>The Son of Man;</hi> who is no other then the Lord of Glory, who in obedience to his Fathers will, and an ardent deſire of our happineſs, was pleaſed to take upon him our nature, and to be born of a pure Virgin (<hi>Joſeph</hi> being his reputed Father) in whoſe Womb, and of whoſe ſubſtance he was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt; and by a real and proper parturition was born into the world, <hi>in the fulneſs of time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4.</note> and at the very ſeaſon which God had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the redemption of Men, in reſpect whereof he ſtiles himſelf <hi>The Son of Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The original power of Judgment doth certainly belong to God, who hath an abſolute ſovereignty over his Creatures; he as grand Lord of all the world hath intruſted us with vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous gifts and talents; an improvement whereof he will require from us, and exact an account of our obedience. But ſuch is the brightneſs and glory of his Majeſty,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.20.</note> that we poor mortals are unable to behold him. If he ſhould diſplay the Beams of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:51925:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>his glory to us we ſhould certainly be aſtoniſhed and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with his dreadful preſence. It hath therefore pleaſed him to conſtitute the Son of Man to execute that laſt and grand truſt of his Mediatory Office, becauſe he is capable, by reaſon of his human nature which he aſſumed from his Mother, of being viſible to an eye of fleſh; <hi>The father judgeth no man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.22, 27.</note> 
               <hi>but hath committed all judgment unto the Son, and hath given him authority to execute judgment, becauſe he is the Son of Man.</hi> This Doctrine of his ſecond coming, our Saviour before his aſcenſion into Heaven, gave in ſtrict charge to his Apoſtles principally and publickly to preach unto the People;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 10.42.</note> 
               <hi>That it was he which was ordained of God to be judg of the quick and dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To him the Father delegated his power, and commiſſioned him to be his Agent in performing this great work.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ch.</hi> 17.31.</note> 
               <hi>He hath appointed a day in the which he will judge the world with righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, by a man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14.</note> (that peculiar man mentioned in <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Viſion) <hi>whom he hath ordained and confirmed</hi> under the broad Seal of Heaven, <hi>John</hi> 6.27. <hi>to judg the world.</hi> The Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſhall deſcend from heaven, the Mediator between God and Man ſhall come in his own perſon, and not by a repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive; every eye ſhall ſee him: tho to agrandize his Advent, all the holy Angels ſhall attend him,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhall be revealed from heaven with his mighty Angels in flaming fire, to take vengeance of them that know not God, and that obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus.</hi> Now if the Judg be appointed, and that <hi>the Son of Man</hi> is the perſon to whom the office of executing judgment is conſigned; that the Divine Goodneſs hath committed it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his hands, who hath taken upon him our nature, hath born our griefs, hath felt our infirmities, and undergon thoſe cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſements by which our peace of reconciliation with God, our ſalvation and happineſs were purchaſed and effected. The conſideration hereof ſhould deeply engage us to make our ſelves ready to meet our Sovereign Lord: For what can we wiſh more in our own favour than this? that he ſhall be our Judg, who hath been touched with a fellow feeling of our miſeries, and can have compaſſion of our infirmities. For his coming we ſhould be always ready, becauſe none but ſuch as are in a prepared ſtate ſhall pertake of the joys which God hath laid up for thoſe that love him.</p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:51925:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="2">ii. It is certain that the Son of Man <hi>will</hi> come; he is about it, upon the point of coming. As for thoſe perſons that have the impudence and impiety to redicule and deride this funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Article of our Chriſtian Faith; they are generally ſuch as deny the Being and Providence of God, the immortality of the Soul, and future rewards and puniſhments. Men of Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtical principles and diſſolute lives, whoſe intereſt it is that this Doctrine ſhould not be true, becauſe it lays a great reſtraint upon their Luſts; and fills them with fears and terrors, and dreadful expectation of fiery wrath and indignation, which ſhall be their portion, if in the end they ſhould prove miſtak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en; but their judgment is not to be relied upon againſt the conſentient belief of men of all Ages and Nations to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; for not only the Greeks and Romans, (perſons among whom Arts and Sciences, Learning and Policy have been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved to a conſiderable degree) but alſo the rude and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous people, among whom little of Policy, or Religion, or good Manners are to be met with, have been of this perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <q rend="margQuotes">That the Soul is immortal and deſtined to a future life, in joy or miſery, according to its demerits in this life, and that there ſhall paſs future ſcrutinies after death upon the actions of this life.</q> That there are places of reſt and pleaſure provided for good men. Some Paradyſical Gardens, and Elizian Fields, where they ſhall partake of purer joys, and ſweeter delights, then the fineſt ſenſitive pleaſures.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, that black and diſmal Regions are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for wicked men, <hi>ubi fera regnat Erinnys,</hi> where they ſhall be tormented by infernal Furies, frightful Officers, and grim Judges, and dreadful puniſhments, ſuch as <hi>Ixion</hi> and <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> ſuffered, who are ſaid to have a Vulture perpetually gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Vitals. But ſuppoſe that this ſort of men were wiſer then all the world beſides, yet it is a great piece of rudeneſs and incivility to maintain a Poſition contrary to the ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of all mankind: and their deriding the Doctrine of Chriſts Advent, and ſcurrilouſly ſporting with that which we account an eſſential principle of the Chriſtian Religion, is a clear agument of the truth and verity of it, and of the near approach of his coming. So St. <hi>Peter</hi> affirms, that there ſhall come in the <hi>laſt days,</hi> (a little before the Son of Man appeareth)
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:51925:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Scoffers walking after their own luſts, and ſaying,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>where is the promiſe of his coming; for ſince the Fathers fell aſleep, all things continue as they were from the Creation.</hi> They obſerved no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernible change or alteration, ſaving that men die, and others ſucceed in their room, and ſo for ought they know, may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue for ever. In the following verſes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 8.9.</note> he reflects their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, and ſhews that <hi>a thouſand years</hi> (which by a Synec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doche, may be put for the longeſt revolution of time), is with an infinite and eternal God, but <hi>as one day:</hi> who, tho he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts his promiſe, hath not changed his purpoſe, but will ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill it; and his forbearing to do it, is out of abundance of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and long-ſuffering to Sinners, as alſo for the tender love he bears to his Spouſe <hi>the Church,</hi> which is a Body made up of collective parts, and by degrees; <hi>in fluxu</hi> &amp; <hi>corpore tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> as <hi>Tertul.</hi> ſaith, in every Age and Generation there being more or leſs to be gathered into Chriſt's Sheepfold, which ſhall obtain Salvation; and tho there are ſtrifes and contentions, diviſions and ſchiſms within the Church's Boſom, which break her peace and unity, by a voluntary receſſion of ſome of her members from her Communion, upon the account of ſtricter Purity,
<note place="margin">Vid. The Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>op of Worce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nableneſs of Separation.</note> which was the Plea <hi>of Parmenian</hi> and <hi>Petilian</hi> in the laſt Conference at <hi>Carthage, of Feliciſſimus</hi> and his Brethren for their ſeparation from St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and <hi>of</hi> the Meletians, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciferians, and Donatiſts in general; Tho there be heretical O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions and erroneous Doctrines, which externally oppoſe the ſound fundamental Principles of Chriſtian Religion, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine the Faith of Chriſt in ſome one or more eſſential Branches of it; yet theſe things muſt be,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19</note> 
               <hi>that they which are approved may be made manifeſt:</hi> and that others who are now in being, or yet unborn, may in ſucceſſion of time be added to the Church, and by Faith and Repentance obtain Salvation; for this reaſon, <hi>that the ſeed of Chriſtians,</hi> that the numbers of Believers may be compleated, the conflagration of the world is protracted, and the great Judge delays his coming; but for this, he will moſt certainly perform his word. We have the higheſt teſtimony that can be given to confirm us in the belief of this Article of our Faith, <hi>viz.</hi> of good men, who ſpake by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt, of bleſſed and glorious Angels, of God, and Chriſt himſelf, who at his Aſcenſion into Heaven,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:51925:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>gave his diſconſolate Apoſtles an aſſured promiſe that he would come again.</p>
            <p>We have the teſtimony of good men, who ſpake as they were inſpired. God was pleaſed in former times to reveal his mind unto his Prophets by ſundry degrees and parcels, and in divers forms and manners of Revelation. To the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> he communicated this great truth in a viſion by night, to whom this great Aſſize was repreſented after the manner of the great Synedrion or Conſiſtory of <hi>Iſrael;</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. Mr. Mede's Anſwer to Dr. Meddus.</note> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Wherein the Pater Judicii had his Aſſeſſors (as afterwards</hi> Conſtantine <hi>the Great had in the Synod of</hi> Nice) <hi>ſitting ſemi-circle wiſe before him, from his right hand to his left.</hi>
               </q>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.10, 13, 14.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>He beheld till the Thrones were pitched down,</hi> for the Senators to ſit upon, <hi>and the Ancient of Days (Pater Conſiſtorii,</hi> who is the King and Judge of all; ſo called, becauſe of his eternal Deity, which is without begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of time, or end of days) <hi>did ſit, whoſe Garment was white as Snow, and the hair of his Head like pure Wooll, his Throne was like the fiery Flames; a fiery ſtream iſſued, and came forth from before him</hi> (Words denoting his Majeſty and Righteouſneſs in Judgment, and his Juſtice in giving Sentence) <hi>thouſand thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands miniſtred unto him, and ten thouſand times ten thouſand ſtood before him; and the Books, viz.</hi> of Conſcience, and of God's eternal Decree <hi>were opened, and behold, one like the Son of man came with the Clouds of Heaven, &amp;c.</hi>
               </q> a very lively deſcription of Chriſt's Advent; for it well agrees with what the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts have ſaid of it in the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>To this may be added <hi>Job</hi>'s evidence concerning it; he was a good man, and had his hopes fixed above the felicity of this world; his Faith mounted aloft in the ſerious meditation of a Redeemer, and in the premeditation of his coming to Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 19.25, 26.</note> 
               <hi>I know that my Redeemer liveth, and that he ſhall ſtand at the latter day upon the Earth.</hi> It was an Article of this holy Patriarch's Faith, that at the end of the World, the day of the general Reſurrection and Judgment, Jeſus Chriſt ſhould appear in perſon on Earth, and raiſe up his people, and vindicate them from all the injuries and reproaches which are now caſt upon them, and bring them to glory; and that the Judge ſhould be <hi>viſible,</hi> he affirms in the following words, <hi>In my fleſh ſhall I ſee God:</hi> In this numerical body, which is now full of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:51925:44"/>ſores and ulcers; in this putrid, rotten fleſh, which is now in a great meaſure waſted and conſumed, and ſhall certainly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a prey to worms, and put on rottenneſs and corruption; in this ſame body (which ſhall be raiſed from the Grave by the mighty power of God, and be re-united to my ſoul), with theſe ſame eyes which I now have, ſhall I ſee my Redeemer, <hi>whom I ſhall ſee for my ſelf,</hi> and not by a deputy or proxy, but in my own perſon, for my own comfort and benefit, and to my own infinite happineſs and ſatisfaction. <hi>Mine eyes ſhall behold him, and not another.</hi> With theſe organs of light ſhall I ſee the Judge in his own proper perſon, and not in any repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative of him.</p>
            <p>This was an early Doctrin in the Church of God, and ought for the great antiquity thereof to be believed and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced; for it is as old as <hi>Enoch,</hi> the ſeventh Patriarch in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent of the Churches line from <hi>Adam;</hi> a very good man, who was the great Inſtance of Piety and Vertue in a corrupt Age: and for his extraordinary obedience, received an unuſual reward, <hi>viz.</hi> a bodily change, from a mortal and corruptible, to an immortal and incorruptible ſtate, without any ſeparation of his ſoul from his body; <hi>Being tranſlated,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.5.</note> 
               <hi>that he ſhould not ſee death.</hi> This righteous perſon hath given in his ſuffrage to this Doctrin, <hi>ſaying. Behold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jude, v.</hi> 14.15.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord cometh with ten thouſand of his Saints, to execute judgment upon all.</hi> But, foraſmuch as guilty Criminals endeavour to baniſh the thoughts of the Judges coming out of their minds, this great Article of the Chriſtian Religion, had need of all the ſtrength of evidence that can be given it. Therefore we have in the ſecond place,</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) The infallible teſtimony of pure and ſpotleſs Angels, that are confirmed in holineſs and goodneſs. Two of thoſe bleſſed Spirits, who deſcended from Heaven to attend upon our Saviour's glorious and triumphant Aſcenſion into Heaven, told his Diſciples (who waited on their Lord to the top of <hi>Mount Olivet,</hi> and there ſaw him taken up, and received out of their ſight by a Cloud) that his going away from them was not a final departure, but only for a time, and with a full pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of returning again. <hi>While they ſtedfaſtly looked toward Heaven,</hi> (earneſtly obſerving him) <hi>as he went up,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 1.10, 11</note> 
               <hi>behold two
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:51925:45"/>men ſtood by him in white Apparel, i. e.</hi> Two Angels appeared to them in the ſhape of men in a ſhining glorious Attire, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 28.3.</note> Angels are wont to do, to ſignify that they retain their native purity, and to repreſent the joyfulneſs of the meſſage they are uſually ſent upon. Indeed, Joy had never ſo great reaſon to break forth reduntantly, as at our Lord's Aſcenſion into Heaven. Theſe Angelical Meſſengers rouzed the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples out of the extatical Trance they were in, at that glorious ſight, and ſaid unto them; <hi>This ſame Jeſus which is taken up from you into Heaven, ſhall ſo come in like manner, as ye have ſeen him go into Heaven:</hi> He ſhall certainly come to judge the World, in as glorious a manner as he left it. When he depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the World, he was received up into Heaven by An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels; and when he ſhall come again, he ſhall be attended with his <hi>Satellites</hi> and Officers of State and Royalty, myriads, and legions of Angels. Then a Cloud more than ordinarily bright and reſplendent carried him out of his Apoſtles ſight; at his ſecond coming the innumerable Inhabitants of the whole World, all that ever deſcended out of the loins of <hi>Adam, ſhall ſee him coming in the Clouds with great power and glory.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 13.26. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16.</note> He ſhall certainly and infallibly deſcend from Heaven, and the bodies of all the righteous and good men that ever lived, <hi>ſhall riſe firſt;</hi> and then all <hi>that are alive on Earth, and remain, ſhall be caught up together with them</hi> (either by ſome immediate and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive power of Chriſt, or by the Arms of Angels) <hi>into the Clouds to meet the Lord in the Air,</hi> where this great Aſſize ſhall be held, as being moſt convenient both for the capacity of the place, and the more eminent viſibility of the Judge and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors; whom all the wicked ſhall behold with terror and aſtoniſhment,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jude, v.</hi> 15.</note> and then and there be ſo fully <hi>convinced of all their ungodly deeds, which they have ungodly committed, and of all their hard ſpeeches which they have ſpoken,</hi> That they ſhall accuſe themſelves as <hi>Apollodore</hi> did in a dream, fancying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be in a Cauldron of boyling Lead: <hi>I am the cauſe of this Vengeance:</hi> our deſtruction is from our ſelves, we are the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of this miſery; <hi>For we hated inſtruction, and our hearts deſpiſed reproof, and obeyed not the voice of our Teachers, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined our ears to them that inſtructed us.</hi> We regarded not the ſeaſonable and tender admonitions of our Parents, Friends and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:51925:45"/>Miniſters, who warned us to flee from the wrath to come. Theſe hardned, reprobate Sinners, ſhall now tremble to ſee and hear the ſeverity and righteouſneſs of the judicial proceedings, and more eſpecially at their own final doom and ſentence to everlaſting Burnings; whilſt the Righteous are adjudged to life eternal, to enjoy the ſweet and comfortable preſence of Chriſt for evermore. This is the teſtimony of Angelical Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes: Now if we receive the witneſs of Angels,</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) The witneſs of God the Father, and the aſſured pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of God the Son is greater, and we have both theſe to confirm this Truth.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) The witneſs of God the Father, who hath aſſured us that <hi>he will bring every work into judgment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.14.</note> 
               <hi>with every ſecret thing, whether it be good, or whether it be evil.</hi> He will execute Juſtice and Mercy, in retributing men according to their deeds: But he will tranſact this great work by the Son, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16. to whom he hath committed his power, <hi>John</hi> 5.22. And he is the faithful God, who hath never yet failed in the performance of one tittle of his word or promiſe to his people; and he will not be deficient in this. He hath appointed the day of Judgment, and hath ordained the perſon of the Judge; he hath given <hi>aſſurance,</hi> publick and evident demonſtration <hi>unto all men, in that he hath raiſed him from the dead.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 17.31.</note> His Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection is a ſound Argument of God's ſetting his Seal to his Commiſſion; of his Conſtituting and Confirming him Oecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menical Judge of all the World. To it, our Lord, when he was upon Earth, appealed, as the great proof that he ſhall come again to execute that judicial Office, and by it, that is, the reſurrection from the dead, he is declared to be the Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent Son of God, to whom all Power was given by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) The aſſured promiſe of God the Son. In the laſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon which our Saviour Preached to his beloved Diſciples, he told them that the time of his departure was at hand, and gave them his laſt advice, and dying charge: A new Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment give I unto you, that ye love one another. They were very much troubled to hear of parting with their deareſt Lord, who had reſolved all their doubts, ſatisfied their ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, inſtructed their ignorance, and upon all occaſions moſt
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:51925:46"/>ſweetly communicated to them his heavenly doctrin, and holy comforts. It was very afflictive to them to underſtand from his own mouth, that he was about to leave them; whereupon he adviſeth them not to be diſcouraged at it:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 14.1.</note> 
               <hi>Let not your hearts be troubled, nor be afraid.</hi> He was but returning home, and going to his Father's Houſe: the end of his going was to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare manſions of Glory for them, and for all his faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; and he promiſeth to come again, and make them par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of his Glory.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>V.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>If I go and prepare a place for you, I will come again, and receive you unto my ſelf, that where I am, there ye may be alſo.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.11.</note> Faithful <hi>is he that hath promiſed, who alſo will do it:</hi> He will not fail the performing of his promiſe, nor his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples expectations. <hi>He that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the certainty and full aſſurance of his coming being thus eſtabliſhed by the plain evidence of God, Angels and Men; ſhould breed in us a moſt attentive and accurate regard to every thing that we ſay or do; ſhould make us very ſerious in our thoughts, words and works; ſhould mightily reſtrain us from vice, and quicken us to vertue; and beget in us a care and conſcience in all our actions, becauſe we muſt undergo a ſevere trial; upon the iſſue whereof depends our everlaſting woe, or endleſs felicity. We ſhall be guilty of the greateſt unfaithfulneſs, of the baſeſt treachery to our precious ſouls, if we do not provide for that great account, and prepare for the coming of our Lord, and patiently expect his appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
            <p n="3">iii. I proceed in the laſt place to conſider the uncertainty of the time when our Lord will come: <hi>In ſuch an hour as ye think not.</hi> The Wiſdom of God hath thought fit to keep ſecret the particular time of the Judges coming, that we might not ſpend our thoughts upon it, nor out of curioſity enquire into it. He hath not revealed it to the holy Angels, and therefore it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be expected that he ſhould communicate it to any of the Sons of men, becauſe it is not at all neceſſary that they ſhould know it, but believe it, and walk by Faith and Works, and labour in the Vineyard till the Son of man cometh: <hi>Of that day and hour knoweth no man;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 13.32, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>no, not the Angels which are in Heaven; neither the Son</hi> (as man only) <hi>but the Father. Take
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:51925:46"/>ye heed, watch and pray; for ye know not when the time is, &amp;c. Verſes</hi> 35, 36. When ever he cometh,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.3.</note> it will be by way of ſurprize to many. So he told the Church of <hi>Sardis; If thou wilt not watch, I will come on thee as a Thief, and thou ſhalt not know when I will come upon thee.</hi> The Thief comes when the Maſter of the Houſe leaſt expects him, in the dead and ſolitary time of the night, when all the Inhabitants are aſleep: Such will be the coming of the Son of Man; who (a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Text) repreſents it by the coming of the great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge in the days of <hi>Noah;</hi> or, as the Fire and Brimſtone came upon the Cities of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gemorrah;</hi> as Thro's and Pangs come upon a Woman with Child. <hi>As a Snare ſhall it come upon all that dwell upon the face of the Earth.</hi> Now when a Fowler layeth a Snare to take a Bird, he gives no warning, but ſurprizeth it ſuddenly: even ſo will the Judge of all the world come upon the generality of men, when they promiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves peace and ſecurity, and walk at eaſe, and think of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but plenty and pleaſure; of laying Houſe to Houſe, and Field to Field; of Manſions and Manors; of reigning as Kings on the Earth, and of Lording it over their fellow ſervants. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, the Judge ſtandeth at the door ready to ſurprize them when they are moſt ſecure. And this may be our caſe, if we keep not up our watch.</p>
            <p>If therefore the Kingdom of Heaven be worth ſecuring, and the ſalvation of your ſouls be dear and precious to you, 'tis both your wiſdom and your intereſt, ſpeedily, and without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays, to ſet upon this neceſſary and glorious work: For it is no eaſy matter to obtain Heaven and Happineſs, neither is it the work of a few ſpare minutes to ſhake off evil habits, and to attire the Soul with divine Graces and Vertues, that it may appear without ſpot or wrinkle in the Bridegrooms preſence. Be not deceived, it is not a few penitential tears in the time of Sickneſs, and laſt Viſitation, that can purge the ſoul from the pollution of Sin, which it hath been contracting many years; or change its temper, and in a moment put it into a readineſs for a future ſtate. It is not ſafe for us to run ſo great a hazard; we are not ſure that we ſhall dye deliberately, and by ſlow de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees. But ſuppoſe that a fore going Sickneſs ſhould by little and little weaken the powers of Nature, the Devil will then be
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:51925:47"/>very buſy in tempting us, and the Fleſh unable to bear the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of Sickneſs, and ſink under the groans of expiring Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. If we have then our great work to do, our Oyl to get, and our Lamps to trim when the Bridegroom comes, the door will be ſhut upon us, and we ſhall bewail to all eternity the folly of ſlipping a ſeaſon which can never be regained.</p>
            <p>Let me therefore beſpeak you (dear Chriſtians) in words of love and tenderneſs; and beſeech you by all the obligations that your holy profeſſion lays upon you, by all the kindneſs which you bear to your immortal ſouls, and the deſire which you have to be eternally happy; ſeriouſly to prepare to meet your Lord. Go hence from the Houſe of God, with fixed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, from this time forth, to <hi>depart from all iniquity, and to live righteouſly, ſoberly, and godly in this preſent World, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the glorious appearance of the great God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall change our vile body, that it may be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioned like unto his glorious body, according to the mighty work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whereby he is able to ſubdue all things to himſelf.</hi> To whom, with the Father, and Holy Spirit, three Perſons, but one Eternal God, be Glory, Honour and Power, now and for ever.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The CHARACTER.</head>
               <p>I Have now performed my duty to the <hi>Living,</hi> by ſhewing them both generally, and particularly, that a good life is the beſt preparation for Eternity; and that the way to dye hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily, is to live holily. It remains, that I do now, in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure diſcharge my reſpects to the <hi>Dead,</hi> whoſe memory will be precious among all good Chriſtians, for his many perſonal Excellencies, and uſefulneſs in his Generation.</p>
               <p>'Tis a ſad and mournful occaſion that we are met upon, to Solemnize the Funeral Rites and Obſequies of ſo dear a Friend and Relation: But this is our comfort, that his whole life was an excellent Comment upon this Text; for tho his Viſitation was ſhort (as for the moſt part is uſual in ſuch Apoplectical Diſtempers as carried him off) and his Death ſudden and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing to us, from whom he was ſnatched away in a little time: yet it could not be ſo to him, who by the infirmities of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:51925:47"/>a crazy body, and by many ſenſible decays of Nature, was put in mind of his approaching change; and no doubt but his preparations for Eternity were anſwerable to his frequent and almoſt daily warnings: For as in his youthful days he was (by the mercy of God, a well diſpoſed Nature, and a vertuous Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation) preſerved from all groſs Sins and Vices; ſo in his riper years he lived a life of ſtrict Vertue.</p>
               <p>I am no great Favourer of Funeral Elogies, becauſe they look like mercenary Flattery, if there be not ſome extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary merit to lay a juſt foundation for them: but the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ought to be had in perpetual remembrance, and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of the Juſt ſhall be praiſed. 'Tis <hi>juſtice to give every man his due</hi> praiſe, and to commend thoſe whoſe vertuous lives are bright and illuſtrious to others; and it is kindneſs to the living to hold before their eyes a ſhining light, a glorious pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of Vertue to guide and direct them to walk in the paths of Holineſs and Peace, and to beget in them the like Goodneſs and Charity. Thus our deceaſed Friend in his life and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice did ſhine as a burning Lamp, and adorn'd his holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion by a good Converſation.</p>
               <p>His divine Soul was inflamed with a fervent love and zeal for God, and poſſeſſed with a holy fear and awe of his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Majeſty, whom he ſerved with Reverence and filial Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. His Piety did conſiſt more in the vital and ſubſtantial parts of Religion, than in Circumſtantials. He had a ſincere love for the Preaching of the Word, which he waited upon with diligence; to the end, that he might learn his duty, and grow in grace, and in the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt; whom to know, and in whom to believe, is life eternal. His atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon the Word was with conſtancy, if his infirm body would give him leave; and he heard it with reverence, as the word of Life and Salvation. Great was his regard for the Lord's Day, not only to keep it holy himſelf, but to ſee that his whole Family did ſtrictly obſerve and ſanctify it; not only by reſting from their worldly labours, and putting on finer Clothes, &amp;c. but by performing religious Exerciſes, and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the preſent Vacation from the works of their Callings, unto a more diligent attendance on God in the publick and private Duties of Religion, and in the ſpiritual concernments of their Souls.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:51925:48"/>
               <p>The Government of his Family was very decent and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, his Houſe was an Oratory of Devotion, wherein Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Evening Sacrifice was dayly offered to God, and ſome portion of Holy Scripture was read with ſeriouſneſs and devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with love and delight; and Prayer was the beginning and ending of every day: And this I aſſure you is the duty of all Maſters of Families, which they ought to ſee performed in their Families; for the care and charge of Souls is committed to them. There they are Kings to rule, Prophets to teach, and Prieſts to offer up Spiritual Sacrifices for themſelves, and for thoſe under their roof. They, their Children and Servants ought to ſerve the Lord, and their neglect thereof is one chief cauſe of all that Atheiſm and Irreligion which too much abounds in the Age we live in.</p>
               <p>To this may I add his ſecret Devotion in private, which was moſt conſtantly and diligently performed by him, The ſpirit of Religion eminently dwelt in this good man: His De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions were fervent and ſerious; his affections and deſires were in a great meaſure crucified to the world, and all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and pleaſures of it. He was cloathed with Humility as with a Garment, and beautified with the goodly ornament of a calm, meek and quiet Spirit, which in the ſight of God is of great price. His Mind was exquiſitely tender and compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate: His kindneſs and charity truly admirable; for he loved, relieved and aſſiſted all neceſſitous Objects according to his ability. In company he was pleaſant, cheerful and facetious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly witty. His behaviour was modeſt and affable, kind and courteous to all ſorts of people: By the evenneſs of his temper, and ſweet diſpoſition, and friendly deportment, he gained the love and reſpect of good men. His Servants ſpeak him to be a kind reſpective Maſter, and we all know that he was a true Friend, a good Neighbour, a very uſeful and ſerviceable perſon in his Generation; a Patron to ſeveral Fatherleſs Children and Orphans, a true lover of his King and Country; ſober and temperate in every thing; in his Diet, in his Apparel, in his Words and Behaviour; prudent in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of his own and others Affairs wherein he was much employed; a good Houſekeeper according to his degree and ability, and a great ſupport to many indigent and needy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:51925:48"/>In a word, his many vertuous Qualities, and praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Deeds, deſerve to be commemorated and recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to your practice: But he is gone to his unchangeable ſtate. God grant that we who ſurvive may all of us tread in the ſteps of his exemplary Piety and Vertue, of his unwearied di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and patient continuance in well doing. May the Eccho of his Praiſes tend to the ſetting forth of God's Glory; to whom be aſcribed by us and the whole company of his Saints, as is moſt due, eternal praiſes, <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
